{"test_questions": [[{"question": "Which one of the following is incombustible ?", "opta": "H2", "optb": "CCl4", "optc": "C2H2", "optd": "S", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The softness or hardness of a grinding wheel depends upon the type & amount of bonding material used. For general purpose cutter grinding __________ grinding wheel is normally used.", "opta": "hard", "optb": "soft", "optc": "silicon carbide", "optd": "aluminium oxide", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Tin based white metals are used, where bearings are subjected to", "opta": "high pressure & load.", "optb": "low pressure & load.", "optc": "high temperature.", "optd": "large surface wear.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Friction factor for fluid flow in pipe does not depend upon the", "opta": "pipe length.", "optb": "pipe roughness.", "optc": "fluid density & viscosity.", "optd": "mass flow rate of fluid.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "All of the following alloying elements of steel increases hardness but sacrifice ductility, except", "opta": "nickel", "optb": "vanadium", "optc": "molybdenum", "optd": "chromium", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The following type of bonding is strongly directional in solids.", "opta": "Vander Waal's", "optb": "Ionic", "optc": "Metallic", "optd": "Covalant", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fog is an example of colloidal system of", "opta": "solid dispersed in gas.", "optb": "solid dispersed in liquid.", "optc": "liquid dispersed in gas.", "optd": "gas dispersed in liquid.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Chromium molybdenum steel can not be welded using __________ welding.", "opta": "thermit", "optb": "electrical resistance", "optc": "oxy-acetylene", "optd": "any of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Speisses is a mixture of the following:", "opta": "Arsenides of heavy metals.", "optb": "Antimonides of heavy metals.", "optc": "Arsenides & antimonides of heavy metals.", "optd": "Iron, cobalt and nickel.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Auto collimator is used to check", "opta": "flatness", "optb": "angle", "optc": "rotor balancing", "optd": "roughness", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In troposphere (the weather domain), the temperature 't' at height 'h' above the sea level in metres is given by (where, temperature at sea level is 15\u00b0C and t is in \u00b0C.)", "opta": "t = 15 - 0.0065 h", "optb": "t = 15 + 0.0065 h", "optc": "t = 0.0035 h - 15", "optd": "t = 15 - 0.0035 h", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A high pressure boiler generates steam at a pressure greater than __________ kg/cm2 .", "opta": "10", "optb": "30", "optc": "50", "optd": "80", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Evaporative cooling process employs a combination of cooling and humidification in which the", "opta": "sensible heat is added.", "optb": "sensible heat is removed and the latent heat is added.", "optc": "latent heat is removed.", "optd": "sensible heat is added and latent heat is removed.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not an explosive ?", "opta": "TNT", "optb": "CMC", "optc": "RDX", "optd": "Lead azide", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Maxwell's thermodynamic relations applies to the", "opta": "chemical systems in equilibrium.", "optb": "mechanical systems in equilibrium.", "optc": "irreversible thermodynamic processes.", "optd": "reversible thermodynamic processes.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Annealing ofwhite cast iron produces __________ iron.", "opta": "grey", "optb": "nodular", "optc": "malleable", "optd": "spheroidal", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Resistance of an electrical conductor is proportional to its (where, l = length and A = cross-sectional area of the conductor)", "opta": "A", "optb": "l", "optc": "A2", "optd": "both 'a' & 'b'", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A solar cell converts the sunlight directly into __________ energy.", "opta": "thermal", "optb": "electrical", "optc": "mechanical", "optd": "chemical", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If a nuclear reactor produces more fissile nuclear fuel than it consumes, then it is called a __________ reactor.", "opta": "critical", "optb": "breeder", "optc": "fertile", "optd": "heterogenous", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Wrought iron is never shaped by", "opta": "casting", "optb": "cold working", "optc": "forging", "optd": "welding", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Powder metallurgy process does not make metal powder by", "opta": "atomisation", "optb": "grinding/milling", "optc": "hammering", "optd": "electrolytic deposition", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the blast furnace, incorporation of water vapour in the blast gives the following effect.", "opta": "Increases the reducing potential of the gas.", "optb": "Increases the flame temperature.", "optc": "No significant change occurs.", "optd": "Increases the hydrogen content in the metal.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "A ferromagnetic material becomes paramagnetic above the 'Curie temperature'.", "optb": "Permanent magnets are made of hard materials, whereas electromagnets require soft magnetic materials.", "optc": "Soft magnetic materials (e.g., pure iron) have higher permeability and low hysterisis loss and coercive forces.", "optd": "Tungsten steel and alnico are not hard magnetic materials.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The usual energy consumption in electric arc furnace steel making is __________ KWh/ton of steel.", "opta": "60 - 100", "optb": "400 - 700", "optc": "1200 -1500", "optd": "2000 - 2300", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Maximum permissible air velocity in pipelines is about __________ metre/second.", "opta": "5", "optb": "10", "optc": "20", "optd": "40", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Area under the stress-strain curve upto the __________ is referred to as the modulus of resilience.", "opta": "yield strength", "optb": "elastic limit", "optc": "proportional limit", "optd": "maximum point", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "__________ is the hardest oxide and is hence used where high wear resistance at high temperature is required.", "opta": "Beryllia", "optb": "Zirconia", "optc": "Alumina", "optd": "Magnesia", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Titanium alloys are welded using the Following process:", "opta": "TIG welding.", "optb": "Submerged arc welding.", "optc": "Butt welding.", "optd": "Electron beam welding.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An alloy of Fe - 0.4 % C is", "opta": "cast iron.", "optb": "hypo-eutectoid steel.", "optc": "hyper-eutectoid steel.", "optd": "eutectoid steel", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A material in which the atoms are arranged regularly in some directions but not in others, is termed as 'mesomorphous material'; an example of which is", "opta": "lead", "optb": "glass", "optc": "mica", "optd": "silver", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In extrusion of metals, which of the following statement is true ?", "opta": "speed of the extruded material is same as that of ram speed.", "optb": "Redundant work is a function of the die angle.", "optc": "Relative motion between the billet surface and the container wall is always present.", "optd": "Hollow ram is used for indirect extrusion.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Nuclear fission of one atom of uranium-235 produces the energy equivalent to about __________ MeV.", "opta": "20", "optb": "200", "optc": "500", "optd": "1000", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following parameters is not responsible for the heat loss from a hot steam carrying bare pipe surface located in a room without fans ?", "opta": "Emissivity of pipe surface.", "optb": "Diameter & length of the pipe.", "optc": "Temperature of hot pipe surface & that of air in the room.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Machinability of hard alloys and tool steels is improved by", "opta": "spherodising", "optb": "annealing", "optc": "tempering", "optd": "normalising", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Transformation range for ferrous material is the temperature interval during which __________ is formed during its heating.", "opta": "cementite", "optb": "austenite", "optc": "martensite", "optd": "pearlite", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Maximum amount of thermal radiation is emitted at all wavelengths at any specified temperature by a/an __________ body.", "opta": "grey", "optb": "black", "optc": "opaque", "optd": "white", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In condensers used in thermal power plants, steam is normally used in shell side and cooling water on the tube side, because of the reason that", "opta": "compared to the mass flow rate of cooling water, the rate of condensation of steam is invariably smaller.", "optb": "maintaining vacuum on tube side is more difficult than that on the shell side.", "optc": "water velocity can be increased conveniently to increase the overall heat transfer co-efficient because of its lower specific volume compared to steam.", "optd": "condenser can act as a storage unit for condensed steam.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Cobalt - 60 is used as a source of __________ in medical therapy & industrial radiography.", "opta": "X-rays", "optb": "\u03b3-rays", "optc": "\u03b1-rays", "optd": "\u03b2-rays", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Absolute zero pressure can be attained at a temperature of", "opta": "0\u00b0C", "optb": "50\u00b0K", "optc": "0\u00b0R", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The product out from a cupola is called", "opta": "wrought iron", "optb": "pig iron", "optc": "cast iron", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Nusselt number is related to Grashoff number (Gr) in turbulent & laminar flow respectively, in respect of free convection over a vertical flat plate as", "opta": "Gr0.25, Gr", "optb": "Gr0.25, Gr0.33", "optc": "Gr, Gr0.25", "optd": "Gr0.33, Gr0.25", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the demand for an item is trebled and the order cost is reduced to one third, then the economic order quantity", "opta": "is trebled.", "optb": "remains unchanged.", "optc": "decreases by a factor of 3.", "optd": "decreases by a factor of 1/3.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Copper deposits are found in India at the following location:", "opta": "Kudremukh", "optb": "Kolar", "optc": "Khetri", "optd": "Ramagundam", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Electrical conductivities of semi-conductors are of the order of __________ ohm/cm.", "opta": "10-3", "optb": "103", "optc": "10-15", "optd": "l015", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Corrosion of metals can not be prevented by its", "opta": "tempering", "optb": "chromising", "optc": "aluminising", "optd": "alloying", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Transition from laminar to turbulent zone in free convection heat transfer is governed by the critical value of", "opta": "Grashoff number.", "optb": "Grashoff number & Reynolds number.", "optc": "Reynolds number.", "optd": "Grashoff number & Prandtl number.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The most economical channel section for the fluid flow is the one for which the discharge is maximum for a given cross-sectional area. Vertical velocity distribution in an open channel for laminar flow can be assumed to be", "opta": "parabolic", "optb": "hyperbolic", "optc": "straight line", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Energy of the sun arises mainly from __________ reactions.", "opta": "fusion", "optb": "fission", "optc": "combustion", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following fastening devices has a head at one end and a nut fitted to the other ?", "opta": "Bolt", "optb": "Stud", "optc": "Top bolt", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Sudden fall of atmospheric pressure by a large amount is an indication of the", "opta": "rain", "optb": "cold wave", "optc": "storm", "optd": "fair weather", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Direct costs component of the fixed capital consists of", "opta": "contingencies", "optb": "onsite and offsite costs", "optc": "labour costs", "optd": "raw material costs", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Out of the following, the depreciation calculated by the __________ method is the maximum.", "opta": "diminishing balance", "optb": "straight line", "optc": "sum of the years digit", "optd": "sinking fund", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of working capital to total capital investment for most chemical plants (except for non-seasonal based products) is in the range of __________ percent.", "opta": "0.1 to 1", "optb": "1 to 2", "optc": "10 to 20", "optd": "50 to 60", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Utilities cost in the operation of chemical process plant comes under the", "opta": "plant overhead cost", "optb": "fixed charges", "optc": "direct production cost", "optd": "general expenses", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "The annual depreciation rate for machinery and equipments in a chemical process plant is about 10% of the fixed capital investment.", "optb": "Annual depreciation rate of buildings in a chemical plant is about 3% of its initial cost.", "optc": "Insurance rates on annual basis in a chemical plant may be about 1% of the fixed capital investment.", "optd": "In a chemical industry, research and development cost amounts to about 15% of net sales realisation (NSR).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "__________ method for profitability evaluation of a project does not account for investment cost due to land.", "opta": "Net present worth", "optb": "Pay out period", "optc": "Discounted cash flow", "optd": "Rate of return on investment", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The total investment in a project is Rs. 10 lakhs and the annual profit is 1.5 lakhs. If the project life is 10 years, then the simple rate of return on investment is", "opta": "15%", "optb": "10%", "optc": "1.5%", "optd": "150%", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Nominal and effective interest rates are equal, when the interest is compounded", "opta": "quarterly", "optb": "semi-annually", "optc": "annually", "optd": "in no case, they are equal", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following elements is not included in the scope of market analysis ?", "opta": "Competition from other manufactures.", "optb": "Product distribution.", "optc": "Opportunities", "optd": "Economics", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "__________ of depreciation calculation accounts for the interest on investement.", "opta": "Straight line method", "optb": "Declining balance", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not a component of working capital ?", "opta": "Raw materials is stock.", "optb": "Finished products in stock.", "optc": "Transportation facilities.", "optd": "Semi-finished products in the process.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In declining balance method of depreciation calculation, the", "opta": "value of the asset decreases linearly with time.", "optb": "annual cost of depreciation is same every year.", "optc": "annual depreciation is the fixed percentage of the property value at the beginning of the particular year.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following relationship is not correct is case of a chemical process plant ?", "opta": "Manufacturing cost = direct product cost + fixed charges + plant overhead costs", "optb": "General expenses = administrative expenses + distribution & marketing expenses", "optc": "Total product cost = manufacturing cost + general expenses", "optd": "Total product cost = direct production cost + plant overhead cost.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For a given fluid, as the pipe diameter increases, the pumping cost", "opta": "decreases.", "optb": "increases.", "optc": "remains the same.", "optd": "may increase or decrease, depending upon whether the fluid is Newtonian or non-Newtonian.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In which of the electric power generation system, the operating cost is minimum ?", "opta": "Thermal", "optb": "Nuclear", "optc": "Hydroelectric", "optd": "Fast breeder reactor", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Accumulated sum at the end of 5 years, if Rs. 10000 is invested now at 10% interest per annum on a compound basis is Rs.", "opta": "15000", "optb": "16105", "optc": "18105", "optd": "12500", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Operating profit of a chemical plant is equal to", "opta": "profit before interest and tax i.e., net profit + interest + tax", "optb": "profit after tax plus depreciation", "optc": "net profit + tax", "optd": "profit after tax", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a manufacturing industry, break even point occurs, when the", "opta": "total annual rate of production equals the assigned value.", "optb": "total annual product cost equals the total annual sales.", "optc": "annual profit equals the expected value.", "optd": "annual sales equals the fixed cost.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Gross earning is equal to the total income minus", "opta": "total product cost", "optb": "fixed cost", "optc": "income tax", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The depreciation during the year 'n', in diminishing balance method of depreciation calculation, is calculated by multiplying a fixed percentage 'N' to the", "opta": "initial cost.", "optb": "book value at the end of (n - 1)th year,", "optc": "depreciation during the (n - 1)th year.", "optd": "difference between initial cost and salvage value.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Scheduling provides information about the", "opta": "proper utilisation of machines.", "optb": "means to minimise idle time for machines.", "optc": "time of completion of job.", "optd": "time of starting of job and also about how much work should be completed during a particular period.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The inventory of raw materials included in the working capital is usually about __________ months supply of raw materials valued at delivery prices.", "opta": "one", "optb": "three", "optc": "six", "optd": "twelve", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is the costliest material of construction used in pressure vessel construction ?", "opta": "Low alloy steel", "optb": "Lead", "optc": "Titanium", "optd": "High alloy steel", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Most chemical plants use an initial working capital amounting to 10-20% of the total capital investment. But this percentage may increase to __________ percent in case of seasonal products manufacturing plant.", "opta": "30", "optb": "50", "optc": "75", "optd": "95", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fixed charges for a chemical plant does not include the", "opta": "interest on borrowed money.", "optb": "rent of land and buildings.", "optc": "property tax, insurance and depreciation.", "optd": "repair and maintenance charges.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "'Utilities' in a chemical process plant includes compressed air, steam, water, electrical power, oxygen, acetylene, fuel gases etc. Utility costs for ordinary chemical process plants ranges roughly from __________ percent of the total product cost.", "opta": "l to 5", "optb": "10 to 20", "optc": "25 to 35", "optd": "35 to 45", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The economic life of a large chemical process plant as compared to a small chemical plant is", "opta": "only slightly more", "optb": "much more", "optc": "slightly less", "optd": "almost equal", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Cost of instrumentation in a modern chemical plant ranges from __________ percent of the total plant cost.", "opta": "5 to 10", "optb": "20 to 30", "optc": "40 to 50", "optd": "60 to 70", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "__________ taxes are based on gross earnings.", "opta": "Property", "optb": "Excise", "optc": "Income", "optd": "Capital gain", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "Net worth means paid up share capital and reserve & surplus (i.e. shareholders equity).", "optb": "Return on equity = profit after tax/net worth.", "optc": "Working capital turn over ratio = sales/net working capital.", "optd": "Total cost of production is more than net sales realisation (NSR) at break even point.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the interest rate of 10% per period is compounded half yearly, the actual annual return on the principal will be __________ percent.", "opta": "10", "optb": "20", "optc": ">20", "optd": "< 20", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is a component of working capital investment ?", "opta": "Utilities plants.", "optb": "Maintenance and repair inventory.", "optc": "Process equipments.", "optd": "Depreciation.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "'Six-tenth factor' rule is used for estimating the", "opta": "equipment installation cost.", "optb": "equipment cost by scaling.", "optc": "cost of piping.", "optd": "utilities cost.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Payback period", "opta": "and economic life of a project are the same.", "optb": "is the length of time over which the earnings on a project equals the investment.", "optc": "is affected by the variation in earnings after the recovery of the investment.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In an ordinary chemical plant, electrical installation cost may be about", "opta": "10-15% of purchased equipment cost.", "optb": "3-10% of fixed capital investment.", "optc": "either (a) or (b).", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b).", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "Debt-equity ratio of a chemical company describes the lenders contribution for each rupee of owner's contribution i.e., debt-equity ratio = total debt/net worth.", "optb": "Return on investment (ROI) is the ratio of profit before interest & tax and capital employed (i.e. net worth + total debt).", "optc": "Working capital = current assets + current liability.", "optd": "Turn over = opening stock + production closing stock.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Personnel working in the market research group is reponsible for the job of", "opta": "equipment selection.", "optb": "product evaluation.", "optc": "equipment design.", "optd": "cost estimation.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "\"Break-even point\" is the point of intersection of", "opta": "fixed cost and total cost.", "optb": "total cost and sales revenue.", "optc": "fixed cost and sales revenue.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "'P' is the investment made on an equipment, 'S' is its salvage value and 'n is the life of the equipment in years. The depreciation for rath year by the sum-of years digit method will be", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "Gross revenue is that total amount of capital received as a result of the sale of goods or service.", "optb": "Net revenue is the total profit remaining after deducting all costs excluding taxes.", "optc": "The ratio of immediately available cash to the total current liabilities is known as the cash ratio.", "optd": "Consolidated income statement based on a given time period indicates surplus capital and shows the relationship among total income, costs & profit over the time interval.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The payback method for the measurement of return on investment", "opta": "gives a correct picture of profitability.", "optb": "underemphasises liquidity.", "optc": "does not measure the discounted rate of return.", "optd": "takes into account the cash inflows after the recovery of investments.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Annual depreciation costs are constant, when the __________ method of depreciation calculation is used.", "opta": "declining balance", "optb": "straight line", "optc": "sum of the years digit", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Cost incurred towards __________ in a chemical plant is a component of the utilities cost.", "opta": "water supply", "optb": "running a control laboratory", "optc": "property protection", "optd": "medical services", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Equipment installation cost in a chemical process plant ranges from __________ percent of the purchased equipment cost.", "opta": "10 to 20", "optb": "35 to 45", "optc": "55 to 65", "optd": "70 to 80", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Annual depreciation cost are not constant when, the __________ method of depreciation calculation is used.", "opta": "straight line", "optb": "sinking fund", "optc": "present worth", "optd": "declining balance.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "Longer tubes are less expensive per unit heat transfer area as compared to shorter tubes.", "optb": "A cost index is merely a number for a given year showing the cost at that time relative to a certain base year.", "optc": "Turn over ratio of a chemical plant is the ratio of gross annual sales to the fixed capital investment.", "optd": "Plates with butt welded joints are less expensive compared to lap welded joints, because squaring of plates is not necessary.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Construction expenses are roughly __________ percent of the total direct cost of the plant.", "opta": "2", "optb": "10", "optc": "30", "optd": "50", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A machine has an initial value of Rs. 5000, service life of 5 years and final salvage value of Rs. 1000. The annual depreciation cost by straight line method is Rs.", "opta": "300", "optb": "600", "optc": "800", "optd": "1000", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not a component of depreciation cost ?", "opta": "Repairs and maintenance cost.", "optb": "Loss due to obsolescence of the equipment.", "optc": "Loss due to decrease in the demand of product.", "optd": "Loss due to accident/breakdown in the machinery.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A series of equal payments (e.g., deposit or cost) made at equal intervals of time is known as", "opta": "perpetuity", "optb": "capital charge factor", "optc": "annuity", "optd": "future worth", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Maximum work that could be secured by expanding the gas over a given pressure range is the __________ work.", "opta": "isothermal", "optb": "adiabatic", "optc": "isentropic", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Internal energy change of a system over one complete cycle in a cyclic process is", "opta": "zero", "optb": "+ve", "optc": "-ve", "optd": "dependent on the path", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Heating of water under atmospheric pressure is an __________ process.", "opta": "isochoric", "optb": "isobaric", "optc": "adiabatic", "optd": "isothermal", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Van Laar equation deals with the activity co-efficients in", "opta": "binary solutions", "optb": "ternary solutions", "optc": "azeotropic mixture only", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "High __________ is an undesirable property for a good refrigerant.", "opta": "specific heat", "optb": "latent heat of vaporisation", "optc": "viscosity", "optd": "specific vapor volume", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Solubility of a substance which dissolves with an increase in volume and liberation of heat will be favoured by the", "opta": "low pressure and high temperature.", "optb": "low pressure and low temperature.", "optc": "high pressure and low temperature.", "optd": "high pressure and high temperature.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Entropy is a measure of the __________ of a system.", "opta": "disorder", "optb": "orderly behaviour", "optc": "temperature changes only", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A chemical reaction will occur spontaneously at constant pressure and temperature, if the free energy is", "opta": "zero", "optb": "positive", "optc": "negative", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fundamental principle of refrigeration is based on the __________ law of thermodynamics.", "opta": "zeroth", "optb": "first", "optc": "second", "optd": "third", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For a spontaneous process, free energy", "opta": "is zero", "optb": "increases", "optc": "decreases whereas the entropy increases", "optd": "and entropy both decrease", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A refrigeration cycle is a reversed heat engine. Which of the following has the maximum value of the co-efficient of performance (COP) for a given refrigeration effect ?", "opta": "Vapor compression cycle using expansion valve.", "optb": "Air refrigeration cycle.", "optc": "Vapor compression cycle using expansion engine.", "optd": "Carnot refrigeration cycle.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a working refrigerator, the value of COP is always", "opta": "0", "optb": "< 0", "optc": "< 1", "optd": "> 1", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "__________ increases with increase in pressure.", "opta": "The melting point of wax", "optb": "The boiling point of a liquid", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A refrigerator may be termed as a", "opta": "heat pump", "optb": "heat engine", "optc": "Carnot engine", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For a stable phase at constant pressure and temperature, the fugacity of each component in a binary system __________ as its mole fraction increases.", "opta": "decreases", "optb": "increases", "optc": "remains same", "optd": "decreases linearly", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not an intensive property ?", "opta": "Chemical potential", "optb": "Surface tension", "optc": "Heat capacity", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Out of the following refrigration cycles, which one has the minimum COP (Co-efficient of performance)?", "opta": "Air cycle", "optb": "Carnot cycle", "optc": "Ordinary vapour compression cycle", "optd": "Vapour compression with a reversible expansion engine", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Measurement of thermodynamic property of temperature is facilitated by __________ law of thermodynamics.", "opta": "1st", "optb": "zeroth", "optc": "3rd", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The theoretical minimum work required to separate one mole of a liquid mixture at 1 atm, containing 50 mole % each of n- heptane and n- octane into pure compounds each at 1 atm is", "opta": "-2 RT ln 0.5", "optb": "-RT ln 0.5", "optc": "0.5 RT", "optd": "2 RT", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Keeping the pressure constant, to double the volume of a given mass of an ideal gas at 27\u00b0C, the temperature should be raised to __________ \u00b0C.", "opta": "270", "optb": "327", "optc": "300", "optd": "540", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Entropy of an ideal gas depends upon its", "opta": "pressure", "optb": "temperature", "optc": "both (a) & (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Isobaric process means a constant process.", "opta": "temperature", "optb": "pressure", "optc": "volume", "optd": "entropy", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "No work is done by the system, when a reaction occurs at constant", "opta": "volume", "optb": "temperature", "optc": "pressure", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the vapour pressure at two temperatures of a solid phase in equilibrium with its liquid phase are known, then the latent heat of fusion can be calculated by the", "opta": "Maxwell's equation", "optb": "Clayperon-Claussius equation", "optc": "Van Laar equation", "optd": "Nernst Heat Theorem", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The freezing point of a liquid decreases when the pressure is increased, if the liquid __________ while freezing.", "opta": "contracts", "optb": "expands", "optc": "does not change in volume", "optd": "either (a), (b) or (c)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "\"At the absolute zero temperature, the entropy of every perfectly crystalline substance becomes zero\". This follows from the", "opta": "third law of thermodynamics", "optb": "second law of thermodynamics", "optc": "Nernst heat theorem", "optd": "Maxwell's relations", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "During Joule-Thomson expansion of gases", "opta": "enthalpy remains constant.", "optb": "entropy remains constant.", "optc": "temperature remains constant.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The accentric factor of a materical, '\u03c9', is defined as \u03c9 = -log10(Prsat)Tr-1 = 0.7, where, Prsat = reduced vapor pressure, Tr = reduced temperature. The value of accentric factor is always", "opta": "> 2", "optb": "< 1", "optc": "> 1", "optd": "< 3", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Degress of freedom at triple point will be", "opta": "0", "optb": "1", "optc": "2", "optd": "3", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "\"Law of corresponding states\" says that", "opta": ", two different gases behave similarly, if their reduced properties (i.e. P, V and T) are same.", "optb": "the surface of separation (i. e. the meniscus) between liquid and vapour phase disappears at the critical temperature.", "optc": "no gas can be liquified above the critical temperature, howsoever high the pressure may be.", "optd": "the molar heat of energy of gas at constant volume should be nearly constant (about 3 calories).", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Linde gas liquefaction process employs cooling", "opta": "by throttling", "optb": "by expansion in an engine", "optc": "at constant pressure", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement pertaining to the decomposition of PCl5 represented by, PCl5  PCl3 + Cl2.Degree of dissociation of PCl5 will", "opta": "decrease on addition of Cl2.", "optb": "increase on addition of an inert gas at constant pressure.", "optc": "decrease on increasing the pressure of the system.", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Joule-Thomson experiment is", "opta": "isobaric", "optb": "adiabatic", "optc": "isenthalpic", "optd": "both(b) & (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Boyle's law for gases states that", "opta": ", when temperature is constant.", "optb": ", when temperature & mass of the gas remain constant.", "optc": "P \u221d V, at constant temperature & mass of the gas.", "optd": "= constant, for any gas.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "1st law of thermodynamics is nothing but the law of conservation of", "opta": "momentum", "optb": "mass", "optc": "energy", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a reversible chemical reaction (where, \u0394x = number of moles of products-number of moles of reactants )", "opta": "addition of inert gas favours the forward reaction, when \u0394x is positive.", "optb": "pressure has no effect on equilibrium, when \u0394n = 0.", "optc": "addition of inert gas has no effect on the equilibrium constant at constant volume for any value of \u0394x (+ ve, - ve) or zero).", "optd": "all 'a', 'b' & 'c'.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Out of the following refrigeration cycles, which one has maximum COP ?", "opta": "Air cycle", "optb": "Carnot cycle", "optc": "Ordinary vapor compression cycle", "optd": "Vapor compression with a reversible expansion engine", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the correct statement:", "opta": "In an isothermal system, irreversible work is more than reversible work.", "optb": "Under reversible conditions, the adiabatic work is less than isothermal work.", "optc": "Heat, work, enthalpy and entropy are all 'state functions'.", "optd": "Matter and energy can not be exchanged with the surroundings in a closed system.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In any spontaneous process,", "opta": "only F decreases", "optb": "only A decreases", "optc": "both F and A decreases", "optd": "both F and A increase", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is a thermodynamic property of a  system ?", "opta": "Concentration", "optb": "Mass", "optc": "Temperature", "optd": "Entropy", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Equilibrium constant decreases as the temperature", "opta": "increases, for an exothermic reaction.", "optb": "decreases, for an exothermic reaction.", "optc": "increases, for an endothermic reaction.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The expression,  , gives the free energy change", "opta": "with pressure changes at constant temperature.", "optb": "under reversible isothermal volume change.", "optc": "during heating of an ideal gas.", "optd": "during cooling of an ideal gas.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "All gases during throttling process at atmospheric temperature and pressure show a cooling effect except", "opta": "CO2", "optb": "H2", "optc": "O2", "optd": "N2", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Compressibility factor for almost all the gases are approximately same at the same", "opta": "pressure and temperature.", "optb": "reduced pressure and reduced temperature.", "optc": "critical pressure and critical temperature.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "Activity co-efficient is dimensionless.", "optb": "In case of an ideal gas, the fagacity is equal to its pressure.", "optc": "In a mixture of ideal gases, the fugacity of a component is equal to the partial pressure of the component.", "optd": "The fugacity co-efficient is zero for an ideal gas.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The co-efficient of performance (COP) of a refrigerating system, which is its index of performance, is defined as the ratio of useful refrigeration to the net work. The units of __________ and COP are the same.", "opta": "kinematic viscosity", "optb": "work", "optc": "temperature", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The chemical potential of a component (\u03bci) of a phase is the amount by which its capacity for doing all work, barring work of expansion is increased per unit amount of sustance added for an infinitesimal addition at constant temperature and pressure. It is given by", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In jet refrigerators, the refrigerating fluid is practically always", "opta": "water", "optb": "ammonia", "optc": "freon", "optd": "brine", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Water on heating from 1 to 4\u00b0C", "opta": "contracts", "optb": "expands", "optc": "has same volume", "optd": "may contract or expand", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the correct statement.", "opta": "Compression ratio of an Otto engine is comparatively higher than a diesel engine.", "optb": "Efficiency of an Otto engine is higher than that of a diesel engine for the same compression ratio.", "optc": "Otto engine efficiency decreases with the rise in compression ratio, due to decrease in work produced per quantity of heat.", "optd": "Diesel engine normally operates at lower compression ratio than an Otto engine for an equal output of work.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Oxidation of SO2 to SO3 is favoured by", "opta": "low temperature and low pressure.", "optb": "low temperature and high pressure.", "optc": "high temperature and low pressure.", "optd": "high temperature and high pressure.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Gun powder,  which is an explosive comprises of charcoal,  sulphur and", "opta": "glycerene", "optb": "salt petre", "optc": "nitro glycerene", "optd": "dynamite", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Starting raw material for the manufacture of alum is", "opta": "alumina", "optb": "gypsum", "optc": "bauxite", "optd": "ammonium bicarbonate", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Salt cake is chemically represented by", "opta": "Na2SO4", "optb": "CaSO4.H2O", "optc": "MgSO4", "optd": "BaSO4", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following sugars is the sweetest?", "opta": "Glucose", "optb": "Fructose", "optc": "Sucrose", "optd": "Lactose", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Paper pulp produced by kraft/sulphate process is", "opta": "bleached easily", "optb": "dull white in color", "optc": "strong fibrous", "optd": "dark colored", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Claude process of gas liquefaction employs", "opta": "merely compression of gas beyond its critical pressure.", "optb": "Joule-Thomson expansion cooling.", "optc": "heat exchange with colder stream.", "optd": "adiabatic expansion against a piston or in a turbine.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The main use of HCl is in the", "opta": "drilling of petroleum wells and pickling of steel sheets.", "optb": "manufacture of cationic detergent.", "optc": "treatment of spent fuel of nuclear reactor.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The gasification reaction represented by, C + H2O = CO + H2,  is a/an __________ reaction.", "opta": "exothermic", "optb": "endothermic", "optc": "catalytic", "optd": "autocatalytic", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Viscose rayon is chemically", "opta": "cellulose nitrate", "optb": "regenerated cellulose nitrate", "optc": "cellulose acetate", "optd": "regenerated cellulose acetate", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "All enzymes are made of", "opta": "fats", "optb": "carbohydrates", "optc": "proteins", "optd": "amino acids", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The combustion reaction,  C + O2 = CO2,  is", "opta": "exothermic", "optb": "endothermic", "optc": "autocatalytic", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Styrene is produced from ethyl benzene by the process of", "opta": "dehydrogenation", "optb": "oxidation", "optc": "alkylation", "optd": "dehydration", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Gelatine which is a nitrogenous organic protein is obtained by the hydrolysis of", "opta": "callagen", "optb": "tannin", "optc": "molasses", "optd": "carbohydrate", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The chamber process is", "opta": "preferred over contact process for producing 98 to 100% H2SO4 and various oleums.", "optb": "non-catalytic and operates only on pyrites.", "optc": "a batch process for directly producing high strength (98 to 100%) H2SO4.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Sucrose content in the raw juice extracted from sugar cane is about __________ percent.", "opta": "1 - 2", "optb": "15 - 20", "optc": "50 - 60", "optd": "80 - 85", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fusel oil is a/an", "opta": "essential oil.", "optb": "extract from medicinal herbs.", "optc": "mixture of higher molecular weight alcohols (a by-product obtained during production of alcohol from molasses).", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Styrene-butadiene-rubber (SBR)  as compared to natural rubber has", "opta": "Poorer tensile strength.", "optb": "poorer resistance to oxidation.", "optc": "greater amount of heat build-up under heavy loading.", "optd": "all (a),  (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Co-efficient of thermal expansion of glass is decreased by the addition of __________ during its manufacture.", "opta": "CaO", "optb": "MnO2", "optc": "ZnO", "optd": "FeS", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The catalyst used in the manufacture of DDT (from chloral and chlorobenzene) is", "opta": "dilute H2SO4", "optb": "oleum", "optc": "ultraviolet light", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Haemoglobin is a/an", "opta": "amino acid", "optb": "biological catalyst", "optc": "protein", "optd": "enezyme", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Epoxy resin", "opta": "is a good adhesive.", "optb": "is an elastomer.", "optc": "cannot be used for surface coatings.", "optd": "is a polyester.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Concentration of NaOH solution produced by mercury electrolytic cell is about __________ percent.", "opta": "10", "optb": "25", "optc": "50", "optd": "98", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is the most adverse factor challenging the choice of mercury electrolytic cell process for the production of caustic soda?", "opta": "High cost of mercury.", "optb": "High specific gravity of mercury.", "optc": "Non-availability of high purity mercury.", "optd": "Pollution of water stream by mercury.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Esterification reaction produces", "opta": "detergent", "optb": "vanaspati", "optc": "soap", "optd": "mercaptans", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Wood charcoal is used for decolouration of sugar,  because  it __________ the  coloured materials.", "opta": "adsorbs", "optb": "oxidises", "optc": "reduces", "optd": "converts", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Producer gas consists mainly of", "opta": "CO,  CO2 N2, H2", "optb": "CO, H2", "optc": "H2,  CH4", "optd": "C2H2, CO2, H2", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Neoprene is the trade name of", "opta": "polyurathane", "optb": "phenol formaldehyde", "optc": "polychloroprene", "optd": "styrene-butadiene rubber", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Hard water", "opta": "does not affect the lather formation by soap.", "optb": "is not unfit for drinking purpose.", "optc": "pollutes the water stream.", "optd": "all (a),  (b) and (c).", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is an organo-metal-lic compound ?", "opta": "Isopropyl alcohol", "optb": "Tetra-ethyl lead", "optc": "Zeolite", "optd": "Cumene", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Sulphur addition in soap is done to", "opta": "improve the soap texture.", "optb": "cure pimples & dandruff.", "optc": "fasten lather formation.", "optd": "increase its cleansing action.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Phosphate rock is a raw material for the manufacture of", "opta": "phosphoric acid", "optb": "phosphorous", "optc": "superphosphates", "optd": "all (a),  (b) and (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Mineral oils (e.g. petroleum oils) are preferred over fatty oils (e.g. mustard oil,  ghee,  tallow,  palm oil,  olive oil etc.) as a lubricant due to its", "opta": "poor oxidation stability and high gum forming tendency.", "optb": "greater tendency of decomposition at elevated temperature.", "optc": "hydrolysis tendency in presence of water.", "optd": "all (a),  (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not a raw material used for the manufacture of ordinary glass?", "opta": "Iron oxide", "optb": "Soda ash", "optc": "Limestone", "optd": "Silica", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Esterification reaction", "opta": "produces soap.", "optb": "is reversible.", "optc": "is a reaction between an alcohol and an organic acid.", "optd": "all (a),  (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In sulphate pulp manufacture,  the pressure and temperature in the digestor is", "opta": "10 atm.,  800 \u00b0C", "optb": "10 atm.,  170-180\u00b0C", "optc": "1 atm.,  170 - 180\u00b0C", "optd": "l atm., 800\u00b0C", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Zeolite removes both temporary as well as permanent hardness of water by precipitating calcium and magnesium present in water as insoluble zeolites. Used zeolite is regenerated by flushing with the solution of", "opta": "calcium sulphate", "optb": "sodium chloride", "optc": "sodium sulphate", "optd": "magnesium chloride.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the endothermic reaction out of the following.", "opta": "C+O2 = CO", "optb": "CO + 3H2 = CH4 + H2O", "optc": "CaCO3 = CaO + CO2", "optd": "CO +O2 = CO2", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pasteurisation of milk means", "opta": "removal of fatty and albuminous substance from it.", "optb": "killing of organisms present in it by heating it at controlled temperature without changing its natural characteristics.", "optc": "inhibiting the growth of micro-organisms without killing them.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fusion of bauxite and __________ produces  high alumina cement.", "opta": "alum", "optb": "limestone", "optc": "coke", "optd": "quartz", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "__________ process is used for the manufacture of sodium carbonate by ammonia soda process.", "opta": "Ostwald's", "optb": "Bosch", "optc": "Solvay", "optd": "Haber's", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Polycaprolactum is commercially known as", "opta": "nylon-6", "optb": "nylon-66", "optc": "dacron", "optd": "rayon", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Frasch process is for", "opta": "making oxygen", "optb": "producing helium", "optc": "mining sulphur", "optd": "making nitrogen", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Very fine suspended and colloidal impurities are removed from water by a process called", "opta": "sedimentation", "optb": "coagulation", "optc": "disinfection", "optd": "softening", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pitch (a product of coal tar distillation) is always mixed with creosote oil,  when it is to be burnt in a burner,  because", "opta": "its calorific value is very less.", "optb": "tar neutralises the residual acids present in pitch.", "optc": "it reduces viscosity and imparts fluidity for its transportation through pipelines at economic pressure drop.", "optd": "all (a),  (b) and (c).", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which is the main reducing agent during production of iron from iron ore in a blast furnace ?", "opta": "C", "optb": "CO", "optc": "CO2", "optd": "H2", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The drug used in contraceptives is", "opta": "sulphadizene", "optb": "mestranol", "optc": "methyl salicylate", "optd": "pencillin", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Raw materials used for producing __________ cement does not contain iron oxide.", "opta": "waterproof", "optb": "slag", "optc": "white", "optd": "pozzolan", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the Lurgi coal gasifier", "opta": "coking coals cannot be used.", "optb": "low carbon conversion efficiency is achieved.", "optc": "entrainment of solids is higher.", "optd": "large quantity of coal can be processed.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Neon gas is", "opta": "flammable in nature.", "optb": "used in color discharge tube.", "optc": "filled in lamps having tungsten filament.", "optd": "all (a),  (b) and (c).", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following will give maximum gas conversion ?", "opta": "Fixed bed reactor.", "optb": "Fluidised bed reactor.", "optc": "Semi-fluidised bed reactor.", "optd": "Plug-flow catalytic reactor.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "__________ explains the mechanism of catalysis.", "opta": "Activated complex theory", "optb": "Collision theory", "optc": "Thermodynamics", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "From among the following, choose one which is not an exothermic process.", "opta": "Methanol synthesis", "optb": "Catalytic cracking", "optc": "Ammonia synthesis", "optd": "Oxidation of sulphur", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The fractional volume change of the system for the isothermal gas phase reaction, A  3B , between no conversion and complete conversion is", "opta": "0.5", "optb": "1", "optc": "2", "optd": "3", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A catalyst", "opta": "initiates a reaction.", "optb": "lowers the activation energy of reacting molecules.", "optc": "is capable of reacting with any one of the reactants.", "optd": "can not be recovered chemically unchanged at the end of a chemical reaction.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "What is the order of a chemical reaction, , if the rate of formation of 'C', increases by a factor of 2.82 on doubling the concentration of 'A' and increases by a factor of 9 on trebling the concentration of 'B'?", "opta": "7/2", "optb": "7/4", "optc": "5/2", "optd": "5/4", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For high conversion in a highly exothermic solid catalysed reaction, use a __________ bed reactor.", "opta": "fixed", "optb": "fluidised bed reactor followed by a fixed", "optc": "fixed bed reactor followed by a fluidised", "optd": "fluidised", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For every 10\u00b0C rise in temperature, the rate of chemical reaction doubles. When the temperature is increased from 30 to 70\u00b0C, the rate of reaction increases __________ times.", "opta": "8", "optb": "12", "optc": "16", "optd": "32", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The single parameter model proposed for describing non-ideal flow is the __________ model.", "opta": "tank in series", "optb": "dispersion", "optc": "both (a) & (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b).", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A first order reaction requires two equal sized CSTR. The conversion is", "opta": "less when they are connected in series.", "optb": "more when they are connected in series.", "optc": "more when they are connected in parallel.", "optd": "same whether they are connected in series or in parallel.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In case of physical adsorption, the heat of adsorption is of the order of __________ kcal/kg.mole.", "opta": "100", "optb": "1000", "optc": "10000", "optd": "100000", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The most unsuitable reactor for carrying out reactions in which high reactant concentration favours high yields is", "opta": "backmix reactor", "optb": "plug flow reactor", "optc": "series of CSTR", "optd": "PFR in series", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement pertaining to space velocity of flow reactors.", "opta": "The unit of space velocity is (time)-1 .", "optb": "The space velocity of 3 hr-1 means that three reactor volumes of feed at specified conditions are being fed into the reactor every hour.", "optc": "The space velocity of 3 hr-1 means that one third reactor volume of feed at specified conditions are being fed into the reactor.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A reactor is generally termed as an autoclave, when it is a", "opta": "high pressure batch reactor.", "optb": "atmospheric pressure tank reactor.", "optc": "high pressure tubular reactor.", "optd": "atmospheric pressure CSTR.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "6 gm of carbon is burnt with an amount of air containing 18 gm oxygen. The product contains 16.5 gms CO2 and 2.8 gms CO besides other constituents. What is the degree of conversion on the basis of disappearance of limiting reactant ?", "opta": "100%", "optb": "95%", "optc": "75%", "optd": "20%", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The rate constant of a chemical reaction decreases by decreasing the", "opta": "pressure", "optb": "concentration of reactants", "optc": "temperature", "optd": "duration of reaction", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Reaction rate equation for the reaction, . If S at is present in large excess, what is the order of this reaction?", "opta": "zero", "optb": "one", "optc": "two", "optd": "three", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Rate of a gaseous phase reaction is given by, . The unit of rate constant is", "opta": "(atm)-1", "optb": "(hr)-1", "optc": "(atm)-1.(hr)-1", "optd": "atm.(hr)-1", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "__________ is the response curve for a step input signal from a reactor.", "opta": "S-curve", "optb": "C-curve", "optc": "I-curve", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "'If the catalyst pore size is small in comparison with the mean free path, collisions with the pore wall controls the process'. The diffusivity under this condition is called 'Knudsen diffusivity', which is affected by the", "opta": "pressure", "optb": "temperature", "optc": "both (a) & (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is the most suitable for very high pressure gas phase reaction ?", "opta": "Batch reactor", "optb": "Tubular flow reactor", "optc": "Stirred tank reactor", "optd": "Fluidised bed reactor", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The reaction between oxygen and organic material is a/an __________ reaction.", "opta": "exothermic", "optb": "endothermic", "optc": "biochemical", "optd": "photochemical", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "With decrease in temperature, the equilibrium conversion of a reversible endother-mic reaction", "opta": "decreases", "optb": "increases", "optc": "remains unaffected", "optd": "increases linearly with temperature", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In an exothermic chemical reaction, the reactants compared to the products have", "opta": "higher temperature", "optb": "more energy", "optc": "less energy", "optd": "same energy.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For a reaction of the type, , the rate of reaction (- rx) is given by", "opta": "(K1+K1)CX", "optb": "(K1+K2+K3)CX", "optc": "K1CV - K2CX", "optd": "(K1-K2)CX", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a consecutive reaction system  when E1 is much greater than E2, the yield of B increases with the", "opta": "increase of temperature.", "optb": "decrease of temperature.", "optc": "increase in initial concentration of A.", "optd": "decrease in initial concentration of A.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A reversible liquid phase endothermic reaction is to be carried out in a plug flow reactor. For minimum reactor volume, it should be operated such that the temperature along the length", "opta": "decreases.", "optb": "increases.", "optc": "is at the highest allowable temperature throughout.", "optd": "first increases and then decreases.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The rate constant of a chemical reaction increases by 100 times when the temperature is increased from 400 \u00b0K to 500 \u00b0K. Assuming transition state theory is valid, the value of E/R is", "opta": "8987\u00b0K", "optb": "9210\u00b0K", "optc": "8764\u00b0K", "optd": "8621\u00b0K", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A batch reactor is suitable for", "opta": "achieving cent percent conversion of reactants into products.", "optb": "large scale gaseous phase reactions.", "optc": "liquid phase reactions.", "optd": "obtaining uniform polymerisation products in highly exothermic reactions.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For a heterogeneous catalytic reaction", "opta": "free energy of activation is lowered in the presence of catalyst, which remains unchanged at the end of reaction.", "optb": "a relatively small amount of catalyst can cause the conversion of large amount of reactants which does not mean that catalyst concentration is important.", "optc": "the catalyst does not form an intermediate complex with the reactant.", "optd": "the surface of the catalyst does not play an important role during reaction.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The increase in the rate of reaction with temperature is due to", "opta": "increase in the number of effective collisions.", "optb": "decrease in activation energy.", "optc": "increase in the average kinetic energy of the reacting molecules.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A catalyst loses its activity due to", "opta": "loss in surface area of the active component.", "optb": "agglomeration of metal particles caused by thermal sintering of the solid surface.", "optc": "covering of the catalytic active sites by a foregin substance.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "'N' plug flow reactors in series with a total volume 'V' gives the same conversion as a single plug flow reactor of volume 'V' for __________ order reactions.", "opta": "first", "optb": "second", "optc": "third", "optd": "any", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Specific rate constant for a second order reaction", "opta": "is independent of temperature.", "optb": "varies with temperature.", "optc": "depends on the nature of the reactants.", "optd": "both (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For the irreversible elementary reactions in parallel viz , the rate of disappearance of 'X' is equal to", "opta": "CA(K1+K2)", "optb": "CA(K1 + K2)/2", "optc": "CA . K1/2", "optd": "CA . K2/2", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For an isothermal variable volume batch reactor, the following relation is applicable for a first order irreversible reaction.", "opta": "XA = k . t", "optb": "", "optc": "-ln(1 - XA) = kt", "optd": "\u03b5A . ln (1 - XA) = k . t", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For a zero order chemical reaction, the", "opta": "half life period is directly proportion to the initial concentration of the reac-tants.", "optb": "plot of products concentration with time is a straight line through the origin.", "optc": "products concentration increases linerarly with time.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "BET apparatus", "opta": "measures the catalyst surface area directly.", "optb": "operates at very high pressure.", "optc": "is made entirely of stainless steel.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Radioactive decay follows __________ order kinetics.", "opta": "first", "optb": "second", "optc": "third", "optd": "zero.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The excess energy of reactants in a chemical reaction required to dissociate into products is termed as the __________ energy.", "opta": "activation", "optb": "potential", "optc": "binding", "optd": "threshold", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For a solid catalysed chemical reaction, the effectiveness of solid catalyst depends upon the __________ adsorption.", "opta": "physical", "optb": "chemical", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the correct statement.", "opta": "In catalytic reactions, the catalyst reacts with the reactants.", "optb": "A catalyst initiates a chemical reaction.", "optc": "A catalyst lowers the activation energy of the reacting molecules.", "optd": "A catalyst can not be recovered chemi cally unchanged at the end of the chemical reaction.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The dimensions of rate constant for reaction 3A  B are (l/gm mole)/min. Therefore the reaction order is", "opta": "0", "optb": "1", "optc": "2", "optd": "3", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the correct statement", "opta": "Reactions with high activation energies are very temperature sensitive.", "optb": "Chemical equilibrium is a static state.", "optc": "A photochemical reaction is catalysed by light.", "optd": "A chemical reaction occurs when the energy of the reacting molecule is less than the activation energy of the reaction.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the time required to complete a definite fraction of reaction varies inversely as the concentration of the reactants, then the order of reaction is", "opta": "0", "optb": "1", "optc": "2", "optd": "3", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Sulphuric acid is used as a catalyst in the", "opta": "hydrogenation of oils.", "optb": "gas phase oxidation of SO2 in chamber process.", "optc": "alkylation of hydrocarbons.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fractional conversion __________ with increase in pressure for ammonia synthesis reaction i.e., N2 + 3H2  2NH3.", "opta": "increases", "optb": "decreases", "optc": "remains unchanged", "optd": "unpredictable from the data", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "The vessel dispersion number (D/UL) for plug flow and mixed flow approaches zero and infinity respectively.", "optb": "Space time in a flow reactor is a measure of its capacity and is equal to the residence time when the density of reaction mixture is constant.", "optc": "Mixed reactor is always smaller than the plug flow reactor for all positive reaction orders for a particular duty.", "optd": "In an ideal tubular flow reactor, mixing takes place in radial direction and there is no mixing in logitudinal direction.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The reason why a catalyst increases the rate of reaction is that, it", "opta": "decreases the energy barrier for reaction.", "optb": "increases the activation energy.", "optc": "decreases the molecular collision diameter.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A first order irreversible reaction, A  B is carried out separately in a constant volume as well as in a variable volume reactor for a particular period. It signifies that __________ in the two reactors.", "opta": "both conversion as well as concentration are same", "optb": "conversion in both will be the same but concentrations will be different", "optc": "both the conversion as well as concentrations will be different", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Suspended solid present in the waste water generated in blast furnace gas cooling and cleaning plant is removed by", "opta": "biological oxygen pond.", "optb": "radial settling tank (thickener) using coagulant (lime & ferrous sulphate).", "optc": "lagoons.", "optd": "filtration.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Persons working in cement plants and limestone quarries are more prone to disease like", "opta": "cancer", "optb": "asthma", "optc": "silicosis", "optd": "flourosis (bone disease)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Particulates (< 1\u03bcm     size) remaining suspended   in    air   indefinitely   and transported by wind currents are called", "opta": "fumes", "optb": "mists", "optc": "smoke", "optd": "aerosols", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Operating principle of cyclone separator is based on the action of __________ dust particles.", "opta": "diffusion of", "optb": "centrifugal force on", "optc": "gravitational force on", "optd": "electrostatic force on", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Exposure to small amount of __________ results in high blood pressure & heart disease in human beings.", "opta": "hydrogen sulphide", "optb": "mercury", "optc": "cadmium", "optd": "asbestos", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Maximum allowable concentration of CO2 in air for safe working is __________ ppm (parts per million).", "opta": "50", "optb": "1000", "optc": "2000", "optd": "5000", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Tolerable limit of nitrogen oxides in air is __________ ppm.", "opta": "0.1", "optb": "1", "optc": "5", "optd": "25", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Iron & manganese present as pollutant in water can not be removed by", "opta": "ion exchange process.", "optb": "oxidation followed by settling & filtration.", "optc": "lime soda process or manganese zeolite process.", "optd": "chlorination.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In water chemical treatment plant, use of chloramines ensures", "opta": "disinfection.", "optb": "taste & odour control.", "optc": "weed control in reservoirs.", "optd": "removal of permanent hardness.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is the common pollutant emitted from metallurgical smelters, thermal power plant and cement plants ?", "opta": "NOx", "optb": "Hg", "optc": "SO2", "optd": "F", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "During which of the following operating conditions of an automobile, carbon monoxide content in the exhaust gas is maximum ?", "opta": "Idle running", "optb": "Acceleration", "optc": "Cruising", "optd": "Deaccelaration", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "H2S present in gaseous stream can be removed by adsorption on", "opta": "silica gel", "optb": "active carbon", "optc": "bog iron", "optd": "limestone powder", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Inhalation of lead compounds present in automobile exhaust (using leaded petrol) causes", "opta": "blood poisoning.", "optb": "anaemia.", "optc": "nervous system disorder.", "optd": "all (a), (b) & (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Replenishment of dissolved oxygen in water stream polluted with industrial waste occurs by", "opta": "natural aeration of water stream.", "optb": "photosynthetic action of algae.", "optc": "both (a) & (b).", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b).", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Aerodynamic noise resulting from turbulent gas flow is the most prevalent source of valve noise in fluid ilow control. It is caused due to", "opta": "Reynold stresses", "optb": "shear forces", "optc": "both (a) & (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Smoke is produced due to", "opta": "insufficient supply of combustion air and insufficient time for combustion.", "optb": "poor quality of fuel and improper mixing of fuel & combustion air.", "optc": "poor design & overloading of furnace.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fluorosis (a bone disease) is caused by the presence of high concentration of __________ in atmospheric air.", "opta": "hydrocarbons", "optb": "hydrogen flouride", "optc": "hydrogen sulphides", "optd": "nitrogen dioxide", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Threshold Limit Value (TLV) is the maximum allowable concentration (i.e. safe limit) of pollutants in air. Safe limit for SO2 in air is __________ ppm.", "opta": "5", "optb": "500", "optc": "1000", "optd": "2000", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Main pollutants released from iron & steel industry is", "opta": "CO, CO2 & SO2.", "optb": "H2S, NO & SO3.", "optc": "CO2, H2S & NO2.", "optd": "SO3, NO2 & CO2.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Exposure to chemicals having carcinogenic properties cause", "opta": "dermatitis (skin disorder)", "optb": "cancer", "optc": "asphyxiation (suffocation)", "optd": "asthma", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Scale formation in boiler is controlled by", "opta": "preheating of feed water.", "optb": "reduction in hardness, silica & alumina in feed water.", "optc": "keeping the pH value of feed water just below 7.", "optd": "eliminating H2S in feed water.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Noise level heard at a distance of about 100 metres from a jet engine with after burner is about __________ decibels.", "opta": "120", "optb": "140", "optc": "170", "optd": "200", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "TLV of mercury in potable (drinking) water is about __________ ppm.", "opta": "0.001", "optb": "0.1", "optc": "1", "optd": "5", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which is the best and the most effective method for the removal of organic contaminant present in the polluted water in very small quantity (say < 200 mg/litre)?", "opta": "Lagooning", "optb": "Activated carbon adsorption", "optc": "Biological oxidation pond", "optd": "Chemical coagulation", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which is a secondary air pollutant ?", "opta": "Photochemical smog", "optb": "Sulphur dioxide", "optc": "Nitrogen dioxide", "optd": "Dust particles", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is the most detrimental for water used in high pressure boiler ?", "opta": "Silica", "optb": "Turbidity", "optc": "Phenol", "optd": "Dissolved oxygen", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Turbidity of water is an indication of the presence of", "opta": "suspended inorganic matter", "optb": "dissolved solids", "optc": "floating solids", "optd": "dissolved gases", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Presence of excess flourine in water causes", "opta": "dental cavity", "optb": "tooth decay", "optc": "fluorosis", "optd": "respiratory disease", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Siderosis is a disease caused by the inhalation of __________ dust.", "opta": "coal", "optb": "silica", "optc": "iron", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following pollutants is not emitted during volcanic eruptions ?", "opta": "SO2", "optb": "H2S", "optc": "CO", "optd": "hydrocarbons", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The main pollutant in waste water discharged from a petroleum refinery is oil (both in free and emulsified form). Free oil is removed by", "opta": "biological oxygen pond.", "optb": "aerated lagoons.", "optc": "trickling filters.", "optd": "gravity separator having oil skimming devices.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Phenolic water generated in coke ovens & by-product plant attached to an integrated steel plant containing phenol in concentration of less than 100 mg/litre can be removed by", "opta": "chlorination", "optb": "treating in biological oxygen pond", "optc": "chemical coagulation", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following dust collection equipments is the least efficient (for sub-micronic particles) ?", "opta": "Dust catcher (gravity type)", "optb": "Cyclone separator", "optc": "Bag filter", "optd": "Hollow wet scrubber", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Bag filter design is predominantly dependent on gas temperature, as it affects the gas density & viscosity and the selection of filtering material. The pressure drop in a bag filter is", "opta": "inversely proportional to viscosity of gas.", "optb": "proportional to the viscosity & density of the gas.", "optc": "proportional to the pressure of the gas.", "optd": "both (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Dust collection efficiency of a cyclone separator depends upon its", "opta": "diameter.", "optb": "inlet gas velocity.", "optc": "overall height.", "optd": "all (a), (b) & (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Ionisation potential employed in the industrial electrostatic precipitator is of the order of", "opta": "30 to 70 kV DC", "optb": "30 to 70 kV AC", "optc": "230 V AC", "optd": "230 V DC", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The widest explosive limit is of __________ , thereby making it the most explosive gas.", "opta": "acetylene", "optb": "petrol vapor", "optc": "hydrogen", "optd": "carbon monoxide", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Aerobic biological oxidation ponds used for the purification of polluted water", "opta": "destroys/removes pathogen from the sewage.", "optb": "is not very effective for nonbiodegradable substances (e.g. ABS) containing effluents.", "optc": "destroys/removes pathogen much more effectively if the sewage is chlorinated.", "optd": "all (a), (b) & (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Polluted water having low BOD are most economically treated in", "opta": "sedimentation tanks", "optb": "oxidation ponds", "optc": "sludge digester", "optd": "clarifier", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Tri-sodium phosphate is used in boiler water treatment to reduce", "opta": "turbidity", "optb": "caustic embrittlement", "optc": "suspended silica", "optd": "dissolved oxygen", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The commonest form of iron & manganese found in ground water as pollutant is in the form of their", "opta": "carbonates", "optb": "bi-carbonates", "optc": "chlorides", "optd": "sulphides", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "80% less than 200 mesh size particles are called", "opta": "smoke", "optb": "powder", "optc": "grit", "optd": "aggregates", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Coal washing waste water containing about 3% suspended solids (comprising of clay, slate, stone etc.) is treated for solid particles removal", "opta": "by chemical coagulation.", "optb": "in sedimentation tanks equipped with mechanical scrapper.", "optc": "in vacuum filter.", "optd": "in clarifiers.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Inhalation of lead compounds present in the automobile exhausts (using leaded petrol) causes", "opta": "blood poisoning.", "optb": "anaemia.", "optc": "nervous system disorder.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "TLV of ozone (O3) and phosgene (COCl2) in air is __________ ppm.", "opta": "0.1", "optb": "25", "optc": "100", "optd": "1000", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Most of the atmospheric air pollutants are present in large quantity in", "opta": "stratosphere", "optb": "thermosphere", "optc": "trophosphere", "optd": "mesosphere", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "Caustic embrittlement of boiler's metallic parts is caused by high concentration of caustic soda in boiler feed water.", "optb": "Cooling and freezing of water kills the bacteria present in it.", "optc": "With increasing boiler operating pressure of steam, the maximum allowable concentration of silica in feed water goes on decreasing.", "optd": "Dissolved oxygen content in high pressure boiler feed water should be nil.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "'Pneumoconiosis' is a disease caused by the inhalation of __________ dust.", "opta": "coal", "optb": "uranium ore", "optc": "iron ore", "optd": "lime", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of oxygen available to the oxygen required for stabilisation of sewage is called the", "opta": "bacterial stability factor.", "optb": "relative stability.", "optc": "biological oxygen demand (BOD).", "optd": "oxygen ion concentration.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "The concentric atmosphere layer just above troposphere is called stratosphere, which is rich in ozone.", "optb": "Mesosphere is characterised by very low atmospheric pressure and low temperature.", "optc": "Troposhere is a dusty zone containing water vapor and clouds.", "optd": "The radio waves used in the long distance radio communication are reflected back to earth by stratosphere.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Phosphorus vapour comprises of", "opta": "P", "optb": "P2", "optc": "P3", "optd": "P4", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Conversion of yellow phosphorous to red phosphorous is done by heating it in covered retorts at __________ \u00b0C in absence of air.", "opta": "50-80", "optb": "250-400", "optc": "1000-1200", "optd": "800-900", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Commercial fertilisers are available mostly in the form of", "opta": "powder", "optb": "grannules", "optc": "lumps", "optd": "flakes", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "All the nitrogenous fertilisers are not soluble in water.", "optb": "A straight fertiliser contains only one nutrient.", "optc": "Calcium cynamide is used as weed killer in onion fields.", "optd": "The phosphorous nutrient makes the plant stem stronger and increases its branches.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Ammonia synthesis gas is produced from natural gas by", "opta": "thermal cracking", "optb": "steam reforming", "optc": "partial oxidation", "optd": "hydrogenation", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Catalyst used in the manufacture of NH3 by Haber's process is finely divided", "opta": "nickel", "optb": "iron", "optc": "vanadium pentoxide", "optd": "alumina", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Red phosphorous is changed into white phosphorous by", "opta": "heating in presence of light.", "optb": "melting under pressure.", "optc": "vaporisation followed by condensation.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Urea is represented as", "opta": "NH2.CO.NH2", "optb": "NH3CO.CH3", "optc": "NH.CO2.NH", "optd": "NH3.CO2.NH3", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Two gas based fertiliser plants are located in", "opta": "Maharashtra and Gujarat", "optb": "Maharashtra and Orissa", "optc": "Gujarat and Madhya Pradesh", "optd": "Jharkhand and Chattisgarh", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fertiliser plants get their N2 requirements", "opta": "by fractionation of liquified air.", "optb": "by dissociating oxides of nitrogen.", "optc": "from coal gas (coke oven gas).", "optd": "from producer gas.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "During conversion of ammonium carbamate into urea, presence of large excess of water", "opta": "increases the yield of urea.", "optb": "adversely affects the yield of urea.", "optc": "reduces the evaporator load by diluting the urea solution.", "optd": "does not affect the yield of urea.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Hydrogen content of coke oven gas is __________ percent.", "opta": "4", "optb": "22", "optc": "58", "optd": "84", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "'Green acid' is the other name of phosphoric acid produced by the reaction of phosphate rock & sulphuric acid.", "optb": "Chemically unreactive nature of red phosphorous is due to its polymeric structure.", "optc": "Red phosphorous is the most reactive allotropic form of phosphorous.", "optd": "Red phosphorous, which is used in the manufacture of safety matches, is converted into white phosphorous by vaporisation followed by condensation.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Ammonium nitrate (a fertiliser) is coated with limestone powder to", "opta": "increase its nitrogen content.", "optb": "cut down its production cost.", "optc": "avoid the risk of explosion.", "optd": "add extra nutrient as fertiliser.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Action of phosphoric acid on rock phosphate produces", "opta": "superphosphate", "optb": "triple superphosphate", "optc": "nitrophosphate", "optd": "diammonium phosphate", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Reaction of dilute sulphuric acid with phosphate rock produces", "opta": "phosphoric acid", "optb": "superphosphate", "optc": "triple superphosphate", "optd": "gypsum", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Phosphoric acid is produced in wet process from phosphate rock and", "opta": "dilute H2SO4", "optb": "concentrated H2SO4", "optc": "concentrated NHO3", "optd": "concentrated HCl", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Base suspension fertiliser essentially contains", "opta": "13% N2 and 43% P2O5", "optb": "43% N2 and 13% P2O5", "optc": "43% N2 and 13% K2O", "optd": "43% K2O and 43% P2O5", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Conditioners like finely divided peat are added to the fertiliser to", "opta": "counteract burning.", "optb": "avoid caking & hardening.", "optc": "produce bulk.", "optd": "increase its solubility.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Liquid ammonia is not used as such a fertiliser in tropical countries like India, because", "opta": "its N2 content is very low.", "optb": "it is very costly.", "optc": "it will evaporate on spraying.", "optd": "it is not available.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "Yellow phosphorous which is the most reactive allotropic form of phosphorous is transported under water.", "optb": "Apatite is the principal material present in phosphate rock which is chemically Ca10 (PO4)6 (F, Cl, OH).", "optc": "Urea is more hygroscopic than ammonium nitrate.", "optd": "Nitrogen fixation means the process of bringing atmospheric nitrogen into combination i.e. into nitrogen compound form.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following does not come under the category of 'secondary nutrient' for plant growth?", "opta": "Calcium", "optb": "Magnesium", "optc": "Sulphur", "optd": "Oxygen", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Steam reforming of naphtha is a source of hydrogen production for nitrogeneous fertiliser industry. What is the usual ratio of steam to carbon maintained in the process of steam reforming of naphtha ?", "opta": "1.5:1", "optb": "3.5:1", "optc": "10:1", "optd": "15:1", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(CH3 C6 H4)3 PO4 is the chemical formula of", "opta": "triple superphosphate", "optb": "tricresyl phosphate", "optc": "flourapatite", "optd": "superphosphate", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which is a catalyst promoter used in catalytic ammonia synthesis reaction ?", "opta": "Al2O3", "optb": "Cr2O3", "optc": "K2O", "optd": "MnO", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The concentration (weight %) of nitric acid produced by the oxidation of ammonia and absorption of nitrogen oxides with water is about __________ percent.", "opta": "60", "optb": "30", "optc": "95", "optd": "100", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Urea is a __________ fertiliser.", "opta": "nitrogenous", "optb": "potassic", "optc": "phosphatic", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Calcium ammonium nitrate (CAN) is", "opta": "a mixed fertiliser", "optb": "a straight fertiliser", "optc": "a complex fertiliser", "optd": "not a fertiliser ; it is an explosive", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "CO2 present in reformed gas (obtained by steam reforming of naphtha) is removed by absorbing in", "opta": "mono-ethanolamine (MEA)", "optb": "slaked lime", "optc": "ammoniacal liquor", "optd": "Methyl-Ethyl Ketone (MEK)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which is the most suitable fertiliser for paddy ?", "opta": "CAN", "optb": "Ammonium sulphate", "optc": "Ammonium nitrate", "optd": "Superphosphate", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Ammonium sulphate fertiliser is", "opta": "the highest concentration nitrogenous fertiliser.", "optb": "the best fertiliser for paddy.", "optc": "a basic fertiliser.", "optd": "a neutral fertiliser.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Lower temperature and large excess of ammonia in urea melt", "opta": "increases biuret formation", "optb": "decreases biuret formation", "optc": "is undersirable", "optd": "does not effect biuret formation", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Superphosphate is manufactured by reacting phosphate rock with", "opta": "acetic acid", "optb": "sulphuric acid", "optc": "aluminium chloride", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Vetrocoke solution is", "opta": "a mixture of K2CO3 and As2O3.", "optb": "K2SO4.", "optc": "a mixture of Na2CO3 and As2O3.", "optd": "Na2SO4.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In calcium ammonium nitrate (CAN) fertil-ser", "opta": "nitrate nitrogen is quick acting", "optb": "ammoniacal nitrogen is quick acting", "optc": "nitrate nitrogen is slower acting", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "P2O5 content in triple superphosphate is about __________ percent.", "opta": "42-50", "optb": "15-20", "optc": "85-90", "optd": "70-75", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "H3PO4 is the chemical formula of __________ phosphoric acid.", "opta": "pyro", "optb": "ortho", "optc": "meta", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Heating of orthophosphoric acid to 250\u00b0C produces", "opta": "metaphosphoric acid", "optb": "pyrophosphoric acid", "optc": "no change in it", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Vapor phase reaction of ammonia & nitric acid to produce ammonium nitrate is termed as the __________ process.", "opta": "Haber's", "optb": "Stengel", "optc": "Le-chatlier's", "optd": "Du-pont's", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Use of catalyst is a must in the ammonia manufacture, because the reaction is reversible as well as the heat of dissociation of N2 & H2 is high. The presence of promoter along with the catalyst helps in __________ of the catalyst.", "opta": "stabilisation", "optb": "increasing the effectiveness", "optc": "improving the strength & heat resistance", "optd": "all a, b & c", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Prilling tower is found in the flowsheet for the manufacture of", "opta": "ammonia", "optb": "urea", "optc": "superphosphate", "optd": "triple superphosphate", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Reaction of orthophosphoric acid with soda ash produces", "opta": "sodium tripolyphosphate (STPP)", "optb": "tricresyl phosphate", "optc": "tributyl phosphate", "optd": "nitrophosphate", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Urea is formed only", "opta": "in liquid phase", "optb": "in vapour phase", "optc": "at very high temperature", "optd": "at very low pressure (vacuum)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Dehydration of ammonium carbamate (to produce urea) is a/an __________ reaction.", "opta": "reversible", "optb": "catalytic", "optc": "exothermic", "optd": "endothermic", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Electric process as compared to wet process (for the manufacture of phosphoric acid)", "opta": "can use only high grade phosphate rock.", "optb": "is used less frequently.", "optc": "produces a valuable by-product called gypsum.", "optd": "is weak acid process.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Ammonium sulphate can be produced by reacting gypsum with", "opta": "ammonia", "optb": "ammonium carbonate", "optc": "nitric acid", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Nitrogenous fertiliser is required", "opta": "during the early stage of growth to promote development of stem and leaves.", "optb": "for accelerating fruit formation in later stage of growth.", "optc": "to lessen the effect of excessive potash application.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fertiliser plant making ammonium sulphate employing gypsum-ammonia reaction (usual practice is to use ammonia and sulphuric acid) is located at", "opta": "Rourkela (under SAIL)", "optb": "Bokaro (under SAIL)", "optc": "Sindri (under FCI)", "optd": "Baroda (under G.S.F.C.)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Catalyst used in Haber's process for ammonia production is", "opta": "reduced iron oxide", "optb": "nickel", "optc": "vanadium pentoxide", "optd": "silica gel", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Sodium tri poly phosphate (STPP) is manufactured by reaction of phosphoric acid with sodium", "opta": "carbonate", "optb": "phosphate", "optc": "bicarbonate", "optd": "silicate", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The fluid property, due to which, mercury does not wet the glass is", "opta": "surface tension", "optb": "viscosity", "optc": "cohesion", "optd": "adhesion", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Laminar flow of a Newtonion fluid ceases to exist, when the Reynolds number exceeds", "opta": "4000", "optb": "2100", "optc": "1500", "optd": "3000", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When the momentum of one fluid is used for moving another fluid, such a device is called a/an", "opta": "jet pump", "optb": "blower", "optc": "acid egg", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The normal stress is the same in all directions at a point in a fluid, when the fluid is", "opta": "non-viscous.", "optb": "incompressible.", "optc": "both (a) and (b).", "optd": "having no motion of one fluid layer relative to the other.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Head developed by a centrifugal pump depends on its", "opta": "speed", "optb": "impeller diameter", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Hydraulic mean depth (Dm) for a circular pipe of diameter 'D' flowing full is 0.25 D. For a circular channel, at Dm = 0.3 D, gives the condition for the maximum", "opta": "flow rate", "optb": "mean velocity", "optc": "both 'a' & 'b'", "optd": "neither 'a' nor 'b'", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The head loss in turbulent flow in a pipe varies", "opta": "as velocity", "optb": "as (velocity)2", "optc": "inversely as the square of diameter", "optd": "inversely as the velocity", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Most commonly used joint in the underground pipe lines is the", "opta": "sleevejoint", "optb": "coupling", "optc": "flange", "optd": "expansion joint", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Schedule number of a pipe, which is a measure of its wall thickness, is given by", "opta": "1000 P'/S", "optb": "100 P'/S", "optc": "1000 S/P'", "optd": "10000 P'/S", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The net positive suction head (NPSH) of a centrifugal pump is defined as the sum of the velocity head and the pressure head at the", "opta": "discharge.", "optb": "suction.", "optc": "suction minus vapor pressure of the liquid at suction temperature.", "optd": "discharge minus vapor pressure of the liquid at the discharge temperature.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "With increasing flow rate, the hydraulic efficiency of a centrifugal pump", "opta": "monotonically decreases.", "optb": "decreases and then increases.", "optc": "remains constant.", "optd": "increases and then decreases.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The velocity profile for turbulent flow through a closed conduit is", "opta": "logarithmic", "optb": "parabolic", "optc": "hyperbolic", "optd": "linear", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In case of hydraulically smooth pipe, the resistance to flow depends only on the Reynolds number, whereas for a hydraulically rough pipe, the resistance to flow is governed by the relative roughness. Two pipes are said to have the same hydraulic roughness, when they have equal values of", "opta": "relative roughness.", "optb": "absolute roughness.", "optc": "friction co-efficient for flows at equal Reynold number.", "optd": "all (a), (b) & (c).", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Water hammer in a pipeline results from the", "opta": "bursting of pipelines due to closure by a valve.", "optb": "rapid pressure change due to a rapid change in the rate of flow.", "optc": "pressure increase due to closure of a valve resulting in decrease in rate of flow.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Molten soap mass is transported by a __________ pump.", "opta": "diaphragm", "optb": "reciprocating", "optc": "gear", "optd": "centrifugal", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following denotes the effect of compressibility in fluid flow ?", "opta": "Weber number", "optb": "Mach number", "optc": "Euler number", "optd": "Reynolds number", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Nominal size of the discharge pipe of a pump is usually __________ the nominal size of the inlet pipe.", "opta": "smaller than", "optb": "larger than", "optc": "same as", "optd": "twice", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The terminal velocity of a small sphere settling in a viscous fluid varies as the", "opta": "first power of its dimeter.", "optb": "inverse of the fluid viscosity.", "optc": "inverse square of the diameter.", "optd": "square of the difference in specific weights of solid & fluid.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the discharge of a centrifugal pump is throttled, then its suction lift", "opta": "increases", "optb": "decreases", "optc": "remains unchanged", "optd": "data insufficient to predict", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Foot valves provided in pumps are __________ valves.", "opta": "relief", "optb": "three/four way", "optc": "pressure reducing", "optd": "directional control", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "At high Reynolds number", "opta": "inertial forces control and viscous forces are unimportant.", "optb": "viscous forces predominate.", "optc": "inertial forces are unimportant and viscous forces control.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Power loss in an orificemeter is __________ that in a venturimeter.", "opta": "less than", "optb": "same as", "optc": "more than", "optd": "data insufficient, cannot be predicted", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The terminal velocity of a particle moving through a fluid varies as dpn. What is the value of n' for Newton's law regime ?", "opta": "0.5", "optb": "1", "optc": "1.5", "optd": "3", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "What is the normal range of exit cone angle of a venturimeter ?", "opta": "2 to 5", "optb": "7 to 15", "optc": "15 to 25", "optd": ">25", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The dimension of dynamic viscosity is", "opta": "ML-1T-1", "optb": "L2T-1", "optc": "LT-2", "optd": "ML-1T-2", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A particle A of diameter 10 microns settles in an oil of specific gravity 0.9 and viscosity 10 poise under Stoke's law. A particle B with diameter 20 microns settling in the same oil will have a settling velocity", "opta": "same as that of A.", "optb": "one fourth as that of A.", "optc": "twice as that of A.", "optd": "four times as that of A.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The pitot static tube does not measure the __________ pressure.", "opta": "static", "optb": "total", "optc": "difference in static & dynamic", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The fluid in which the shearing stress within it is proportional to the velocity gradient across the sheared section, is called a __________ fluid.", "opta": "Bingham", "optb": "Newtonion", "optc": "perfect", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In fluid flow, cavitation is caused, if the", "opta": "fluid velocity decreases to zero.", "optb": "total energy decreases.", "optc": "both (a) and (b).", "optd": "flow pressure approaches its vapor pressure at the prevailing temperature.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of the depth of flow to the hydraulic radius for the most economical trapezoidal section, in open channel flow is", "opta": "0.5", "optb": "1", "optc": "1.5", "optd": "2", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The drag co-efficient for a bacterium moving in water at 1 mm/s, will be of the following order of magnitude (assume size of the bacterium to be 1 micron and kinematic  viscosity  of water  to  be 10-6m2/s).", "opta": "24000", "optb": "24", "optc": "0.24", "optd": "0.44", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For Laminar flow through a packed bed, the pressure drop is proportional to (Vs is the superficial liquid velocity and Dp is the particle diameter)", "opta": "Vs/Dp2", "optb": "Vs2/Dp2", "optc": "Vs2/Dp3", "optd": "Vs/Dp3", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum delivery pressure of compressors can be upto __________ atmospheres.", "opta": "10", "optb": "100", "optc": "250", "optd": "1000", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Dimension of surface tension is(where, F = force, L = length)", "opta": "FL-1", "optb": "F-1 . L", "optc": "F.L-2", "optd": "F-2 . L", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not a dimension-less parameter ?", "opta": "Euler number", "optb": "Specific gravity", "optc": "Fanning friction factor", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Co-efficient of velocity is __________ the coefficient of discharge.", "opta": "less than", "optb": "more than", "optc": "equal to", "optd": "not related to", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "All pipes of a particular nominal size have the same", "opta": "inside diameter", "optb": "outside diameter", "optc": "thickness", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For the transfer of solution of thick slurry, the pump used is a __________ pump.", "opta": "reciprocating", "optb": "gear", "optc": "diaphragm", "optd": "centrifugal", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not concerned with the fluid-particle interaction ?", "opta": "Drag co-efficient", "optb": "Froude number", "optc": "Galileo number", "optd": "Weber number", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Maximum theoretical suction lift for water at 15\u00b0C by a centrifugal pump is 34 ft. The same for water at 90\u00b0C will be __________ ft.", "opta": "40", "optb": "34", "optc": "8", "optd": "37", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "Momentum transfer in laminar flow results from veclocity gradient.", "optb": "A fluid in equilibrium is not free from shear stress.", "optc": "The viscosity of a non-Newtonion fluid is a function of temperature only.", "optd": "both (b) and (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pressure drag does not depend upon the", "opta": "roughness of surface of the body.", "optb": "pressure of main flow only.", "optc": "length of the body in flow direction.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Dimension of absolute viscosity is", "opta": "ML-1T-1", "optb": "MLT-1", "optc": "ML-1T", "optd": "MLT", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "__________ pumps are axial flow pumps.", "opta": "Turbine", "optb": "Propeller", "optc": "Diffuser", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Brownian movement is prominent in the particle size range of __________ microns in case of settling of a particle in a fluid.", "opta": "2 to 3", "optb": "0.01 to 0.10", "optc": "200 to 300", "optd": "100 to 1000", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For a particle settling in water at its terminal settling velocity, which of the following is true ?", "opta": "Buoyancy = weight + drag", "optb": "Weight = buoyancy + drag", "optc": "Drag = buoyancy + weight", "optd": "Drag = weight", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A Bingham fluid of viscosity \u03bc = 10 Pa.s and yield stress, \u03c40 = 10 KPa, is shared between flat parallel plates separated by a distance of 10-3 m. The top plate is moving with a velocity of 1 m/s. The shear stress on the plate is", "opta": "10 KPa", "optb": "20 KPa", "optc": "30 KPa", "optd": "40 KPa", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the correct statement.", "opta": "A forced vortex occurs when fluid rotates as a solid about an axis.", "optb": "In laminar flow, Newton's law of viscosity does not apply.", "optc": "A free vortex occurs, when fluidrotates as a solid.", "optd": "In turbulent flow, there are neither cross-currents nor eddies.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Shear stress in a fluid flowing in a round pipe", "opta": "varies parabolically across the cross-section.", "optb": "remains constant over the cross-section.", "optc": "is zero at the centre and varies linearly with the radius.", "optd": "is zero at the wall and increases linearly to the centre.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The resistance wire used in a hot wire anemometer for conducting electrical current is made of", "opta": "copper", "optb": "tungsten", "optc": "chromium", "optd": "aluminium", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Higher efficiency in the combustion of solid fuel can not be achieved by", "opta": "proper fuel preparation.", "optb": "keeping the flue gas exhaust temperature very high.", "optc": "adopting efficient-fuel firing technique & equipment.", "optd": "supplying correct quantity of combustion air.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A coal containing very high percentage of durain is called __________ coal.", "opta": "bright", "optb": "splint", "optc": "non-banded", "optd": "boghead", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "During combustion of gaseous fuels, deficiency of air", "opta": "lengthens the flame.", "optb": "tends to shorten the flame.", "optc": "does not affect the flame length.", "optd": "increases the flame temperature.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Gross and net calorific value of a fuel will be the same", "opta": "if its ash content is zero.", "optb": "ifits carbon content is very low.", "optc": "if its hydrogen/hydrogen compound content is zero.", "optd": "under no circumstances.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Low temperature carbonisation", "opta": "is mainly for producing the smokeless domestic coke.", "optb": "is meant for the production of 'metallurgical coke'.", "optc": "produces higher quantity of gas than high temperature carbonisation.", "optd": "produces less quantity of tar than high temperature carbonisation.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not used as a binder in coal briquetting ?", "opta": "Tar", "optb": "Molasses", "optc": "Pitch", "optd": "Line", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Size of blast furnace grade coke is __________ mm.", "opta": "25-80", "optb": "0-15", "optc": "15-25", "optd": ">100", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Presence of __________ in a dry gaseous fuel does not contribute to its calorific value.", "opta": "sulphur", "optb": "oxygen", "optc": "hydrogen", "optd": "carbon", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The internal energy of the combustion products is __________ compared to that of reactants.", "opta": "more", "optb": "less", "optc": "equal", "optd": "more or less ; (depends on the state of fuel.)", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not a product of tar distillation ?", "opta": "Phenol & naphthalene", "optb": "Benzol & pitch", "optc": "Anthracene & creosote", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Junker's calorimeter is used to determine the calorific value of", "opta": "pulverised coal", "optb": "gaseous fuels", "optc": "fuel oil", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Combustion reaction of fuels is a/an __________ reaction.", "opta": "auto catalytic", "optb": "exothermic", "optc": "endothermic", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Improper storage condition results in the weathering of coal and spontaneous combustion, which increases its", "opta": "caking index.", "optb": "yield of carbonised products.", "optc": "friability & oxygen content.", "optd": "calorific value.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following constituents of coal is the most important in the production of coke?", "opta": "Moisture", "optb": "Ash", "optc": "Volatiles", "optd": "Carbon", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "High temperature in gasification of coal favours", "opta": "high production of CO2.", "optb": "low production of CO2.", "optc": "high production of CO.", "optd": "both (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "LPG is also used as fuel for automobiles & small furnaces and for cutting & welding of metals.", "optb": "The minimum temperature, at which a petroleum oil vapor catches fire and continues to burn, is called its flash point.", "optc": "Each ton of petroleum oil on distillation produces about 30-50 Nm3 of gas.", "optd": "Maximum yield of naphthalene is obtained on distillation of crude oil.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Stack heat losses can be minimised by", "opta": "controlling the excess air.", "optb": "oxygen enrichment of combustion air.", "optc": "using low c.v. fuels.", "optd": "maintaining proper draft in the furnace.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Laboratory gas is obtained by the cracking of", "opta": "gasoline", "optb": "diesel", "optc": "fuel oil", "optd": "kerosene", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Bituminous coal", "opta": "ignites less easily than anthracite.", "optb": "is generally coking.", "optc": "burns with smoky yellow flame.", "optd": "both (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Ratio of primary air to secondary air increases with increase in the rank of coal, because the", "opta": "high rank coals have higher amount of volatile matter.", "optb": "ratio of fixed carbon to volatile matter increases.", "optc": "oxygen      content      progressively decreases.", "optd": "calorific value of the coal increases.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A coal having high amount of volatile matter", "opta": "would require smaller combustion chamber.", "optb": "produces very little of tar and gas on carbonisation.", "optc": "ignites easily and burns with long smoky flame.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Carbon Content by weight in air dried wood may be about __________ percent.", "opta": "10", "optb": "25", "optc": "50", "optd": "80", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following accentuates clinker-ing trouble on furnace grate burning coal ?", "opta": "Low reactivity of carbonised residue containing high proportions of iron & sulphur.", "optb": "Low forced draught and fuel bed temperature.", "optc": "Thick fire bed and preheated primary air.", "optd": "All (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Natural draught produced by a chimney depends upon the", "opta": "density of the chimney gases.", "optb": "height of the chimney.", "optc": "both (a) and (b).", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b).", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Gross & net calorific value is the same for", "opta": "blast furnace gas", "optb": "coke oven gas", "optc": "L.D. converter gas", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Higher percentage of ash in coal meant for the production of metallurgical grade coke", "opta": "decreases the hardness of coke.", "optb": "decreases the abrasion resistance of coke.", "optc": "causes brittleness in steel.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Combustion of pulverised coal as compared to that of lump coal", "opta": "develops a non-luminous flame.", "optb": "develops a low temperature flame.", "optc": "can be done with less excess air.", "optd": "provides a lower rate of heat release.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "'Wobbe index' is a characteristic of", "opta": "solid fuels", "optb": "gaseous fuels", "optc": "liquid fuels", "optd": "fat coals", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A coal with high ash content is undesirable, as", "opta": "it is abrasive to the coal pulveriser (ie.g. ball mill) and the combustion chamber.", "optb": "the ash in molten condition gets absorbed in the pores of the refractory lining of the furnace and causes its spalling due to different co-efficient of expansion/contraction of the refractory and the ash.", "optc": "the ash retains the sulphur & phosphorus and thus affects the quality of products in metallurgical furnace apart from increasing the slag volume. Besides, it may fuse and stick to the boiler tubes thereby reducing the heat transfer.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Presence of free moisture in coal during its high temperature carbonisation", "opta": "reduces the coking time.", "optb": "protects the volatile products from pyrolysis (cracking) in the presence of hot coke and hot oven walls.", "optc": "increases the loss of fine coal dust from the ovens when charging.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Gray King Assay and Swelling Index of a coal is a measure of its", "opta": "swelling characteristics.", "optb": "abradability.", "optc": "agglutinating properties.", "optd": "resistance to impact breakage.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Explosion limit of blast furnace gas is 37 to 71% gas in gas-air mixture. It means that the blast furnace gas will explode when burnt in a confined space, if its concentration in the gas-air mixture is __________ percent.", "opta": "< 37%", "optb": ">71%", "optc": "in between 37 & 71%", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Prime coking coal is always blended with medium or non- coking coal before ear-bonisation", "opta": "to check against its excessive swelling during heating, which may exert high pressure and damage coke oven walls.", "optb": "because, it alone produces unreactive coke.", "optc": "both (a) and (b).", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b).", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Actual flame temperature is always lower than the adiabatic flame temperature, because there is", "opta": "no possibility of obtaining complete combustion at high temperature.", "optb": "always loss of heat from the flame.", "optc": "both (a) and (b).", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b).", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Coke oven gas consists mainly of", "opta": "H2, & CH4", "optb": "CO, & CO2", "optc": "H2, & CO", "optd": "CH4, & CO", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fuel gases containing hydrocarbons (ie.g. coke oven gas) are not preheated before burning, mainly because", "opta": "the hydrocarbons crack thereby choking and fouling the heat transfer surface by carbon soot.", "optb": "it reduces its calorific value tremendously.", "optc": "it reduces its flame temperature tremendously.", "optd": "there are chances of explosion during preheating.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is the most reactive (as regards the formation of CO + H2 from C + H2O) ?", "opta": "Blast furnace coke", "optb": "Low temperature coke", "optc": "Anthracite coal", "optd": "Sub-bituminous coal", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Calorific value of coal middling generated in coal washeries during washing of coal may be around __________ Kcal/kg.", "opta": "1000", "optb": "4000", "optc": "6000", "optd": "8000", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Flue gas discharge velocity through chimney of a big thermal power plant may be around __________ m/sec.", "opta": "0.5", "optb": "10", "optc": "50", "optd": "500", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is used for making the explosive 'TNT' ?", "opta": "Benzol", "optb": "Toluene", "optc": "Pyridine", "optd": "Cerosote", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Adiabatic flame temperature of a fuel is dependent on the initial temperature of", "opta": "fuel", "optb": "air", "optc": "both (a) & (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following gaseous fuels has the lowest calorific value ?", "opta": "Gobar gas", "optb": "Refinery gas", "optc": "Converter gas", "optd": "Blast furnace gas", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not a by-product recovered in a high temperature coal carbonisation plant ?", "opta": "Benzol", "optb": "Pitch-cresosote mixture (PCM)", "optc": "Napthalene", "optd": "Ethylene", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pensky-Marten apparatus is used for those oils, whose flash points are __________ \u00b0F.", "opta": "<120", "optb": ">120", "optc": "<90", "optd": "90-110", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In high temperature carbonisation of coal compared to low temperature carbonisation", "opta": "yield of ammonia is less.", "optb": "aromatic content of tar is low.", "optc": "H2 content in the coke oven gas is more.", "optd": "calorific value of the coke oven gas is lower.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When incomplete combustion loss is high, the flue gas analysis shows large amount of", "opta": "CO2", "optb": "CO", "optc": "O2", "optd": "C", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The gas which contributes maximum to the heating value of natural gas is", "opta": "CO", "optb": "CO2", "optc": "H2", "optd": "CH4", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The temperature at which plastic layer formation takes place during carbonisation of coal varies from __________ \u00b0C.", "opta": "100 to 150", "optb": "350 to 450", "optc": "550 to 650", "optd": "700 to 850", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Yield of coke oven gas in low temperature carbonisation of coal is about __________ Nm3 /ton of dry coal.", "opta": "60", "optb": "160", "optc": "500", "optd": "750", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Temperature of preheated air used for the transportation of pulverised coal through pipes to the burner of a boiler furnace is restricted to a maximum limit of about 300\u00b0 C to avoid the", "opta": "requirement of large volume combustion chamber.", "optb": "risk of explosion.", "optc": "chances of clinker formation.", "optd": "incomplete combustion of coal.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Cement Kiln is a", "opta": "rotary Kiln", "optb": "tunnel Kiln", "optc": "natural draft furnace", "optd": "batch furnace", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a furnace employing forced draught as compared to induced draught,", "opta": "air is sucked in, so air leaks are more and hence the furnace efficiency is reduced.", "optb": "the fan operates hot and hence blades are liable to corrosion and erosion.", "optc": "positive pressure exists in the furnace.", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Regenerators are installed in", "opta": "coke ovens", "optb": "open hearth furnace", "optc": "both (a) & (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is a heat treatment furnace ?", "opta": "Muffle furnace", "optb": "Annealing furnace", "optc": "Reheating furnace", "optd": "Rotary kiln", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "__________ atmosphere is maintained inside an iron blast furnace.", "opta": "Oxidising", "optb": "Reducing", "optc": "Inert", "optd": "Decarburising", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Example of an indirectly heated furnace is", "opta": "hood annealing furnace", "optb": "muffle furnace", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which furnace employs preheating, heating and soaking zones ?", "opta": "Soaking pit", "optb": "Reheating furnace", "optc": "Open hearth furnace", "optd": "Cupola", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Calcination of limestone to produce lime is done in a __________ kiln.", "opta": "tunnel", "optb": "rotary", "optc": "vertical shaft", "optd": "both (b) and (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Thickness of stock does not affect the fuel economy of furnaces, if the material to be heated is of", "opta": "low emissivity", "optb": "high thermal conductivity", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Ceramic recuperators compared to metallic recuperators for the same duty", "opta": "are lighter.", "optb": "occupy more space.", "optc": "are less costly.", "optd": "have higher pressure differential between flue gas & air side.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In order to maintain a reducing atmosphere in a furnace, it should have", "opta": "no O2 in flue gas", "optb": "CO in flue gas", "optc": "high excess air", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which is the most thermally efficient furnace ?", "opta": "Reheating furnace", "optb": "Reverberatory furnace", "optc": "Rotary kilns", "optd": "Boiler furnace", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The heat recoverable from flue gases of furnaces depends on the", "opta": "thermal efficiency of furnace.", "optb": "quantity of flue gases.", "optc": "flue gas temperature drop through the furnace.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Ceramic recuperators (made of SiC) is economical, only when used for preheating combustion air above __________ \u00b0C.", "opta": "250", "optb": "650", "optc": "850", "optd": "1000", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which is a continuous furnace ?", "opta": "Coke ovens", "optb": "Annealing furnace", "optc": "Glass tank furnace", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is the most suitable for preheating combustion air above 650\u00b0C ?", "opta": "Regenerator", "optb": "Metallic recuperator", "optc": "Ceramic recuperator", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Soaking pits are meant for heating steel", "opta": "ingots", "optb": "coils", "optc": "sheets", "optd": "slabs", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The purpose of controlling the furnace atmosphere is to prevent surface attack by", "opta": "oxidation/scaling", "optb": "decarburising", "optc": "sulphur penetration", "optd": "either of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Thermal efficiency of a limestone calcination rotary kiln may be around __________ percent.", "opta": "20", "optb": "40", "optc": "65", "optd": "80", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In producer gas making furnace, steam is added along with air to mainly control the", "opta": "fusion of coal ash & clinker formation.", "optb": "C. V. of producer gas.", "optc": "temperature of producer gas.", "optd": "tar content in producer gas.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fuel used in B.F. stove is", "opta": "pulverised coal", "optb": "furnace oil", "optc": "blast furnace gas/mixed gas", "optd": "coke oven gas", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Tunnel kilns are usually used for", "opta": "roasting of pyrites.", "optb": "drying/tempering of refractories.", "optc": "reheating of slabs.", "optd": "melting of glass.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The thermal efficiency of a steel slab reheating furnace (walking beam type) may be about __________ percent.", "opta": "15", "optb": "40", "optc": "70", "optd": "85", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Higher furnace temperature can not be achieved by use of a lean fuel gas in the furnace by", "opta": "increasing the draft in the furnace.", "optb": "preheating the fuel gas.", "optc": "oxygen enrichment of combustion air.", "optd": "preheating the combustion air.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Temperature of a furnace fired with low calorific value fuel gas (i.e. lean gas) can be increased by", "opta": "preheating the combustion air.", "optb": "oxygen enrichment of combustion air.", "optc": "preheating the fuel gas.", "optd": "all (a), (b) & (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Ceramic coating material for furnace refractory, which increases its emissivity and thus the radiation heat transfer rate in the furnace, comprises of", "opta": "graphite powder", "optb": "thoria", "optc": "zircon powder", "optd": "beryllium", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In reverberatory furnace, charge is heated mainly by", "opta": "conduction.", "optb": "natural convection.", "optc": "radiation of heat from the roof of the combustion chamber.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An example of a periodic furnace is the", "opta": "blast furnace stoves", "optb": "blast furnace", "optc": "coke oven heating chamber", "optd": "rotary kilns", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Ostwald charts are meant for", "opta": "computing the excess/deficiency of combustion air.", "optb": "calculation of flue gas temperature.", "optc": "computation of flue gas analysis.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Maximum heat transfer in high temperature furnaces is by", "opta": "conduction", "optb": "convection", "optc": "radiation", "optd": "either (a), (b) or (c); depends on the type of furnace", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is a natural draft furnace ?", "opta": "Blast furnace stoves", "optb": "Power plant boilers", "optc": "Sintering furnace", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To reduce the stack loss, heat recovery from flue gas can be done by", "opta": "preheating of cold stock.", "optb": "preheating of combustion air.", "optc": "steam generation in waste heat boilers.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Large tonnage of refractory bricks are dried in a", "opta": "shaft furnace", "optb": "rotary hearth furnace", "optc": "tunnel kiln", "optd": "muffle furnace", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pulverised fuel fired furnaces employ __________ fuel firing.", "opta": "horizontal", "optb": "vertical", "optc": "tangential", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not a directly fired furnace ?", "opta": "By-product coke oven", "optb": "Calcination kiln", "optc": "Sintering furnace", "optd": "Open hearth furnace", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The reason for excessive clinker formation in gas producers is the", "opta": "use of coal/coke containing a high % of fines and ash.", "optb": "use of fuel having too low an ash fusion temperature.", "optc": "development of hot spots in the fuel bed and an abnormally high rate of gasification.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not an additive for flue gases from furnace to reduce its dew-point?", "opta": "Ammonia", "optb": "Fine dolomite", "optc": "Alkaline powders", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Acid dew point temperature (ADT) of a flue gas produced by the combustion of a fuel containing 1% sulphur may be about __________ \u00b0C.", "opta": "80", "optb": "130", "optc": "180", "optd": "250", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Low stack loss indicates the", "opta": "use of sub-stoichiometric air for combustion.", "optb": "efficient use of fuel.", "optc": "inefficient use of fuel.", "optd": "oxygen enrichment of combustion air.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Thermal efficiency of blast furnace stoves used for heating blast (air) may be about __________ percent.", "opta": "20", "optb": "40", "optc": "60", "optd": "80", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Heat transfer rate to the stock/charge in the furnace does not depend upon the", "opta": "emissivity of the refactory walls.", "optb": "size of the furance.", "optc": "use of waste heat recovery equipments.", "optd": "thickness of the stock.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Coke ovens in steel plant are heated by", "opta": "electricity", "optb": "blast furnace gas/mixed gas", "optc": "coke oven gas", "optd": "both (b) and (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Power required in case of forced draught as compared to induced draught (for the same draught produced) is", "opta": "same", "optb": "less", "optc": "more", "optd": "either more or less; depends on the flue gas density", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Means for giving direction to the circulation of gases in furnaces are", "opta": "fans.", "optb": "arrangement of heating stock in the furnaces.", "optc": "location of outlet ports and heating & combustion devices.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The amount of combustible escaping uncon-sumed from the furnace, depends upon the", "opta": "air supplied and furnace temperature.", "optb": "burner design (thoroughness of mixing versus stratification).", "optc": "air preheat and the flow of gases in the furnace (mixing by induction, by acceleration or by change of direction).", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "__________ is an indirectly heated furnace.", "opta": "Open hearth furnace", "optb": "Muffle furnace", "optc": "Soaking pit", "optd": "Reheating furnace", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The thermal efficiency of an air/fuel gas preheating recuperator may be as high as __________ percent.", "opta": "50", "optb": "65", "optc": "85", "optd": "99", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a muffle furnace, the muffle", "opta": "retards the heat transfer.", "optb": "assists in temperature equalisation in the charge.", "optc": "permits the use of controlled atmosphere for the protection of stock.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which is not a hearth furnace ?", "opta": "Glass tank furnace", "optb": "Open hearth furnace", "optc": "Cupola", "optd": "Reheating furnace", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An example of shaft furnace is the", "opta": "L.D. converter", "optb": "glass melting tank", "optc": "blast furnace", "optd": "soaking pit", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Crystal size in a continuous crystalliser depends upon the", "opta": "rate of heat transfer.", "optb": "degree of turbulence.", "optc": "degree of supersaturation.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Heat waves", "opta": "can not pass through vacuum.", "optb": "travel in straight line.", "optc": "can be reflected by a mirror.", "optd": "both (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Air is best heated with steam in a heat exchanger of", "opta": "plate type.", "optb": "double pipe type with fin on steam side.", "optc": "double pipe type with fin on air side.", "optd": "shell and tube type.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is generally considered as opaque surface towards radiations?", "opta": "Gases", "optb": "Solids", "optc": "Liquids", "optd": "Both (b) and (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Black liquor generated during paper manufacture is concentrated in a", "opta": "single effect evaporator.", "optb": "single effect evaporator followed by a crystalliser.", "optc": "multiple effect evaporator.", "optd": "multiple effect evaporators followed by a crystalliser.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When vaporisation takes place directly at the heating surface, it is called", "opta": "film boiling", "optb": "nucleate boiling", "optc": "vapour binding", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Steam consumption in kg/hr in case of an evaporator is given by (where, C & E are capacity the economy of the evaporator respectively)", "opta": "C/E", "optb": "E/C", "optc": "CE", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Reynold's analogy states that", "opta": "Nst \u03b1 f", "optb": "Nst \u03b1 NRe", "optc": "NNu \u03b1 f", "optd": "NRe \u03b1 f", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "With increase in temperature, the thermal conductivity of non-metallic amorphous solids", "opta": "decreases", "optb": "increases", "optc": "remains constant", "optd": "first decreases upto certain temperature and then increases", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fourier's law applies to the heat transfer by", "opta": "convection", "optb": "radiation", "optc": "conduction", "optd": "all (a), (b) & (c)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Shell side pressure drop in a shell and tube heat exchanger does not depend upon the", "opta": "baffle spacing & shell diameter.", "optb": "tube diameter & pitch.", "optc": "viscosity, density & mass velocity of shell side fluid.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the equation Q = UA\u0394t; \u0394t is", "opta": "geometric mean temperature difference.", "optb": "arithmetic mean temperature difference.", "optc": "logarithmic mean temperature difference.", "optd": "the difference of average bulk temperatures of hot and cold fluids.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "With increase in porosity, the thermal conductivity of a solid substance", "opta": "increases", "optb": "decreases", "optc": "remains unchanged", "optd": "may increase or decrease; depends on the solid", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For an ideal black body", "opta": "absorptivity = 1", "optb": "reflectivity = 1", "optc": "emissivity = 0", "optd": "transmissivity = 1", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In Joule's experiment, an insulated container contains 20 kg of water initially at 25\u00b0C. It is stirred by an agitator, which is made to turn by a slowly falling body weighing 40 kg through a height of 4 m. The process is repeated 500 times. The acceleration due to gravity is 9.8 ms-2. Neglecting the heat capacity of agitator, the temperature of water (in \u00b0C) is", "opta": "40.5", "optb": "34.4", "optc": "26.8", "optd": "25", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fouling factor", "opta": "is a dimensionless quantity.", "optb": "does not provide a safety factor for design.", "optc": "accounts for additional resistances to heat flow.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In case of vertical tube evaporator, with increase in liquor level, the overall heat transfer co-efficient", "opta": "increases", "optb": "decreases", "optc": "is not affected", "optd": "may increase or decrease; depends on the feed", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The steam ejector is used to", "opta": "remove condensate from the steam pipelines.", "optb": "create vacuum.", "optc": "superheat the steam.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For shell and tube heat exchanger, with increasing heat transfer area, the purchased cost per unit heat transfer area", "opta": "increases", "optb": "decreases", "optc": "remains constant", "optd": "passes through a maxima", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The thermal efficiency of a reversible heat engine operating between two given thermal reservoirs is 0.4. The device is used either as a refrigerator or as a heat pump between the same reservoirs. Then the coefficient of performance as a refrigerator (COP)R and the co-efficient of performance as a heat pump (COP)HP are", "opta": "(COP)R =  (COP)HP = 0.6", "optb": "(COP)R = 2.5; (COP)HP = 1.5", "optc": "(COP)R = 1.5; (COP)HP = 2.5", "optd": "(COP)R = (COP)HP = 2.5", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Hot water (0.01 m3 /min) enters the tube side of a counter current shell and tube heat exchanger at 80\u00b0C and leaves at 50\u00b0C. Cold oil (0.05 m3/min) of density 800 kg/m3 and specific heat of 2 kJ/kg.K enters at 20\u00b0C. The log mean temperature difference in \u00b0C is approximately", "opta": "32", "optb": "37", "optc": "45", "optd": "50", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a heat exchanger, floating head is provided to", "opta": "facilitate cleaning of the exchanger.", "optb": "increase the heat transfer area.", "optc": "relieve stresses caused by thermal expansion.", "optd": "increase log mean temperature gradient.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Leidenfrost point is a term concerned with the", "opta": "condensation of the saturated vapor on a cold surface.", "optb": "concentration of a corrosive solution by evaporation.", "optc": "heat transfer between two highly viscous liquids.", "optd": "boiling of a liquid on a hot surface.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A process stream of dilute aqueous solution flowing at the rate of10 Kg.s-1 is to be heated. Steam condensate at 95\u00b0C is available for heating purpose, also at a rate of 10 Kg.s-1. A 1 - 1 shell and tube heat exchanger is available. The best arrangement is", "opta": "counter flow with process stream on shell side.", "optb": "counter flow with process stream on tube side.", "optc": "parallel flow with process stream on shell side.", "optd": "parallel flow with process stream on tube side.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Heat produced when a steady state current, I passes through an electrical conductor having resistance, 'R' is", "opta": "IR", "optb": "I2R", "optc": "IR2", "optd": "I2R2", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "Orifice baffles are never used in a shell and tube heat exchanger.", "optb": "Pressure drop on the shell side of a heat exchanger depends upon tube pitch also.", "optc": "In a horizontal tube evaporator, surface blanketing by air is avoided.", "optd": "Split ring type and pull through type floating heads are two commonly used floating heads is heat exchangers.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Convective heat transfer co-efficient in case of fluid flowing in tubes is not affected by the tube length/diameter ratio, if the flow is in the __________ zone.", "opta": "laminar", "optb": "transition", "optc": "both 'a' & 'b'", "optd": "highly turbulent", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The actual temperature drop across the heating surface in an evaporator depends on the", "opta": "feed.", "optb": "depth of liquid over heating surface.", "optc": "pressure difference between steam chest and vapour space.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not used as a medium for high temperature heating ?", "opta": "Dowtherm", "optb": "mercury", "optc": "liquid metal (e.g. molten sodium)", "optd": "fused salts (e.g., an eutectic mixture of 53% KNO3, 40% NaNO2and 7% NaNO3)", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Presence of a non-condensing gas in a condensing vapour", "opta": "increases the rate of condensation.", "optb": "decreases thermal resistance.", "optc": "is desirable to increase the film co-efficient.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Kirchoff s law applies to __________ radiation.", "opta": "total", "optb": "monochromatic", "optc": "both (a)  &  (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "With the increase of temperature, the Col-burn jH factor", "opta": "increases.", "optb": "decreases.", "optc": "remains unchanged.", "optd": "may increase or decrease ; depending on temperature.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In case of evaporators, liquid entrainment results primarily due to", "opta": "high vacuum in the evaporator.", "optb": "high evaporation rate.", "optc": "foaming of the solution.", "optd": "high heat transfer rate.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Baffles in the shell side of a shell and tube heat exchanger", "opta": "increase the cross-section of the shell side liquid.", "optb": "force the liquid to flow parallel to the bank.", "optc": "increase the shell side heat transfer co-efficient.", "optd": "decrease the shell side heat transfer co-efficient.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Air is to be heated by condensing steam. Two heat exchangers are available (i) a shell and tube heat exchanger and (ii) a finned tube heat exchanger. Tube side heat transfer area are equal in both the cases. The recommended arrangement is", "opta": "finned tube heat exchanger with air inside and steam outside.", "optb": "finned tube heat exchanger with air outside and steam inside.", "optc": "shell and tube heat exchanger with air inside tubes and steam on shell side.", "optd": "shell and tube heat exchanger with air on shell side and steam inside tubes.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The unit of heat transfer co-efficient in SI unit is", "opta": "J/M2\u00b0K", "optb": "W/m2\u00b0K", "optc": "W/m\u00b0K", "optd": "J/m\u00b0K", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The number of kg vaporised per kg of steam fed to the evaporator is defined as", "opta": "capacity", "optb": "rate of evaporation", "optc": "economy", "optd": "rate of vaporisation", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "In case of heat transfer by purely forced convection, GR/Re2 \u2264 1.", "optb": "The equivalent diameter of heat transfer for a duct of square cross-section (having each side as 'x') is equal to 4x.", "optc": "Distillation process is not the same as evaporation.", "optd": "The effectiveness of nucleate boiling depends basically on the ease with which the bubbles are formed and detached from the heating surface.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Economy of a multiple effect evaporator is not influenced much by the", "opta": "boiling point elevations", "optb": "temperature of the feed", "optc": "rate of heat transfer", "optd": "ratio of the weight of the thin liquor to thick liquor", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Increasing the liquor level in the evaporator results in the", "opta": "decreased capacity.", "optb": "increase in liquor film co-efficient.", "optc": "decreased effect of hydrostatic head.", "optd": "increased true temperature drop.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The equivalent diameter for pressure drop is __________ that for heat transfer.", "opta": "smaller than", "optb": "greater than", "optc": "equal to", "optd": "not related with", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Controlling heat transfer film co-efficient is the one, which offers __________ resistance to heat transfer.", "opta": "no", "optb": "the least", "optc": "the largest", "optd": "lower", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The heat flux (from outside to inside) across an insulating wall with thermal conductivity, K= 0.04 W/m.\u00b0K and thickness 0.16m is 10 W/m2. The temperature of the inside wall is   - 5\u00b0C. The outside wall temperature is", "opta": "25\u00b0C", "optb": "30\u00b0C", "optc": "35\u00b0C", "optd": "40\u00b0C", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Thermal conductivity of a conducting solid material depends upon its", "opta": "temperature", "optb": "porosity", "optc": "both (a) & (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "The controlling resistance in case of heating of air by condensing steam is in the air film.", "optb": "The log mean temperature difference (LMTD) for counter flow and parallel flow can be theoretically same when any one of the fluids (hot or cold fluid) passes through the heat exchanger at constant temperature.", "optc": "In case of a 1 - 2 shell and tube heat exchanger, the LMTD correction factor value increases sharply, when a temperature cross occurs.", "optd": "Phase change in case of a pure fluid at a given pressure from liquid to vapor or vice-versa occurs at saturation temperature.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The average heat transfer co-efficient for laminar film condensation on vertical surface is inversely proportional to (where, \u0394T = Temperature drop across condensate film )", "opta": "(\u0394T)2", "optb": "\u0394T", "optc": "(\u0394T)1/4", "optd": "(\u0394T)3/2", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Bulk of the convective heat transfer resistance from a hot tube surface to the fluid flowing in it, is", "opta": "in the central core of the fluid.", "optb": "uniformly distributed throughout the fluid.", "optc": "mainly confined to a thin film of fluid near the surface.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is concerned with both heat and mass transfer ?", "opta": "Lewis relationship", "optb": "Nusselt number", "optc": "Kutateladze number", "optd": "Froude number", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A backward feed multiple effect evaporator is better than forward feed for concentrating cold feed, because it provides", "opta": "higher economy", "optb": "lower capacity", "optc": "both (a) & (b)", "optd": "lower economy", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A 10 cm dia steam pipe, carrying steam at 180\u00b0C, is covered with an insulation (conductivity = 0.6 W/m.\u00b0C). It losses heat to the surroundings at 30\u00b0C. Assume a heat transfer co-efficient of 0.8 W/m2.\u00b0C for heat transfer from surface to the surroundings. Neglect wall resistance of the pipe and film resistance of steam. If the insulation thickness is 2 cms, the rate of heat loss from this insulated pipe will be", "opta": "greater than that for uninsulated steam pipe.", "optb": "less than that of the uninsulated steam pipe.", "optc": "equal to that of the uninsulated steam pipe.", "optd": "less than the steam pipe with 5 cms insulation.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Mass transfer rate between two fluid phases does not necessarily depend on the __________ of the two phases.", "opta": "chemical properties", "optb": "physical properties", "optc": "degree of turbulence", "optd": "interfacial area", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a solution containing 0.30 Kg mole of solute and 600 kg of solvent, the molality is", "opta": "0.50", "optb": "0.60", "optc": "2", "optd": "1", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fenske equation determines the", "opta": "maximum number of ideal plates.", "optb": "height of the distillation column.", "optc": "minimum number of theoretical plates.", "optd": "optimum reflux ratio.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The term \"cooling range\" in a cooling tower refers to the difference in the temperature of", "opta": "cold water leaving the tower and the wet bulb temperature of the surrounding air.", "optb": "hot water entering the tower and the wet bulb temperature of the surrounding air.", "optc": "hot water entering the tower and the cooled water leaving the tower.", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is the most suitable for extraction in a system having very low density difference ?", "opta": "Mixer-settler extractor", "optb": "Centrifugal extractor", "optc": "Pulsed extractor", "optd": "Packed extraction tower", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Total reflux in a distillation operation requires minimum", "opta": "reboiler load", "optb": "number of plates", "optc": "condenser load", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c)", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The amount of steam required per unit quantity of distillate in case of steam distillation will be reduced by", "opta": "raising the temperature.", "optb": "lowering the total pressure.", "optc": "both (a) and (b).", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b).", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The difference of wet bulb temperature and adiabatic saturation temperature of unsaturated mixture of any system is", "opta": "+ve", "optb": "-ve", "optc": "zero", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fenske's equation for determining the minimum number of theoretical stages in distillation column holds good, when the", "opta": "relative volatility is reasonably constant.", "optb": "mixture (to be separated) shows negative deviation from ideality.", "optc": "mixture (to be separated) shows positive deviation from ideality.", "optd": "multicomponent distillation is involved.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When the temperature and humidity of air is low, we usually use __________ draft cooling tower.", "opta": "natural", "optb": "forced", "optc": "induced", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the correct statement.", "opta": "In case of liquid-liquid extraction, no separation is possible, if the selectivity of the solvent used is unity.", "optb": "With increase in temperature, the selectivity of the solvent used in solvent extraction decreases.", "optc": "The selectivity of solvent used in solvent extraction is unity at the plait point.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "__________ columns are used for liquid dispersion in a continuous gas phase.", "opta": "Packed", "optb": "Pulse", "optc": "Bubble cap", "optd": "Sieve plate", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Overall efficiency of the distillation column is", "opta": "the ratio of number of ideal plates to actual plates.", "optb": "the ratio of number of actual plates to ideal plates.", "optc": "same as the Murphree efficiency.", "optd": "always more than the point efficiency.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "On addition of solute in the solvent, the __________ of the solution decreases.", "opta": "boiling point", "optb": "freezing point", "optc": "vapour pressure", "optd": "both (b) and (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which is the controlling factor for a drum drier?", "opta": "Diffusion", "optb": "Heat transfer", "optc": "Both (a) and (b)", "optd": "Neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Drying operation under vacuum is carried out to", "opta": "dry those materials which have very high unbound mositure content.", "optb": "reduce drying temperature.", "optc": "increase drying temperature.", "optd": "dry materials having high bound moisture content.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Air initially at 101. 3 kPa and 40\u00b0C and with a relative humidity of 50%, is cooled at constant pressure to 30\u00b0C. The cooled air has a", "opta": "higher dew point.", "optb": "higher absolute (specific) humidity.", "optc": "higher relative humidity", "optd": "higher wet bulb temperature.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Separation of two or more components of a liquid solution can not be achieved by", "opta": "fractional crystallisation", "optb": "liquid extraction", "optc": "absorption", "optd": "evaporation", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Stefan's law describes the mass transfer by", "opta": "diffusion", "optb": "bulk flow", "optc": "both 'a' & 'b'", "optd": "neither 'a' nor 'b'", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "At minimum reflux ratio for a given separation", "opta": "number of plates is zero.", "optb": "number of plates is infinity.", "optc": "minimum number of the theoretical plates is required.", "optd": "separation is most efficient.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Relative humidity is the ratio of the", "opta": "partial pressure of the vapour to the vapour pressure of the liquid at room temperature.", "optb": "partial pressure of the vapour to the vapour pressure of the liquid at gas temperature.", "optc": "actual humidity to saturation humidity.", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In batch distillation with constant reflux, overhead product composition __________ with time.", "opta": "increases", "optb": "decreases", "optc": "does not vary", "optd": "may increase on decrease, depends on the system.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Psychrometry deals with the properties of gas-vapor mixture. Humidity can be determined by the measurement of the __________ of a fibre.", "opta": "electrical resistance", "optb": "thermal conductivity", "optc": "strength", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Heat in BTU necessary to increase the temperature of 1 lb of gas and its accompanying vapour by 1\u00b0F is called the", "opta": "latent heat", "optb": "humid heat", "optc": "specific heat", "optd": "sensible heat", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To increase the absorption factor, (where, G = gas flow rate, S = solvent flow rate)", "opta": "increase both 'G' and 'S'.", "optb": "decrease both 'G' and 'S'.", "optc": "increase 'S' and decrease 'G'.", "optd": "increase 'G' and decrease 'S'", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The mass diffusivity, the thermal diffusivity and the eddy momentum diffusivity are same for, NPr = NSc = __________", "opta": "1", "optb": "0.5", "optc": "10", "optd": "0", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Dew point of a gas-vapour mixture", "opta": "increases with temperature rise.", "optb": "decreases with temperature rise.", "optc": "decreases with decrease in pressure.", "optd": "increases with increase in pressure.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a packed absorption tower, if the equilibrium and operating lines are both straight lines, then the ratio, HETP/HTUOG __________ the absorption factor.", "opta": "increases with increase in", "optb": "is one at unity value of", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following plays an important role in problems of simultaneous heat and mass transfer ?", "opta": "Lewis number", "optb": "Schmidt number", "optc": "Prandtl number", "optd": "Sherwood number", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In case of an absorber, the operating", "opta": "line always lies above the equilibrium curve.", "optb": "line always lies below the equilibrium curve.", "optc": "line can be either above or below the equilibrium curve.", "optd": "velocity is more than the loading velocity.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "As the reflux ratio in a distillation coloumn is increased from the minimum, the", "opta": "slope of the operating line in stripping section decreases.", "optb": "number of plates decreases very slowly first and then more and more rapidly.", "optc": "total cost first decreases and then increases.", "optd": "liquid flow increases while the vapor flow decreases for a system.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Absorption factor is defined as (where, S1 = slope of the operating line S2 = slope of the equilibrium curve)", "opta": "S2/S1", "optb": "S1/S2", "optc": "S1 - S2", "optd": "S1 x S2", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A plait point is the point on the solubility curve, where the tie line reduces to a point. What is the number of plait point for a ternery system containing twopairs of partially miscible liquids ?", "opta": "0", "optb": "1", "optc": "2", "optd": "3", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following remains constant during sensible cooling process ?", "opta": "Specific humidity", "optb": "Partial pressure of vapour", "optc": "Both (a) and (b)", "optd": "Neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Physical absorption is", "opta": "an irreversible phenomenon.", "optb": "a reversible phenomenon.", "optc": "accompanied by evolution of heat.", "optd": "both (b) and (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Make up water is required in a cooling tower to replace the water lost by", "opta": "evaporation", "optb": "drift", "optc": "blowdown and leakage", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following quantities need not be fixed before starting the design of a co-current absorber ?", "opta": "Heat gain or loss", "optb": "Flow rate of entering liquid", "optc": "Flow rate of gas", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Mass transfer co-efficient of liquid is", "opta": "affected more by temperature than that for gases.", "optb": "affected much less by temperature than that for gases.", "optc": "not affected by the temperature.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Absorption accompanied with chemical reaction is exemplified by the absorption of", "opta": "ammonia in water.", "optb": "benzol present in coke oven gas by wash oil.", "optc": "SO2 in alkaline solution.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following unit operations makes use of Thiele-Geddes equation ?", "opta": "Liquid-liquid extraction", "optb": "Solid-liquid extraction", "optc": "Multicomponent absorption with chemical reaction", "optd": "Multicomponent distillation.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following liquid-vapor contacting devices provides maximum contact surface area for a particular duty ?", "opta": "Sieve plate column", "optb": "Bubble cap column", "optc": "Randomly packed column", "optd": "Wetted wall column", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The equipment frequently used for adiabatic humidification-cooling operation with recirculating liquid is", "opta": "natural draft cooling tower", "optb": "induced draft cooling tower", "optc": "spray chamber", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Chemisorption (chemical adsorption) is", "opta": "same as \"Van der Waals\" adsorption.", "optb": "characterised by adsorption of heat.", "optc": "an irreversible phenomenon.", "optd": "a reversible phenomenon.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The rate of solid-liquid extraction is limited by the", "opta": "phase change of the solute as it dissolves in the solvent.", "optb": "diffusion of the solute through the solvent in the pores to the outside of the particle.", "optc": "diffusion of the solute from the solution in contact with the particle to the main bulk of the solution.", "optd": "all 'a', 'b' & 'c'.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Raoult's law applies to the", "opta": "all liquid solutions", "optb": "non-ideal solution only.", "optc": "non-volatile solute.", "optd": "solvents.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In distillation columns, the number of bubble caps per tray primarily depends upon the", "opta": "allowable liquid velocity.", "optb": "allowable gas velocity.", "optc": "allowable gas and liquid velocities.", "optd": "feed composition.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In distillation, overhead product contains", "opta": "only one component", "optb": "two components", "optc": "any number of components", "optd": "only saturated liquid", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "With increase in pressure, the relative volatility for a binary system", "opta": "increases.", "optb": "decreases.", "optc": "remains same.", "optd": "either (a) or (b), depends on the system.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Low viscosity absorbent is preferred for reasons of", "opta": "rapid absorption rates and good heat transfer characteristics.", "optb": "improved flooding characteristics.", "optc": "low pressure drop on pumping.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Mass transfer co-efficient (K) and diffusivity (D) are related according to film theory as", "opta": "K \u221d D", "optb": "K  \u221dD", "optc": "K  \u221d D1.5", "optd": "K  \u221d D2", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The behaviour of visco-elastic material is time dependent. This behaviour is common in __________ materials.", "opta": "non-crystalline solid", "optb": "crystalline", "optc": "rubberry", "optd": "non-crystalline organic polymeric.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Coke oven regenerators are made of __________ bricks.", "opta": "fire clay", "optb": "silica", "optc": "low thermal conductivity", "optd": "high electrical conductivity", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is universally employed as the low expansion metal in the bimetallic thermometer, which is an iron-nickel alloy containing 36% nickel and has very low co-efficient of expansion (l/20th of ordinary metals) ?", "opta": "Invar", "optb": "Constantan", "optc": "Chromel", "optd": "Alumel", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Shock resisting steels should possess high", "opta": "hardness", "optb": "toughness", "optc": "tensile strength", "optd": "wear resistance", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The purpose of nitriding the steel is to", "opta": "harden its surface.", "optb": "soften its surface.", "optc": "improve its reliability.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Ceramic recuperators are generally made of", "opta": "silicon carbide.", "optb": "calcium carbide.", "optc": "fireclay bricks.", "optd": "high alumina bricks.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Hammers and railway rails are normally made of", "opta": "mild steel", "optb": "dead mild steel", "optc": "medium carbon steel", "optd": "high carbon steel", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Softness of silver can be converted into hardness by alloying it with small quantity of", "opta": "copper & nickel", "optb": "zinc", "optc": "aluminium", "optd": "tin", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The addition of antimony in tin-based alloys improves its", "opta": "rupture strength and hot hardness.", "optb": "impact strength and bonding strength.", "optc": "deformation resistance.", "optd": "wear resistance.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The melleability of a material is the property by virtue of which it can be rolled or hammered into thin sheets. Which of the following materials has the miximum malleability ?", "opta": "Lead", "optb": "Copper", "optc": "Aluminium", "optd": "Wrought iron", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The main purpose of galvanising iron sheets is to", "opta": "harden the surface.", "optb": "increase its glossiness and lustre.", "optc": "prevent the action of water.", "optd": "prevent the action of oxygen.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The impure iron (pig iron) that is tapped out from blast furnace contains about __________ percent carbon.", "opta": "0.2", "optb": "2", "optc": "4", "optd": "8", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Invar used in thermocouples is an alloy of nickel and", "opta": "iron", "optb": "copper", "optc": "chromium", "optd": "lead", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Nickel (56%) and molybdenum (17%) alloys are called", "opta": "monel", "optb": "hastealloy C", "optc": "inconel", "optd": "bronzes", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Lead pipes are not safe for carrying drinking water because water containing dissolved oxygen attacks lead thereby forming poisonous Pb (OH)2. Lead pipes are readily corroded by", "opta": "dilute HCI", "optb": "acetic acid", "optc": "concentrated H2SO4", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Constituents of stellite are", "opta": "zinc, copper and nickel.", "optb": "cobalt, chromium and tungsten.", "optc": "zinc, aluminium and nickel.", "optd": "nickel, cobalt and vanadium.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Residual magnetism in steel for magnets is increased by the addition of", "opta": "nickel", "optb": "cobalt", "optc": "tungsten", "optd": "chromium", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Presence of nickel in steel improves its", "opta": "corrosion resistance.", "optb": "cutting ability.", "optc": "wear resistance.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Cementite is", "opta": "Fe3C chemically.", "optb": "a compound of carbon and iron.", "optc": "characterised by an orthorhombic crystal structure.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Acetylene gas holder is made of", "opta": "copper", "optb": "cast iron", "optc": "steel", "optd": "monel metal", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Sulphur melting pit in the sulphuric acid plant is made of", "opta": "lead lined stainless steel.", "optb": "cast iron.", "optc": "steel or cement-brick lined.", "optd": "hard wood.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The hardest material just prior to diamond in Mho's scale is", "opta": "topax", "optb": "carborundum", "optc": "corrundum", "optd": "calcite", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Percentage elongation of a material is a measure of its", "opta": "ductility", "optb": "brittleness", "optc": "toughness", "optd": "malleability", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Chlorination of benzene is done to produce benzene hexachloride (a pesticide) in a photochemical reactor lined with", "opta": "karbate", "optb": "lead or glass", "optc": "fireclay bricks", "optd": "PVC", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Heavy duty bearings are usually made of", "opta": "white metal", "optb": "phosphorous bronze", "optc": "monel", "optd": "zinc", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Dielectric strength of a material is", "opta": "its energy stroage capacity.", "optb": "a magnetic property.", "optc": "its capacity to resist the flow of current.", "optd": "its capacity to withstand high voltage.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following stainless steels is non-magnetic ?", "opta": "Ferritic", "optb": "Martensitic", "optc": "Austenitic", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "18-4-1 high speed steel contains 18%, 4% and 1% respectively of", "opta": "tungsten, vanadium and chromium", "optb": "tungsten, chromium and vanadium", "optc": "vanadium, chromium and tungsten", "optd": "chromium, tungsten and vanadium", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Aluminium as a material of construction suffers from the disadvantage of", "opta": "very high cost.", "optb": "rather low tensile strength.", "optc": "very low strength to weight ratio.", "optd": "scarce availability.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Babbit metal used for bearings is a____base alloy.", "opta": "tin", "optb": "lead", "optc": "aluminium", "optd": "copper", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "18/8 steel is a/an __________ stainless steel.", "opta": "austenitic", "optb": "ferritic", "optc": "martensitic", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Cast iron has very high", "opta": "compressive strength", "optb": "ductility", "optc": "shock resistance", "optd": "resistance to brittleness", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Liquid ammonia is shipped in __________ containers.", "opta": "steel", "optb": "aluminium", "optc": "glass", "optd": "lead lined", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Cermets are __________ materials.", "opta": "refractory", "optb": "reinforced", "optc": "abrasive", "optd": "fully metallic", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Cast irons are generally specified by their", "opta": "carbon content", "optb": "tensile strength", "optc": "hardness", "optd": "manufacturing proces", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Austenitic manganese steel used for making jaws of crushing machines contains about __________ percent manganese.", "opta": "1.5-2", "optb": "3.5-4.5", "optc": "7-9", "optd": "12-14", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "White cast iron is not", "opta": "malleable", "optb": "whitish in color", "optc": "brittle", "optd": "strong and hard", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Galvanised iron is", "opta": "harder", "optb": "protected from rusting", "optc": "alumina coated iron", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "German silver used for decorative purposes contains maximum percentage of", "opta": "silver", "optb": "copper", "optc": "zinc", "optd": "nickel", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The metals occuring at the lower most position in the electromotive series", "opta": "do not resist corrosion.", "optb": "resist corrosion very strongly.", "optc": "are very brittle.", "optd": "are heat insulators.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "German silver in an alloy of", "opta": "copper, nickel and zinc.", "optb": "copper, aluminium and silver.", "optc": "silver, zinc and aluminium.", "optd": "silver, nickel and zinc.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A suitable material of construction to use with fuming sulphuric acid is", "opta": "carbon steel", "optb": "stainless steel type 304", "optc": "nickel", "optd": "monel", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following crystal structures characterises the austenitic stainless steel?", "opta": "Simple hexagonal", "optb": "Body centred cubic", "optc": "Face centred cubic", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Caustic soda is produced in a mercury cell having anode and cathode made respectively of moving mercury and", "opta": "moving mercury and graphite.", "optb": "graphite and moving mercury.", "optc": "moving mercury and carbon.", "optd": "moving mercury and crimped steel wire.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Addition of __________ in steel can help in increasing the depth of hardness.", "opta": "nickel", "optb": "chromium", "optc": "vanadium", "optd": "tungsten", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following has the highest compressive strength ?", "opta": "Wrought iron", "optb": "Cast iron", "optc": "Mild steel", "optd": "High carbon steel", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Zinc is not used", "opta": "for producing zinc base die casting alloys.", "optb": "in its oxide form as pigments.", "optc": "as anode for corrosion prevention in boiler.", "optd": "as an alloying element in various bronzes.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Refined acetic acid storage vessel are made of", "opta": "copper", "optb": "aluminium", "optc": "high carbon steel", "optd": "nickel", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Addition of __________ to the steel helps in increasing the residual magnetism in steel used for making magnets.", "opta": "chromium", "optb": "nickel", "optc": "tungsten", "optd": "cobalt", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Constantan is an alloy of", "opta": "Cu (55%) & Sn (45%).", "optb": "Cu (55%) & Ni (45%).", "optc": "Pt (95%) & Rh (10%).", "optd": "Fe (80%) & Ni (20%).", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Short distance transportation of grain, gravel, sand, ash, asphalt etc. is done by using a __________ conveyor.", "opta": "flight", "optb": "slat or drag", "optc": "ribbon", "optd": "screw", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Equivalent diameter of a particle is the diameter of the sphere having the same", "opta": "ratio of surface to volume as the actual volume.", "optb": "ratio of volume to surface as the particle.", "optc": "volume as the particle.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If dp is the equivalent diameter of a non-spherical particle, Vp its volume and sp its surface area, then its sphericity is \u03a6s is defined by", "opta": "\u03a6s = 6 Vp/dp sp", "optb": "\u03a6s = Vp/dp sp", "optc": "\u03a6s = 6 dp Sp/Vp", "optd": "\u03a6s = dp Sp/Vp", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Power required to drive a ball mill with a particular ball load is proportional to (where, D = diameter of ball mill )", "opta": "D", "optb": "1/D", "optc": "D2.5", "optd": "1/D2.5", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "Recycled coarse material to the grinder by a classifier is termed as circulating load.", "optb": "Wear and tear in wet crushing is more than that in dry crushing of materials.", "optc": "Size enlargement (opposite of size reduction) is not a mechanical operation.", "optd": "A 'dust catcher' is simply an enlargement in a pipeline which permits the solids to settle down due to reduction in velocity of the dust laden gas.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In continuous filtration (at a constant pressure drop), filtrate flow rate varies inversely as the", "opta": "square root of the velocity.", "optb": "square of the viscosity.", "optc": "filtration time only.", "optd": "washing time only.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For sizing of fine materials, the most suitable equipment is a", "opta": "trommel", "optb": "grizzly", "optc": "shaking screen", "optd": "vibrating screen", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not categorised as a \"mechanical operation\" ?", "opta": "Agitation", "optb": "Filtration", "optc": "Size enlargement", "optd": "Humidification", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is a pressure filter ?", "opta": "Leaf filter (Moore filter).", "optb": "Plate and flame filter.", "optc": "Rotary drum filter.", "optd": "Sand filter.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Tabular bowl centrifuges as compared to disk bowl centrifuges", "opta": "operate at higher speed.", "optb": "employ bowl of larger diameter.", "optc": "can not be operated under pressure/vacuum.", "optd": "can't be used for separation of fine suspended solids from a liquid.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pebble mills are tumbling mills widely used for grinding in the manufacture of paints & pigments and cosmetic industries, where iron contamination in the product is highly objectionable. Pebbles used in pebble mill are made of", "opta": "bronze", "optb": "stainless steel", "optc": "flint or porcelain", "optd": "concrete", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Filter aids like asbestos, kieselguhr, diatomaceous earth etc. are used to increase the porosity of the final filter cake & reducing the cake resistance during filtration. Filter aid is", "opta": "added to the feed slurry.", "optb": "precoated on the filter medium prior to filtration.", "optc": "separated from the cake by dissolving solids or by burning it off.", "optd": "all 'a', 'b'&'c'.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following relationships between co-efficinet of friction (\u03bc) between rock & roll and a (half of the angle of nip) of the particle to be crushed is correct ?", "opta": "\u03bc > tan \u03b1", "optb": "\u03bc \u2265 tan \u03b1", "optc": "\u03bc > tan 2\u03b1", "optd": "\u03bc \u2264 tan \u03b1", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement pertaining to the roll crushers.", "opta": "Maximum feed size determines the required roll diameter.", "optb": "For hard material's crushing, the reduction ratio should not exceed 4.", "optc": "Both the rolls run necessarily at the same speed.", "optd": "Reduction ratio and differential roll speed affect production rate & energy consumed per unit of surface produced.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not an ultrafine grinder (colloid mill)?", "opta": "Micronizers", "optb": "Agitated mills and fluid energy mills", "optc": "Toothed roll crusher", "optd": "Hammer mills with internal classification", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Two particles are called to be equal settling, if they are having the same.", "opta": "size.", "optb": "specific gravity.", "optc": "terminal velocities in the same fluid & in the same field of force.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is the most suitable for handling fibrous and dense slurries ?", "opta": "Propeller agitator", "optb": "Cone type agitator", "optc": "Turbine agitator", "optd": "Radial propeller agitator", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "__________ centrifuge is normally used in sugar mills.", "opta": "Tubular bowl", "optb": "Disc-bowl", "optc": "Suspended batch basket", "optd": "Perforated horizontal basket continuous", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Solid particles separation based on the difference in their flow velocities through fluids is termed as the", "opta": "clarification", "optb": "classification", "optc": "elutriation", "optd": "sedimentation", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Diatomaceous earth is a/an", "opta": "explosive", "optb": "filter aid", "optc": "filter medium", "optd": "catalyst", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The distribution given by microscopic analysis of powder is", "opta": "number", "optb": "length", "optc": "area", "optd": "volume", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Number of particles in a crushed solid sample is given by (where, m = mass of particles in a sample, Vp = volume of one particle, \u03c1= density of particles)", "opta": "m/\u03c1 . Vp", "optb": "m . \u03c1/Vp", "optc": "m . Vp/\u03c1", "optd": "Vp/m . \u03c1", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For a non-spherical particle, the sphericity", "opta": "is defined as the ratio of surface area of a sphere having the same volume as the particle to the actual surface area of the particle.", "optb": "has the dimension of length.", "optc": "is always less than 1.", "optd": "is the ratio of volume of a sphere having the same surface area as the particle to the actual volume of the particle.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In washing type plate and frame filter press, the ratio of washing rate to the final filtrate rate is", "opta": "4", "optb": "1/4", "optc": "1", "optd": "1/2", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Ball mills and tube mills with flint or porcelain balls are used for size reduction of", "opta": "asbestos", "optb": "rubber", "optc": "non-metallic ores", "optd": "limestone", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Size reduction of __________ is accomplished in steam heated rollers and roll crushers.", "opta": "resins", "optb": "gums", "optc": "hard rubber", "optd": "waxes", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The capacity of a belt conveyor depends upon two factors. If one is the cross-section of the load, the other is the __________ of the belt.", "opta": "speed", "optb": "thickness", "optc": "length", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not a part of the Blake jaw crusher?", "opta": "Hanger", "optb": "Check plates", "optc": "Toggles", "optd": "Pitman", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If a force greater than that of gravity is used to separate solids & fluids of different densities, the process is termed as the", "opta": "sedimentation", "optb": "flocculation", "optc": "dispersion", "optd": "centrifugation", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Filter aid is used to", "opta": "increase the rate of filtration.", "optb": "decrease the pressure drop.", "optc": "increase the porosity of the cake.", "optd": "act as a support base for the septum.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following mineral dressing operations is termed as 'comminution'?", "opta": "Panning", "optb": "Spiralling", "optc": "Tabling", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The capacity of a pneumatic conveying system depends upon the", "opta": "bulk density of materials.", "optb": "pressure of the conveying air.", "optc": "diameter of the conveying line.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "Close circuit grinding is more economical than open circuit grinding.", "optb": "Cod oil, beef tallow or aluminium stearates are used as grinding aids in cement 'industries'.", "optc": "The equipment used for the removal of traces of solids from a liquid is called a classifier.", "optd": "Size enlargement is a mechanical operation exemplified by medicinal tablet making.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Gravity settling process is not involved in the working of a", "opta": "hydrocyclone", "optb": "classifier", "optc": "dorr-thickener", "optd": "sedimentation tank", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Froth floatation is the most suitable for treating", "opta": "iron ores", "optb": "sulphide ores", "optc": "quartzite", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The energy required per unit mass to grind limestone particles of very large size to 100 \u03bcm is 12.7 kWh/ton. An estimate (using Bond's law) of the energy to grind the particles from a very large size to 50 \u03bcrn is", "opta": "6.35 kWh/ton", "optb": "9.0 kWh/ton", "optc": "18 kWh/ton", "optd": "25.4 kWh/ton", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is the most suitable for cleaning of fine coal dust (<0.5 mm) ?", "opta": "Trough washer", "optb": "Baum jig washer", "optc": "Spiral separator", "optd": "Froth floatation", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the correct statement:", "opta": "Removal of iron from ceramic material is necessitated (by magnetic separation method) so as to avoid discolouration of ceramic products.", "optb": "The operating cost of shaking screen is more than that of a vibrating screen.", "optc": "Screen capacity does not depend upon the specific gravity of the minerals.", "optd": "Asphalt is best crushed using toothed roll crusher.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Range of compressibility co-efficient of the commercial compressible cake obtained in filtration operation is", "opta": "0.01 to 0.1", "optb": "0.1 to 0.3", "optc": "0.2 to 0.8", "optd": "0.2 to 0.4", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Highly viscous liquids & pastes are agitated by", "opta": "propellers", "optb": "turbine agitators", "optc": "multiple blade paddles", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The value of 'angle of nip' is generally about", "opta": "16\u00b0", "optb": "32\u00b0", "optc": "52\u00b0", "optd": "64\u00b0", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Size reduction of the __________ can be suitably done by ball mills, crushing rolls and rod mills.", "opta": "metalliferrous ores", "optb": "non-metallic ores", "optc": "basic slags", "optd": "asbestos & mica", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Sulphuric acid mist is arrested by using a __________ scrubber.", "opta": "packed wet", "optb": "hollow wet", "optc": "venturi", "optd": "co-current", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The main size reduction operation in ultrafine grinders is", "opta": "cutting", "optb": "attrition", "optc": "compression", "optd": "impact", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In case of a hammer crusher,", "opta": "crushing takes place by impact breaking.", "optb": "maximum acceptable feed size is 30 cms.", "optc": "reduction ratio can be varied by adjusting the distance from cage to hammers.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Jigging is a technique by which different particles can be", "opta": "separated by particle size.", "optb": "separated by particle density.", "optc": "separated by particle shape.", "optd": "mixed.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Crushing of mineral particles is accomplished in a 'cage mill', when one or more alloy steel bars are revolved in opposite directions. It is a type of __________ mill.", "opta": "impact", "optb": "roll", "optc": "vibratory", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Balls for ball mills are never made of", "opta": "forged/cast steel", "optb": "lead", "optc": "cast iron", "optd": "alloy steel", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "200 mesh screen means 200 openings per", "opta": "cm2", "optb": "cm", "optc": "inch", "optd": "inch2", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "__________ is the most commonly used 'filter aid'.", "opta": "Diatomaceous earth", "optb": "Fuller's earth", "optc": "Vermiculite", "optd": "Semi-plastic clay", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following may be used to measure the rate of nuclear disintegration?", "opta": "Geiger-Muller Counter", "optb": "Cyclotron", "optc": "Cold chamber", "optd": "Mass spectrograph", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The decrease in the atomic number is not observed in case of", "opta": "electron capture", "optb": "\u03b2-emission", "optc": "\u03b1-emission", "optd": "positron emission", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The mass number of an element is not changed, when it emits __________ radiations.", "opta": "\u03b1 & \u03b2", "optb": "\u03b2 & \u03b3", "optc": "\u03b3 & \u03b1", "optd": "\u03b1, \u03b2, & \u03b3", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is   not   a   naturally occurring nuclear fuel ?", "opta": "Uranium-238", "optb": "Thorium-233", "optc": "Plutonium-239", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An electron has a mass that is approximately __________ that of the proton.", "opta": "1836 (approximately)", "optb": "1/1836 (approximately)", "optc": "1", "optd": "\u221e", "ans": "B", "explanation": "An electron has a mass that is approximately 1/1836.15267245(75) that of the proton."}, {"question": "Which is the most commonly used molten metal for cooling of nuclear reactors ?", "opta": "Calcium", "optb": "Sodium", "optc": "Mercury", "optd": "Zinc", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The amount of a radioactive material (having a half life of 100 years) remaining after 400 years will be __________ of its original weight.", "opta": "1/2", "optb": "1/4", "optc": "1/8", "optd": "1/16", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The second underground nuclear test was conducted by India at", "opta": "Jaisalmer", "optb": "Pokhran", "optc": "Kalpakkan", "optd": "Narora", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is artificially produced as it does not occur in nature ?", "opta": "Uranium-235", "optb": "Uranium-233", "optc": "Plutonium-239", "optd": "Both (b) and (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Gas cooling as compared to water cooling of nuclear reactors", "opta": "can not attain a high temperature.", "optb": "is more efficient as gas has a higher specific heat.", "optc": "can produce only saturated steam for feeding to power turbine.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The decay product of tritium (a beta emitter) is", "opta": "lithium", "optb": "helium", "optc": "deuterium", "optd": "hydrogen", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Heat is generated in a nuclear reactor (thermal) by", "opta": "combustion of a nuclear fuel e.g. uranium.", "optb": "fusion of atoms of uranium.", "optc": "absorption of neutrons in uranium atoms.", "optd": "fission of U-235 by neutrons.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The time taken for a radioactive element to reduce to 50% of its original weight is __________ years, if its half life period is 12 years.", "opta": "24", "optb": "18", "optc": "6", "optd": "36", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following may not need a moderator ?", "opta": "Candu reactor", "optb": "Fast breeder reactor", "optc": "Homogeneous reactor", "optd": "Pressurised water reactor", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The amount of a radioisotope remaining undecayed after a time equal to four times its half life, will be __________ percent.", "opta": "3.125", "optb": "6.25", "optc": "12.50", "optd": "25", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fast breeder reactors do not", "opta": "use Th-232 as fissile fuel.", "optb": "convert fertile material to fissile material.", "optc": "use fast neutrons for fission.", "optd": "use molten sodium as coolant.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Thorium-232 is converted into uranium-233 in a/an __________ nuclear reactor.", "opta": "thermal", "optb": "fast breeder", "optc": "heavy water moderated", "optd": "enriched uranium", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following may not need a control rod ?", "opta": "Liquid metal cooled reactor.", "optb": "Fast breeder reactor.", "optc": "Candu reactor.", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One 'amu' is equivalent to", "opta": "9.31 MeV", "optb": "931 eV", "optc": "931 Mev", "optd": "931J", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Commercial power generation from fusion reactor is not yet possible, because", "opta": "it is difficult to control fusion reaction.", "optb": "the fuel required (e.g. deuterium and tritium) is scarce.", "optc": "it is difficult to initiate fusion reaction.", "optd": "quantity of fuel required for initiating fusion reaction is prohibitively high.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Spent fuel from the nuclear thermal reactor contains", "opta": "fission products", "optb": "plutonium", "optc": "unused fuel", "optd": "all (a), (b) & (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A boiling water reactor is the one, in which the", "opta": "coolant water is allowed to boil in the core of the reactor.", "optb": "coolant water, after being heated in the reactor core, generates steam in a boiler.", "optc": "pressurised water is pumped into the core.", "optd": "fuel and the coolant are thoroughly mixed to form a homogeneous solution.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which is used as a coolant in nuclear reactor due to its high capture cross-section ?", "opta": "H2", "optb": "N2", "optc": "He", "optd": "CO2", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Moderating material used in a thermal-reactor should be a", "opta": "good absorber of neutrons.", "optb": "solid substance.", "optc": "poor absorber of neutrons.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Ordinary water is not used as a moderator because, it", "opta": "has a low absorption cross-section.", "optb": "has a low scattering cross-section.", "optc": "absorbs neutrons.", "optd": "does not absorb neutrons.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The atomic number of a radioactive element is not changed, when it emits __________ rays.", "opta": "\u03b1", "optb": "\u03b2", "optc": "\u03b3", "optd": "\u03b1 & \u03b2", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fission of U-235 on slow neutron bombardment can be represented by", "opta": "92U235 + 3 \u03b31  56Ba143 + 36Kr90", "optb": "92U235 + 0n1  56Ba143 + 36Kr90 + 3 0n1", "optc": "92U235 + 0n1  56Ba143 + 36Kr90 + 3 0n1  + Q (energy)", "optd": "92U235 + 0n1  92U236 + 30n1+ Q (energy)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A nuclear reactor can't be used for", "opta": "the production of radioisotopes.", "optb": "supplying intense fields or beams of neutron for scientific experiments.", "optc": "marine ship propulsion.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is a moderating material used in nuclear reactor ?", "opta": "Graphite.", "optb": "Cadmium.", "optc": "Zircalloy (an alloy of zirconium and aluminium).", "optd": "Stainless steel.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The atomic number of an element is equal to the number of __________ present in its atom.", "opta": "neutrons", "optb": "electrons", "optc": "protons", "optd": "either (b) or (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not, a fertile material ?", "opta": "Th-232", "optb": "U-238", "optc": "U-233", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Molten sodium (as a coolant in fast breeder reactor)", "opta": "can't attain high temperature at normal pressure.", "optb": "is not at all corrosive, even at a higher temperature.", "optc": "is highly radioactive at elevated temperatures and can cause explosion, when it comes in contact with air or water.", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Final product of uranium extraction plant at Jadugoda (Bihar) is", "opta": "uranium", "optb": "uranium oxide", "optc": "uranium carbide", "optd": "magnesium diuranate", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one is the radioactive isotope of hydrogen ?", "opta": "Deuterium", "optb": "Ortho-hydrogen", "optc": "Tritium", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A homogeneous reactor is the one, in which the", "opta": "fissile atoms are evenly distributed throughout the mass of nuclear reactor.", "optb": "same substance (e.g. heavy water) is used as moderator & coolant.", "optc": "the fuel and the moderator is mixed to form a homogeneous material.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Hydrogen has __________ isotopes.", "opta": "no", "optb": "one", "optc": "two", "optd": "three", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "MeV is the unit of", "opta": "radioactivity", "optb": "energy", "optc": "potential difference", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Velocity of the thermal neutron (< 0.025 eV) used for fission of U-235 is around __________ m/sec.", "opta": "1", "optb": "2200", "optc": "3 x 1011", "optd": "9 x 1021", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Energy equivlant to one atomic mass unit (amu) is __________ MeV.", "opta": "9.31", "optb": "93.1", "optc": "931", "optd": "9310", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "\"Critical mass\" is the minimum mass of nuclear fissile material required for the", "opta": "sustainment of chain reaction.", "optb": "power generation on commercial scale.", "optc": "economic power generation.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The type of pump used for the recirculation of molten sodium coolant in liquid metal cooled reactor is a/an __________ pump.", "opta": "electromagnetic", "optb": "reciprocating", "optc": "centrifugal", "optd": "volute", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fast breeder Test Reactor (FBTR) is located at", "opta": "Kalpakkam (near Madras).", "optb": "Kota (in Rajasthan).", "optc": "BARC (Trombay).", "optd": "Tarapur (in Maharashtra).", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Tarapur atomic power station", "opta": "has two boiling water reactors of American design.", "optb": "has an installed capacity of 400 MW.", "optc": "is the first power reactor in India, which became critical in 1969.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a nuclear explosion, the energy is released primarily in the form of __________ energy-", "opta": "potential", "optb": "thermal", "optc": "kinetic", "optd": "electrical", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The largest stable nucleus is", "opta": "U-235", "optb": "U-238", "optc": "Pb-206", "optd": "Bi-209", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Hydrogen bomb employs the nuclear fusion of", "opta": "hydrogen", "optb": "deuterium", "optc": "tritium", "optd": "helium", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Sodium melts (at atmospheric pressure) at a temperature of __________ \u00b0C.", "opta": "58", "optb": "98", "optc": "348", "optd": "588", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of volume of an atom to that of its nucleus is", "opta": "1012", "optb": "10-12", "optc": "10-8", "optd": "108", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Research reactors are normally meant for", "opta": "producing high neutron flux 1012-1013 neutrons/cm2, sec and studying the effect of neutron bombardment on dif ferent materials.", "optb": "accelerating the neutrons.", "optc": "power generation.", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Out of the followingplaces, a nuclear power plant is not located at", "opta": "Talcher (Orissa)", "optb": "Kaiga (Karnataka)", "optc": "Rawatbhata (Rajsthan)", "optd": "Kalpakkam (Tamilnadu)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Diesel used in naval applications has a minimum cetane number of", "opta": "25", "optb": "35", "optc": "45", "optd": "65", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following tests is not done for transformer oil ?", "opta": "Flash point and acid value.", "optb": "Aniline point.", "optc": "Dielectric strength.", "optd": "Copper strip corrosion test.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which is the most undesirable component in kerosene ?", "opta": "Aromatics", "optb": "i-paraffins", "optc": "n-paraffins", "optd": "Naphthenes", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement about the smoking tendency of various hydrocarbon constituents of kerosene.", "opta": "Smoking tendency of hydrocarbons increases in the order : paraffins \u2192 isoparaffins \u2192 naphthenes \u2192 aromatics.", "optb": "Smoking tendency of paraffins increases with decrease in its molecular weight.", "optc": "Smoking tendency of naphthenes decreases with its increasing molecular weight & also on addition of double bond.", "optd": "Smoking tendency of aromatics decreases with increase in its molecular weight.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Solvent used in duo-sol extraction for lube oil upgradation is a mixture of", "opta": "propane & phenol-cresol mixture.", "optb": "methyl ethyl ketone & glycol.", "optc": "phenol & furfural.", "optd": "propane & liquid sulphur dioxide.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following fractions of a crude oil will have the maximum gravity API (i.e. \u00b0API) ?", "opta": "Diesel", "optb": "Gasoline", "optc": "Atmospheric gas oil", "optd": "Vacuum gas oil", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For gasoline, the flash point (<50\u00b0C) is determined by the", "opta": "Abel apparatus.", "optb": "Pensky-Marten's apparatus.", "optc": "Saybolt chromometer.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Flash point of atmospheric distillation residue is determined by __________ apparates.", "opta": "Pensky-Martens (closed cup type).", "optb": "Abel.", "optc": "Cleveland (open cup type)", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Maximum sulphur percentage in low sulphur heavy stock (LSHS) furnace oil is about", "opta": "0.1", "optb": "1", "optc": "2.5", "optd": "3.5", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pour point and freezing point is equal for", "opta": "petrol", "optb": "diesel", "optc": "water", "optd": "crude petroleum", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Smoke point of a test sample of kerosene is found to be 15 mm. On removal of __________ from it, the smoke point rises to 25 mm.", "opta": "n-paraffins", "optb": "olefins", "optc": "aromatics", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "__________ is not an important refinery process for upgrading the quality of lubricating oil.", "opta": "Deoiling", "optb": "Solvent refinning", "optc": "Clay treatment", "optd": "Hydrotreatment", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the undesirable property for a solvent meant for dewaxing of lube oil.", "opta": "Complete miscibility with oil.", "optb": "High solubility of wax in the solvent.", "optc": "Both (a) and (b).", "optd": "Neither (a) nor (b).", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is used as a catalyst in fluidised bed catalytic cracking ?", "opta": "Silica-magnesia", "optb": "Silica-alumina", "optc": "Bentonite clays", "optd": "All (a), (b) and (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Casing head gasoline is the liquid", "opta": "butane.", "optb": "propane.", "optc": "natural gas.", "optd": "gasoline separated from wet natural gas by compression.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Most commonly used crude heater before the fractionation tower in a refinery is the __________ heater.", "opta": "electric immersion", "optb": "pipestill", "optc": "steam coil", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Viscosity index of a lubricating oil", "opta": "is the measure of its flash point.", "optb": "is the measure of variation of viscosity with temperature.", "optc": "should be low.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Visbreaking process is used mainly for making", "opta": "high cetane diesel", "optb": "high octane gasoline", "optc": "fuel oil", "optd": "smoke free kerosene", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Operating condition in the electrical dehydrators for crude oil is about", "opta": "6.5 kgf/Cm2 & 95\u00b0C.", "optb": "1 atm. & 110 \u00b0C.", "optc": "20 kgf/cm2 & 110\u00b0C.", "optd": "50 atm. and 150\u00b0C.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Crude oil is pumped by a __________ pump.", "opta": "gear", "optb": "centrifugal", "optc": "screw", "optd": "reciprocating", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Solvent used in the deasphalting process is", "opta": "furfurol", "optb": "phenol", "optc": "propane", "optd": "hexane", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A good lubricant should have high", "opta": "viscosity index", "optb": "volatility", "optc": "pour point", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Complete removal of __________ from gasoline is done by Unisol process using caustic soda and methyl alcohol.", "opta": "waxes", "optb": "mercaptans", "optc": "asphalt", "optd": "diolefins", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The main use of heavy gas oil produced by the vacuum distillation unit is as a", "opta": "blending component for kerosene.", "optb": "blending component for petrol.", "optc": "feedstock for fluid catalytic cracking unit.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Stabilisation of gasoline (petrol) means", "opta": "removal of dissolved gases from it.", "optb": "increasing its oxidation stability.", "optc": "improving its lead susceptibility.", "optd": "increasing its vapour pressure.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In petroleum refining, the process used for conversion of hydrocarbons to aromatics is", "opta": "catalytic cracking", "optb": "catalytic reforming", "optc": "hydrotreating", "optd": "alkylation", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Diesel index.(an alternative index for expressing the quality of diesel) is", "opta": "determined by using a test engine.", "optb": "not related to aniline point.", "optc": "equal to cetane number plus 3.", "optd": "all (a), (b) & (c).", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Octane number of gasoline is a measure of its", "opta": "resistance to knock.", "optb": "ignition delay.", "optc": "ignition temperature.", "optd": "smoke point.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the additive property of a lube oil out of following.", "opta": "\u00b0API gravity", "optb": "Specific gravity", "optc": "Viscosity", "optd": "Flashpoint", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Catalyst used in catalytic reforming is", "opta": "platinum on alumina", "optb": "nickel", "optc": "iron", "optd": "aluminium chloride", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Tanks used for the storage of petroleum products (which are inflammable) should be painted with a __________ paint.", "opta": "black", "optb": "white", "optc": "red", "optd": "yellow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Cetane number of diesel used in trucks may be about", "opta": "50", "optb": "14", "optc": "35", "optd": "85", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Generally, diesel engines operate well with a Cetane number from 40 to 55."}, {"question": "__________ test is done to find out the softening point of bitumen.", "opta": "Impact", "optb": "Ball and ring", "optc": "Flame", "optd": "Viscosity", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "__________ determination is not a very significant and important test for gasoline.", "opta": "Gum & sulphur content", "optb": "Viscosity", "optc": "Octane number", "optd": "Reid vapor pressure", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following has the lowest viscosity (at a given temperature) of all?", "opta": "Naphtha", "optb": "Kerosene", "optc": "Diesel", "optd": "Lube oil", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Mercaptans are", "opta": "low boiling sulphur compounds.", "optb": "added in LPG cylinders to detect gas leakage by its smell.", "optc": "undesirable in petrol, as they reduce its octane number.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Paraffin base crude oil as compared to asphalt base crude gives", "opta": "higher yield of straight run gasoline.", "optb": "higher octane number gasoline.", "optc": "lower viscosity index lube oil.", "optd": "poorer yield of lube oil.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "True boiling point apparatus is used for the", "opta": "determination of characterisation factor.", "optb": "evaluation of oil stocks.", "optc": "determination of true vapour pressure.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the atmospheric pressure crude distillation, the content of __________ from lighter fraction to heavier ones.", "opta": "sulphur increases", "optb": "sulphur decreases", "optc": "nitrogen decreases", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Catalytic desulphurisation process used for sweetening of straight run gasoline and kerosene uses __________ as catalyst.", "opta": "bauxite", "optb": "fuller's earth", "optc": "activated clay", "optd": "all (a), (b) & (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Solution used in Doctor's treatment for the removal of mercaptans is", "opta": "sodium hydroxide", "optb": "sodium plumbite", "optc": "cupric chloride", "optd": "potassium isobutyrate", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Flash point of motor gasoline may be around __________ \u00b0C.", "opta": "10", "optb": "45", "optc": "100", "optd": "150", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "__________ converts n-paraffins to i-paraffins.", "opta": "Alkylation", "optb": "Polymerisation", "optc": "Isomerisation", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The colour of gasoline is an indication of its", "opta": "octane number.", "optb": "lead susceptibility.", "optc": "gum forming tendency & thoroughness of refining.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The octane number of aviation gasoline may be", "opta": "79", "optb": "87", "optc": "97", "optd": ">100", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Flash point of an oil gives an idea of the", "opta": "nature of boiling point diagram of the system.", "optb": "amount of low boiling fraction present.", "optc": "explosion hazards.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Furfural solvent extraction is used for upgrading (by dissolving aromatics)", "opta": "naphtha", "optb": "lubricating oils", "optc": "wax", "optd": "cracking feedstock", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Illuminating characteristics of kerosene is expressed by its", "opta": "smoke point", "optb": "aniline point", "optc": "luminosity number", "optd": "aromatic content", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following constituents present in petroleum is responsible for ash formation?", "opta": "Nitrogen compounds", "optb": "Organometallic compounds", "optc": "Sulphur compounds", "optd": "Oxygen compounds", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The coking process normally mostly used in Indian oil refineries is the __________ coking process.", "opta": "delayed", "optb": "flexi", "optc": "fluid", "optd": "contact", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Nylon-6 is manufactured from", "opta": "caprolactum.", "optb": "adipic   acid   and   hexamethylene diamine.", "optc": "maleic anhydride and hexamethylene diamine.", "optd": "sebasic acid  and hexamethylene diamine.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Caprolactum, a raw material for the manufacture of nylon-6, is produced from", "opta": "phenol", "optb": "naphthalene", "optc": "benzene", "optd": "pyridine", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The monomer of poly vinyl chloride (PVC) is", "opta": "chloroethene", "optb": "ethylene dichloride", "optc": "ethyl chloride", "optd": "chloroform", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Buna-S is also known as", "opta": "teflon", "optb": "PTFE", "optc": "SBR", "optd": "polycrylates", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Neoprene is chemically known as", "opta": "polybutandiene", "optb": "styrene butadiene rubber (SBR)", "optc": "polyurethane", "optd": "poly chloroprene", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Lavatory cisterns are normally made of", "opta": "expanded polystyrene", "optb": "saturated polyester", "optc": "perspex", "optd": "PVC", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Plasticisers are added to synthetic plastics to", "opta": "impart flexibility.", "optb": "improve workability during fabrication.", "optc": "develop new improved properties not present in the original resin.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Cellulose is the main contituent of most __________ fibres.", "opta": "acrylic", "optb": "spandex", "optc": "synthetic", "optd": "natural", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "__________ resins are produced by the condensation polymerisation of formaldehyde with urea or melamine.", "opta": "Epoxy", "optb": "Amino", "optc": "Alkyd", "optd": "Phenolic", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "__________ tubes are good substitude for human blood vessels onrheart by-pass operation.", "opta": "PVC", "optb": "Polythene", "optc": "Teflon/dacron", "optd": "Polystyrene", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Natural rubber is obtained from latex, which is a colloidal dispersion of rubber in water. Which of the following is used as a coagulant in latex ?", "opta": "Ammonium alum", "optb": "Potassium alum", "optc": "both a & b", "optd": "neither a nor b", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Automobile steering wheels are normally made of", "opta": "cellulose acetate", "optb": "cellulose nitrate", "optc": "PVC", "optd": "high density polythene", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a cross linked polymer, the monomeric units are linked together to constitute a three dimensional network. Which of the following is a cross-linked polymer ?", "opta": "Bakelite (phenol formaldehyde)", "optb": "Polyester", "optc": "Polythene", "optd": "Nylon-6", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "90% of the caprolactum is converted to nylon-6 on its condensation polymerisation in the reactor maintained at a temperature of __________ \u00b0C.", "opta": "-5", "optb": "10-30", "optc": "250-280", "optd": "500-600", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Out of all the elastomers, natural rubber has the longest elongation range & flexibility of the order of __________ percent.", "opta": "1-1000", "optb": "1000-1500", "optc": "1500-2000", "optd": "2000-2500", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following low molecular weight (<104 ), soft & waxy polymer is used in chewing gum ?", "opta": "Cellulose acetate", "optb": "Polyvinyl acetate", "optc": "Thiokol", "optd": "PVC", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Buna-S is a __________ material.", "opta": "fibrous", "optb": "plastic", "optc": "resinous", "optd": "rubbery", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Zeigler - Natta catalyst (AlR3 - AlCl3) is used in the polymerisation of", "opta": "vinyl acetate", "optb": "vinyl chloride", "optc": "propylene", "optd": "styrene", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Due to its excellent permeability to air/gas and oxidation resistance, the tubes of automobile tyres is made of", "opta": "cold SBR", "optb": "butyl rubber", "optc": "Bunai N", "optd": "Buna S", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Neoprene is a", "opta": "monomer", "optb": "synthetic rubber", "optc": "polyester", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The main use of butadiene is", "opta": "as a plasticiser for unsaturated polyester.", "optb": "in the manufacture of synthetic rubber.", "optc": "as an anti-skimming agent in paint.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Mastication of rubber means", "opta": "its softening.", "optb": "a treatment to retard its deterioration due to oxidation.", "optc": "improving its curing rate.", "optd": "depression of its freezing point.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Polymethyl methacrylate (PMMA) is known as", "opta": "bakelite", "optb": "teflon", "optc": "perspex", "optd": "nylon-6", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Reaction of dimethyl terephthalate (DMT) and ethylene glycol produces", "opta": "nylon-6", "optb": "dacron", "optc": "polyester", "optd": "PVC", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Tubeless tyres are made of __________ rubber, which is a co-polymer of isoprene & isobutylene.", "opta": "nitrile", "optb": "silicone", "optc": "neoprene", "optd": "butyl", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Density of high density polythene is about __________ gm/c.c.", "opta": "1.18", "optb": "1.05", "optc": "0.95", "optd": "0.99", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Vinyl flooring is done using __________ sheets.", "opta": "polypropylene", "optb": "PVC", "optc": "polythene", "optd": "polyvinyl acetate", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Thiokol is nothing but", "opta": "polysulphide rubber", "optb": "polyamide fibre", "optc": "engineering plastic", "optd": "exponded polystyrene", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Transistor parts and refrigerator components are normally made of", "opta": "polystyrene", "optb": "polyester", "optc": "high density polythene", "optd": "polyurathane", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Dacron (or terylene) fibres as compared to nylon fibres have", "opta": "better heat & acid resistant properties.", "optb": "poorer resistance to alkalis.", "optc": "poorer dyeability.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Orlan fibre which is used as a wool sub stitute is", "opta": "an amorphous polymer.", "optb": "a natural polymeric fibre.", "optc": "polyacrylonitrile.", "optd": "polymethylmethacrylate (PMMA).", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Neoprene is the trade name of", "opta": "polyurethane", "optb": "phenol formaldehyde", "optc": "polychlorophrene", "optd": "styrene butadiene rubber (SBR)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Trade name of __________ is neoprene.", "opta": "polychloroprene", "optb": "polyisoprene", "optc": "polytetraflouroethylene", "optd": "poly vinyl acetate", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "SBR is produced by the copolymerisation of butadiene & styrene by employing emulsion polymerisation. The weight ratio of styrene and butadiene is maintained at", "opta": "1:3", "optb": "3:1", "optc": "1:2", "optd": "2:1", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Dacron is a/an", "opta": "polyester", "optb": "unsaturated polyester", "optc": "polyamide", "optd": "inorganic polymer", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Starting material for the production of SBR is", "opta": "ethyl alcohol", "optb": "ethylene", "optc": "both (a) & (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is a copolymer ?", "opta": "PVC", "optb": "Bakelite", "optc": "Polythene", "optd": "Teflon", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fillers such as zinc oxide and carbon black are added to the crude natural rubber before vulcanisation in order to improve its", "opta": "elasticity", "optb": "strength", "optc": "plasticity", "optd": "weathering characteristics", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The organic acid monomer in nylon 66 is", "opta": "sebasic acid", "optb": "terephthalic acid", "optc": "adipic acid", "optd": "benzoic acid", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Neoprene which is used for making shoe heels & belts is superior to natural rubber in its stability to aerial oxidation and resistance to oils & other solvents. The monomer used for making neoprene is", "opta": "chloroethane", "optb": "chlorophrene", "optc": "isoprene", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The synthetic fibres produced from __________ are known as rayon.", "opta": "lignin", "optb": "cellulose", "optc": "polyamides", "optd": "ethylene glycol", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Peptizers like aromatic mercaptans (e.g. thiophenes) are added in rubber to", "opta": "protect rubber goods from attack by oxygen & ozone present in the atmosphere.", "optb": "reduce its viscosity to permit easier processing.", "optc": "reduce the time of vulcanisation and quantity of vulcanising agent.", "optd": "increase its viscosity.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Visco-elastic behaviour exhibited by plastics is a __________ like behaviour.", "opta": "solid", "optb": "liquid", "optc": "combination of solid & liquid", "optd": "neither solid nor liquid", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is generally not used as eord for synthetic rubber tyre casing ?", "opta": "Dacron", "optb": "Nylon", "optc": "Cellulose", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "__________ is not a polyester fibre.", "opta": "Terylene", "optb": "Dacron", "optc": "Nylon", "optd": "Polyacrylonitrite", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Nitrile rubber is produced by the polymerisation of", "opta": "acrylonitrile & butadiene.", "optb": "acrylonitrile & styrene.", "optc": "isobutylene & isoprene.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Celluloid is", "opta": "cellulose acetate", "optb": "regenerated cellulose", "optc": "cellulose nitrate", "optd": "cellulose acetate butyrate", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Styrene butadiene rubber (SBR) as compared to natural rubber has", "opta": "poor tensile strength.", "optb": "poorer resistance.", "optc": "greater amount of heat build up heavy loading.", "optd": "all (a), (b) ana (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following polymers has the tendency of decomposing before melting ?", "opta": "Polystyrene", "optb": "Nylon", "optc": "PVC", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following polymers belong to the class of formaldehyde resin ?", "opta": "Melamine resins", "optb": "Teflon", "optc": "Dacron", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is an undesirable dynamic characteristic of an instrument ?", "opta": "Reproducibility", "optb": "Dead zone", "optc": "Time lag", "optd": "Static error", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not the triple point of water ?", "opta": "32\u00b0R", "optb": "273\u00b0K", "optc": "492\u00b0R", "optd": "32\u00b0F", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the one which is a first order instrument.", "opta": "Mercury in glass thermometer (without any covering or air gap).", "optb": "Bare metallic thermometer.", "optc": "Bare vapor pressure thermometer.", "optd": "All (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Load cells are used for the measurement of", "opta": "stress", "optb": "weight", "optc": "strain", "optd": "velocity", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is the dynamic characteristics of an instrument ?", "opta": "Reproducibility", "optb": "Sensitivity", "optc": "Dead zone", "optd": "Fidelity", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "O2, NO and NO2 exhibit paramagnetic properties as a result of unpaired electrons.", "optb": "CO2 is the strongest paramagnetic gas.", "optc": "Paramagnetic susceptibility of gases decreases with temperature.", "optd": "Paramagnetic susceptibility of gases permits the measurement of their concentration.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The __________ of a vapor pressure thermometer is a functioning element.", "opta": "pointer", "optb": "bourdon tube", "optc": "bulb", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A negative gain margin expressed in decibels means a/an __________ system.", "opta": "stable", "optb": "unstable", "optc": "critically damped", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Thermistor, which has high temperature co-efficient of resistivity, is used as the sensing element in resistance thermometer. It is a/an", "opta": "insulator", "optb": "conductor", "optc": "solid semi-conductor", "optd": "liquid semi-conductor", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Flapper nozzle is used in a/an __________ controller.", "opta": "electronic", "optb": "hydraulic", "optc": "pneumatic", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Typical specifications for design stipulates the gain margin and phase margin to be respectively", "opta": "> 1.7 and > 30\u00b0", "optb": "< 1.7 and  > 30\u00b0", "optc": "< 1.7 and < 30\u00b0", "optd": "> 1.7 and < 30\u00b0", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Working principle of radiation pyrometer is based on the", "opta": "Wien's law", "optb": "Kirchoffs law", "optc": "Stafan-Boltzman law", "optd": "Seebeck effect", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following relates the emf. generated in a single homogeneous wire to the temperature difference ?", "opta": "Peltier effect", "optb": "Thomson effect", "optc": "Seebeck effect", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Dilute wine was used as a thermometric liquid initially to develop temperature scale. First emperical temperature scale developed was the __________ scale.", "opta": "Kelvin", "optb": "Centigrade", "optc": "Fahrenheit", "optd": "Reaumer", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a single tank system, the transfer function of level to inlet flow rate is", "opta": "R/TS", "optb": "R/(TS + 1)", "optc": "l(TS + l)", "optd": "1/TS", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is a desirable characteristic of an instrument ?", "opta": "High drift", "optb": "High fidelity", "optc": "High measuring lag", "optd": "Poor reproducibility", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The operation of a rotameter is based on", "opta": "variable flow area.", "optb": "rotation of a turbine.", "optc": "pressure drop across a nozzle.", "optd": "pressure at a stagnation point.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The temperature of tempering oil baths maintained at 400\u00b0C during heat treatment of steel is measured by a/an __________ thermocouple.", "opta": "chromel-alumel", "optb": "iron-constantan", "optc": "platinum-platinum/rhodium", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Instrumentation in a plant offers the advantage of", "opta": "greater safety of operation", "optb": "better quality of product", "optc": "greater operation economy", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following temperature measuring instruments need not touch the object whose temperature is being measured ?", "opta": "Radiation/infrared pyrometer", "optb": "Filled system thermometer", "optc": "Mercury in glass thermometer", "optd": "Thermo electric pyrometer", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Thermal conductivity measurement com-prises the working principle of a", "opta": "CO2 analyser", "optb": "polarimeter", "optc": "spectrometer", "optd": "chromatograph", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Response of a system to a sinusoidal input is called __________ response.", "opta": "impluse", "optb": "unit step", "optc": "frequency", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The closed loop pole of a stable second order system could be", "opta": "both real and positive.", "optb": "complex conjugate with positive real parts.", "optc": "both real and negative.", "optd": "one real positive and the other real negative.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Smoke density of the flue gas going out of the chimney is measured by a", "opta": "polarograph", "optb": "thermal conductivity meter", "optc": "photo electric cell", "optd": "chromatograph", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Transfer function of transportation lag is", "opta": "eTS", "optb": "e-TS", "optc": "", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Temperature measuring instruments are standardised mostly with __________ points of pure substances.", "opta": "melting", "optb": "boiling", "optc": "both (a) & (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the first order system from among the following.", "opta": "Damped vibrator.", "optb": "Mercury in glass thermometer kept in boiling water.", "optc": "Interacting system of two tanks in series.", "optd": "Non-interacting system of two tanks in series.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum service temperature for fibre glass used as thermocouple wire insulation material is __________ \u00b0C.", "opta": "250", "optb": "500", "optc": "750", "optd": "1000", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following controllers has the least maximum deviation ?", "opta": "P-controller", "optb": "P-I controller", "optc": "P-I-D controller", "optd": "P-D controller", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Volumetric expansion is the working principle of the __________ thermometers.", "opta": "mercury in glass", "optb": "constant volume gas", "optc": "vapor pressure", "optd": "bimetallic", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following measurements can be made by the measurement of emf ?", "opta": "pH value", "optb": "Degree of hydrolysis", "optc": "Composition of complex ions", "optd": "All (a), (b) & (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A magnetic flowmeter is", "opta": "based on the principle of Faraday's law.", "optb": "capable of measuring the flow rate of slurries and electrolytes.", "optc": "based on the linear relationship between the fluid flow rate and the induced voltage.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Zirconia probe is used for the continuous measurment of __________ flue gases going out of the furnace.", "opta": "oxygen in", "optb": "carbon dioxide in", "optc": "carbon monoxide in", "optd": "temperature of", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Strain gage pressure transducers are used to measure __________ pressures.", "opta": "gage as well as vacuum", "optb": "absolute as well as differential", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The transfer function for a PID controller is (where, \u03c4 i is the integral (reset) time and \u03c4D is the derivative time.)", "opta": "Kc(1 + \u03c4is + \u03c4D ). s", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Compositional analysis of __________ is done using mass spectrometer.", "opta": "an isotope", "optb": "natural gas", "optc": "a solid", "optd": "an alloy", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The function of a transducer is to", "opta": "modify the input signal.", "optb": "amplify the input signal.", "optc": "convert the primary signal into a more useful quantity, usually an electric impulse.", "optd": "codify/decodify the input signal.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Nichol's chart deals with", "opta": "A.R. vs. phase lag of first order.", "optb": "A.R. vs. phase lag of second order.", "optc": "closed loop values vs. open loop values.", "optd": "frequency response values of controllers.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following thermocouples will give the highest output for the same value of hot and cold junction temperature ?", "opta": "Platinum-platinum + rhodium.", "optb": "Iron-constantan.", "optc": "Chromel-constantan.", "optd": "All will give the same output.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A proportional controller with a gain of Kc is used to control a first order process. The offset will increase, if", "opta": "Kc is reduced.", "optb": "Kc is increased.", "optc": "integral control action is introduced.", "optd": "derivative control action is introduced.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The symbol for \"capillary line\" in instrumentation diagram is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "__________ is undesirable in thermocouples used in industries,", "opta": "Linear relation of emf to temperature", "optb": "Corrosion resistance", "optc": "Oxidation resistance", "optd": "Non-linear relation of emf to temperature", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Select the correct statement from the following.", "opta": "The frequency response of a pure capacity process is unbounded.", "optb": "The phase lag of a pure time delay system decreases with increasing frequency.", "optc": "The amplitude ratio of a pure capacity process is inversely proportional to frequency.", "optd": "The amplitude ratio of a pure time delay system increases with frequency.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For an input forcing function, X(t) = 2t2, the Laplace transform of this function is", "opta": "2/s2", "optb": "4/s2", "optc": "2/s3", "optd": "4/s3", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Continuous shell temperature measurement in a liquid-liquid heat exchanger is done by a", "opta": "thermocouple", "optb": "reistance thermometer", "optc": "mercury in glass thermometer", "optd": "vapor pressure thermometer", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The __________ of a vapor pressure thermometer is a secondary element.", "opta": "pointer", "optb": "Bourdon tube", "optc": "bulb", "optd": "none ofthese", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Emf developed by a thermocouple, while measuring a temperature of 600\u00b0C is about 5.5 mV. The type of thermocouple used is", "opta": "chromel-alumel", "optb": "iron-constantan", "optc": "platinum-platinum+rhodium", "optd": "either (a), (b) or (c)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following relates the absorption & evolution of heat at the junctions of a thermocouple to the current flow in the circuit?", "opta": "Seebeck effect", "optb": "Peltier effect", "optc": "Joule heating effect", "optd": "Thomson effect", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The second order system with the transfer function  has a damping ratio of", "opta": "2.0", "optb": "0.5", "optc": "1.0", "optd": "4.0", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a shell and tube heat exchanger, the flow rate of heating/cooling fluid is the __________ variable.", "opta": "load", "optb": "controlled", "optc": "manipulated", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fresh water carrying pipelines in chemical industries are coloured with __________ color.", "opta": "sea green", "optb": "brown", "optc": "yellow", "optd": "red", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following material is seldom used for pressure vessel construction ?", "opta": "Rimmed still", "optb": "Mild steel", "optc": "Killed steel", "optd": "Semi-killed steel", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of shear stress to shear strain is called", "opta": "bulk modulus", "optb": "shear modulus", "optc": "modulus of rigidity", "optd": "modulus of elasticity", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "25 per cent cut segmental baffle means that the baffle", "opta": "height is 75% of the I.D. of the shell.", "optb": "height is 25% of the I.D. of the shell.", "optc": "spacing is 75% of its height.", "optd": "width is 25% of its height.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Liquid/petroleum fuel storage tanks are built underground (as in case of petrol pumps), when the storage capacity is less than __________ kilolitres.", "opta": "20", "optb": "30", "optc": "45", "optd": "85", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "for fully open globe value may be around", "opta": "10", "optb": "25", "optc": "75", "optd": "300", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Lug support is", "opta": "the most suitable for thick vertical vessel.", "optb": "same as bracket support.", "optc": "provided usually for vessels of much smaller height than skirt supported vessels.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement pertaining to the use of valve tray, seive tray and bubble cap trays in continuous distillation column.", "opta": "Bubble cap trays though most expensive are the best in situations, where low vapour rates is to be handled and a positive liquid seal is essential at all flow rates.", "optb": "Murphree efficiency of all the three trays are nearly equal, however the peak efficiency is generally higher for seive and valve trays than the bubble cap.", "optc": "Maintenance cost for valve and seive trays are comparatively more than bubble cap tray due to their relatively complicated construction features.", "optd": "Valve trays have the highest turn down ratio (i.e. the ratio of the highest to the lowest vapour flow rates) and thus provides the maximum flexible operating range.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "With increase in the number of shell passes, the value of FT", "opta": "increases", "optb": "decreases", "optc": "remains same", "optd": "remains same, only if the number of tube passes does not change.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Holes of a sieve tray are arranged in triangular pitch of __________ times the hole diameter.", "opta": "1.5 to 2", "optb": "2.5 to 5", "optc": "5 to 10", "optd": "10 to 15", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In case of a shell and tube heat exchanger, the minimum shell thickness for carbon steel (inclusive of corrosion allowance) depends on shell diameter and is in the range of __________ mm.", "opta": "3-5", "optb": "5-11", "optc": "8-15", "optd": "12-18", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The stress developed in a material without any permanent set is called the", "opta": "ultimate stress", "optb": "yield stress", "optc": "elastic limit", "optd": "breaking stress", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a shell and tube heat exchanger, the 'tube pitch' is defined as the", "opta": "O.D. of the tube for square pitch.", "optb": "shortest distance between two adj acent tube holes.", "optc": "shortest centre to centre distance between adjacent tubes.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not a valid assumption in continuous binary distillation for calculating the number of equilibrium stages by Mc-Cabe-Thiele's method ?", "opta": "Sensible heat changes for vapour &  liquid are negligibly small.", "optb": "Reflux is not a saturated liquid.", "optc": "Molar latent heat of the two components are equal.", "optd": "Heat of mixing of normal liquid is assumed to be zero.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Overall distillation column efficiency for most of the refinery columns can be given by (for \u03bc = 0.07 - 1.4 cp and relative volatility < 4) (where \u03b7 = overall column efficiency, % \u03bc = molal average viscosity of feed at average column temperature and pressure, cp \u0394p = pressure drop per tray, psi)", "opta": "\u03b7 = 17 - 61.1 log \u03bc", "optb": "", "optc": "\u03b7 = 1.66 - 0.25 log \u03bc", "optd": "\u03b7 = 0.25 log \u03bc - 1.67", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The value of fouling factor depends upon the", "opta": "characteristic of process fluid.", "optb": "velocity of process fluid containing suspended solids.", "optc": "suspended solids in the fluid.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In case of bubble cap distillation column of diameter greater than 1.2 metres, the cap diameter is roughly about __________ cms.", "opta": "10", "optb": "20", "optc": "30", "optd": "35", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Tube side pressure drop in a 1-2 heat exchanger (for turbulent flow of fluids through the tubes) is about __________ times, that in a 1-1 heat exchanger having the same size & number of tubes and operated at the same liquid flow rate.", "opta": "2", "optb": "1/2", "optc": "4", "optd": "8", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To keep the power input constant for a stirred vessel operating under fully developed turbulent flow conditions (constant power number), if the impeller diameter is increased by 20%, the impeller speed should be decreased by a factor of", "opta": "(1.2)3/2", "optb": "(1.2)3/5", "optc": "(1.2)2/3", "optd": "(1.2)5/3", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a heat exchanger, shell side fluid velocity can be changed by changing the tube", "opta": "layout", "optb": "pitch", "optc": "both (a) & (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Where does the maximum tensile strength occur in a thick cylindrical vessel subjected to internal pressure ?", "opta": "At the inner surface.", "optb": "At the mid thickness of the cylindrical wall.", "optc": "At the outer surface.", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "It is not desirable to design a heat exchanger for LMTD correction factor, FT, of less than", "opta": "0.99", "optb": "0.95", "optc": "0.80", "optd": "0.55", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A rivetted joint does not fail by __________ of rivets.", "opta": "tearing", "optb": "shearing", "optc": "tearing of the plate across a row", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Triangular pitch tube layout as compared to square pitch in a shell and tube heat exchanger", "opta": "permits the use of less tubes in a given shell diameter.", "optb": "facilitates comparatively easier external cleaning because of large clearance.", "optc": "permits the use of more tubes in a given shell diameter.", "optd": "both (b) and (c).", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Bracket supports are the most suitable for supporting __________ vessels.", "opta": "thick walled vertical", "optb": "horizontal", "optc": "thin shperical (e.g. Horton sphere)", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a multipass shell and tube heat exchanger, the shell side cross flow area does not depend upon", "opta": "baffle spacing", "optb": "clearance", "optc": "pitch", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Two iron pipes of the same nominal diameter but different schedule numbers will have the same", "opta": "inside diameter", "optb": "outside diameter", "optc": "wall thickness", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Steam side heat transfer co-efficient for design consideration under ordinary condition can be assumed    to be about __________ kcal/hr.m2.\u00b0C.", "opta": "1250", "optb": "2500", "optc": "7500", "optd": "15000", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement", "opta": "For all the cylindrical process vessels operating above atmospheric pressure, formed heads are used for closing the vessel.", "optb": "Fouling factor of river water is less than that of sea water.", "optc": "Risers provided in bubble cap trays in the distillation column facilitate the flow of both liquid and vapor.", "optd": "both (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Lessing ring is formed by the addition of a partition across the centre of a raschig ring, which results in an area increase of about __________ percent.", "opta": "5", "optb": "20", "optc": "35", "optd": "55", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In chemical process equipments, the conical bottom heads used, usually has an apex angle of", "opta": "20\u00b0", "optb": "40\u00b0", "optc": "60\u00b0", "optd": "80\u00b0", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Smaller sized packings are generally dumped to the packed columns, and the large ones of size greater than __________ mm are stacked individually, which provides better control over bed porosity and offers lower gas pressure drop.", "opta": "25", "optb": "50", "optc": "75", "optd": "150", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Shell side heat transfer co-efficient in case of square pitch as compared to the triangular pitch under similar condition of fluid flow and tube size is", "opta": "more", "optb": "same", "optc": "less", "optd": "twice", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Correct use of 'factor of safety' is very important in equipment design. It is defined as the ratio of the", "opta": "ultimate stress to breaking stress.", "optb": "ultimate stress to working stress.", "optc": "working stress to ultimate stress.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The operating velocity in the absorption tower is usually 40-50% of the flooding velocity. Packed absorption towers are normally designed for a pressure drop of about __________ mm of water    column per metre height of packing.", "opta": "1-5", "optb": "20-40", "optc": "100-150", "optd": "1000-1500", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "__________ tray arrangement is recommended for distillation column having diameter upto 4 ft.", "opta": "Radial flow", "optb": "Cross flow", "optc": "Split flow", "optd": "Cascade", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "What is the value of 'q' for saturated liquid feed to a distillation column ?", "opta": "0", "optb": "<1", "optc": "1", "optd": ">1", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In perforated plate towers, the", "opta": "hole sizes may be around 1/8\" or 3/16\".", "optb": "total hole area may be around 6 to 15% of tower cross-sectional area.", "optc": "pressure drop is less compared is similar bubble cap towers.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The main purpose of providing stepping on the trays is to", "opta": "increase the residence time.", "optb": "decrease the pressure drop.", "optc": "facilitate handling of large flow rate of liquid.", "optd": "improve the flow condition.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The operating pressure drop range in a bag filter is about __________ mm water gauge.", "opta": "50-150", "optb": "5-10", "optc": "500-1500", "optd": "1500-2500", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ends of a cylinderical vessel can be closed by a head, which can be one of the four shapes. For the same thickness, choose the one which can withstand the highest pressure.", "opta": "Flat plate", "optb": "Hemispherical", "optc": "Torispherical", "optd": "Ellipsoidal", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For laminar flow (NRe < 2100) in steel pipe, the optimum inside pipe diameter is given by", "opta": "Di, opt = 3 Q0.36 \u03c10.18", "optb": "Di, opt = 3.9 Q0.45 . \u03c10.23", "optc": "Di, opt = 7.6 Q0.36 . \u03c10.9", "optd": "Di, opt = 3 Q0.36 . \u03c11.86 \u03bc0.08", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the correct statement.", "opta": "When highly corrosive fluids are to be handled, the plate towers prove to be cheaper and easier to construct than packed tower.", "optb": "Packed towers are generally preferred over plate towers, if the liquids have a foaming tendency.", "optc": "The pressure drop through the packed towers is generally more than the pressure drop through plate towers designed for same duty.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Wall thickness of schedule 40 pipe as compared to that of schedule 80 pipe is", "opta": "more", "optb": "less", "optc": "same", "optd": "cither (a) or (b); depends upon the I.D. of the pipe", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement pertaining to the design of a basket type evaporator.", "opta": "It is used for high viscosity liquor having large rate of scaling.", "optb": "The tube bundle is suspended on bracket.", "optc": "There is no central downtake.", "optd": "Downtake is formed by the annular space between the bundle and the shell.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement pertaining to the design of the bubble cap tray of a distillation column to give stable operation and even vapour distribution.", "opta": "The pressure drop due to the caps & slots and the static submergence should be as high as practicable for reasonable operation.", "optb": "Tendency towards stable operation is increased by increasing the skirt clearance of the caps, lowering the rate of liquid flow per unit plate width or increasing the spacing between the caps.", "optc": "The dimensionless ratio of liquid gradient to pressure drop head caused by the bubble cap assembly should be less than 0.4.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Speed of the drum of the rotary vacuum filter normally ranges from __________ rpm.", "opta": "0.1 to 2", "optb": "5 to 7", "optc": "3 to 8", "optd": "8 to 15", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A stuffing box is used for", "opta": "absorbing the contraction/expansion of pipeline due to temperature changes.", "optb": "prevention of fluid leakage around moving parts.", "optc": "facilitating smooth opening and closing of a valve.", "optd": "reducing the resistance of fluid flow.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pressure drop (\u0394p) and the superficial gas mass velocity (G) in case of packed absorption tower operating in the preloading range are related as", "opta": "\u0394p = G", "optb": "\u0394p = G0.5", "optc": "\u0394p = G2", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.In an agitated vertical cylinderical reaction vessel, the", "opta": "ratio of liquid depth to tank diameter (i.e. the filling ratio) recommended for most purposes is 1.", "optb": "filling ratio for dispersing gas in a liquid is 2 for sufficiently long contact period.", "optc": "flat bottom and conical bottom vessels have low agitation efficiency for agitation of heavy solids in liquids.", "optd": "dished bottom vessel has very high power consumption.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Skull is not formed on the carbon blocks in the hearth of a blast furnace, when it becomes cold, becaus  of its", "opta": "non-wetting characteristic.", "optb": "high thermal conductivity.", "optc": "high crushing strength.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Firing temperature of magnesite bricks is about __________ \u00b0C.", "opta": "800-1000", "optb": "1000-1200", "optc": "1600-1800", "optd": "2400-2600", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Hollow refractory bricks are made by", "opta": "slip casting", "optb": "hand moulding", "optc": "pressing/machine moulding", "optd": "extrusion", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Quartz is", "opta": "stable form of silica upto 870\u00b0C.", "optb": "converted to tridymite on firing between 870 to 1470\u00b0C.", "optc": "transformed to crystoballite on heating above 1470\u00b0C.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An indication of degree of firing in silica brick is its", "opta": "specific gravity", "optb": "fusion point", "optc": "RUL", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Panel test determines the __________ of refractories.", "opta": "fusion point", "optb": "spalling resistance", "optc": "slag penetration resistance", "optd": "refractoriness under load (RUL)", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fireclay bricks are not used in the", "opta": "beehive coke oven.", "optb": "by-product coke oven walls.", "optc": "combustion chamber of B.F. stoves.", "optd": "coke oven regenerators.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fusion point of a basic refractory material is", "opta": "reduced by the addition of acid oxides.", "optb": "increased by the addition of acid oxides.", "optc": "not affected by the addition of acid oxides.", "optd": "always less than 1000\u00b0C.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "RUL of refractories depends on the", "opta": "chemical composition.", "optb": "physical structure.", "optc": "presence of impurities like iron & alkali.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which is the stable form of silica between 1470\u00b0C and the melting point 1713\u00b0C ?", "opta": "Cristobalite", "optb": "Tridymite", "optc": "Quartz", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Resistance to slag attack of a refractory", "opta": "depends on the nature of slag & refractory.", "optb": "decreases at higher temperature.", "optc": "decreases, if defective joints & cracks exist in the refractory.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Grog", "opta": "contains both alumina and silica.", "optb": "iscrushed firebrick.", "optc": "is a non-plastic material.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Test piece for determination of RUL of a refractory is heated in a/an", "opta": "oxidising atmosphere", "optb": "reducing atmosphere", "optc": "electric furnace", "optd": "neutral atmosphere", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Magnesite refractories are used for the construction of those furnaces, which are", "opta": "not required to resist the corrosive action of basic slag.", "optb": "not subjected to fluctuation in temperature.", "optc": "used for raising & maintaining high temperature.", "optd": "both (b) and (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Roof of a basic electric furnace is made of __________ bricks.", "opta": "superduty fireclay", "optb": "silica", "optc": "chromite", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Capacity of a refractory brick to withstand-sudden changes in temperature is denoted by the property called", "opta": "spalling resistance.", "optb": "refractoriness.", "optc": "refractoriness under load (RUL).", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Magnesite bricks are used in those parts of furnaces, which are", "opta": "subjected to temperature fluctuation.", "optb": "required to resist corrosive basic slag.", "optc": "subjected to high load.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which is not a basic refractory ?", "opta": "Chrome magnesite", "optb": "Magnesite", "optc": "Dolomite", "optd": "Silicon carbide", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Thoria", "opta": "has high fusion temperature (> 3000\u00b0C) but poor resistance to thermal shock.", "optb": "has high resistance to basic slags.", "optc": "which is expensive & radioactive, is used in crucibles for melting high purity metals.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which property of refractories is the most important for top section of the blast furnace?", "opta": "Resistance to abrasion.", "optb": "Resistance to slag peneration.", "optc": "Stability of volume at high temperature.", "optd": "Resistance to corrosion by slag.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Refractoriness of a typical silica brick corresponds to Segar cone number, '32', which is   equivalent  to   a  temperature  of __________ \u00b0C.", "opta": "1380", "optb": "1520", "optc": "1710", "optd": "1915", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Beryllia (which is used in making crucibles for melting uranium & thorium) is superior to alumina in all respects for high temperature (> 1900\u00b0C ) use, except", "opta": "cost", "optb": "electrical conductivity", "optc": "thermal conductivity", "optd": "fusion point", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An insulating refractory brick should have high porosity and low thermal conductivity. Which of the following is not used for inducing porosity in the insulating refractory bricks during its manufacture ?", "opta": "Cork", "optb": "Saw dust", "optc": "Sand", "optd": "Chemically prepared foam", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Firing of refractory brick is done to", "opta": "dehydrate the dried refractory.", "optb": "develop stable mineral forms in them.", "optc": "form ceramic bonds necessary for development of high crushing strength in the finished product.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Chemically, mullite refractories is", "opta": "3Al2O3.2SiO2", "optb": "Al2O3", "optc": "ZrSO4", "optd": "ThO2", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Thermal diffusivity of a refractory brick is high, when its __________ is high.", "opta": "density", "optb": "specific heat", "optc": "thermal conductivity", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "High porosity refractory bricks have", "opta": "poor resistance to the peneration of molten slag, metal & flue gases.", "optb": "poor heat conductivity & low strength.", "optc": "better thermal spalling resistance.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Vacuum steel degassing units are lined with", "opta": "silica bricks", "optb": "low duty firebricks", "optc": "high alumina bricks", "optd": "graphite blocks", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pyrometric cone equivalent (PCE) value (Segar cone) of 'superduty refractories' is more than 33 which corresponds to a temperature of __________ \u00b0C.", "opta": "1520", "optb": "1630", "optc": "1670", "optd": "1730", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which is the stable form of silica below 870\u00b0C ?", "opta": "Tridymite", "optb": "Cristobalite", "optc": "Quartz", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one expands on heating ?", "opta": "Silica bricks", "optb": "Fireclay bricks", "optc": "Both (a) & (b)", "optd": "Neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Refractoriness/fusion points of 'superduty' refractories is __________ \u00b0C.", "opta": "1520-1630", "optb": "1630-1670", "optc": "> 1730", "optd": "> 2000", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Outer combustion chamber of blast furnace stove is lined with __________ bricks.", "opta": "fireclay", "optb": "silica", "optc": "chrome magnesite", "optd": "zirconia", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Presence of MgO in alumino-silicate refractories __________ its refractoriness.", "opta": "increases", "optb": "lowers", "optc": "does not affect", "optd": "either (a) or (b); depends on its quantity", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Spalling of silica bricks occurs due to abrupt volume changes, when it is cooled below a temperature of __________ \u00b0C.", "opta": "770", "optb": "570", "optc": "270", "optd": "70", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Walls, roofs &  combustion chambers of annealing furnaces are made of __________ bricks.", "opta": "high duty fireclay", "optb": "silica", "optc": "mullite", "optd": "carborundum", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fireclay bricks are used in the", "opta": "coke ovens regenerator.", "optb": "outer lining of L.D. converter.", "optc": "hearth bottom of blast furnace.", "optd": "coke oven walls.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Water content in ground refractory material to be shaped into bricks by hand moulding is about __________ percent.", "opta": "5", "optb": "20", "optc": "40", "optd": "55", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Chromite refractories", "opta": "are bonded with lime and clay.", "optb": "(free from silica) have better thermal fatigue resistance than silica and magnesite refractories.", "optc": "are resistant to basic slag.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Firing temperature is minimum (1250-1400 \u00b0C) for __________ bricks.", "opta": "fireclay", "optb": "direct bonded basic", "optc": "silica", "optd": "magnesite", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "With increase in the alumina content, the refractoriness of high alumina refractories", "opta": "increases", "optb": "decreases", "optc": "remains same", "optd": "may increase or decrease", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A steel member used in the furnace construction to take the thrust of the brickwork is called", "opta": "buckstay", "optb": "breast wall", "optc": "armouring", "optd": "baffle", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "", "opta": "Conversion of quartz to tridymite is associated with 16% volume increase.", "optb": "Conversion of tridymite to crystoballite involves very large expansion in volume.", "optc": "both (a) and (b).", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "With increase in the porosity, thermal spalling resistance of fireclay brick", "opta": "increases", "optb": "decreases", "optc": "remains same", "optd": "may increase or decrease", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Thoria is an expensive refractory material and is radioactive in nature. Thorium oxide is used in the manufacture of", "opta": "segar cones.", "optb": "muffles for muffle furnaces.", "optc": "insulating bricks.", "optd": "crucibles used for melting of high purity metals.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Maximum alumina content in high alumina refractory can be as high as __________ percent.", "opta": "30", "optb": "50", "optc": "70", "optd": "90", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Refractories are dried in the", "opta": "rotary kilns", "optb": "tunnel kilns", "optc": "sun", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Cermets are combination of ceramic and metallic materials due to which they have high strength & resistance to high temperature. Cermets are used in the", "opta": "hearth of the blast furnace.", "optb": "nuclear reactors, missiles & space crafts.", "optc": "insulation of high temperature furnaces.", "optd": "roof of electric furnaces.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Hot metal runner in blast furnace are lined with __________ bricks.", "opta": "silica", "optb": "carborundum", "optc": "fireclay", "optd": "magnesite", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Spray test determines the __________ of refractories.", "opta": "resistance to slag penetration", "optb": "resistance to CO attack", "optc": "RUL", "optd": "permanent linear change", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "CaCO3 contains __________ percent of Ca by weight.", "opta": "40", "optb": "48", "optc": "96", "optd": "12", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Solutions which distil without change in composition are called", "opta": "ideal", "optb": "saturated", "optc": "supersaturated", "optd": "azeotropic", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Gases having same reduced temperatures and reduced pressures", "opta": "deviate from ideal gas behaviour to the same degree.", "optb": "have nearly the same compressibility factor.", "optc": "both (a) and (b).", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b).", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not a unit of pressure ?", "opta": "Torr", "optb": "Newton/m2", "optc": "Parsec", "optd": "Ata, bar or pascal", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The evaporation of aqueous solution of sugar causes its molarity to", "opta": "decrease. (b)   increase.", "optb": "remain unchanged.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One Newton is equal to __________ dynes.", "opta": "102", "optb": "103", "optc": "104", "optd": "105", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A very dilute solution is prepared by dissolving 'x1' mole of solute in 'x2' mole of a solvent. The mole fraction of solute is approximately equal to", "opta": "x1/x2", "optb": "x2/x1", "optc": "1 - (x1/x2)", "optd": "1/x2", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An ideal gas can be liquified, because", "opta": "its molecular size is very small.", "optb": "its critical temperature is more than 0\u00b0C.", "optc": "forces operative between its molecules are negligible.", "optd": "it gets solidified directly without becoming liquid.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The rate of material __________ is zero in case of a steady state system.", "opta": "accumulation", "optb": "production", "optc": "input", "optd": "generation", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A metal oxide is reduced by heating it in a stream of hydrogen. After complete reduction, it is found that 3.15 gm of the oxide has yielded 1.05 gm of the metal. It may be inferred that the", "opta": "atomic weight of the metal is 4.", "optb": "equivalent weight of the metal is 4.", "optc": "atomic weight of the metal is 2.", "optd": "equivalent weight of the metal is 8.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Molar heat capacity of water in equilibrium with ice at constant pressure is", "opta": "0", "optb": "\u221e", "optc": "1", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If pH value of a solution is 8, then its pOH value will be", "opta": "6", "optb": "1", "optc": "7", "optd": "10", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The chemical nature of an element is independent of", "opta": "its atomic number.", "optb": "the number of protons or electrons present in it.", "optc": "the number of neutrons present in it.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The heat change for the reaction, C(s) + 2S(s) \u2192 CS2(l), is 104.2 kJ. It represents the heat of", "opta": "formation", "optb": "solution", "optc": "combustion", "optd": "fusion", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A sample of well water contains 140 gm/m3 Ca2+ ions and 345 gm/m3 Na+ ions. The hardness of the sample of water, expressed in terms of equivalent CaCO3 in gm/m3   is (assuming atomic masses of Ca :40, Na : 23, C : 12, O : 16)", "opta": "350", "optb": "485", "optc": "140", "optd": "345", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Assuming that CO2 obeys perfect gas law, calculate the density of CO2 (in kg/m3) at 263\u00b0C and 2 atm.", "opta": "1", "optb": "2", "optc": "3", "optd": "4", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One micron is equal to", "opta": "10-4 mm", "optb": "10-4 cm", "optc": "10-6 m", "optd": "both(b)&(c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Heat capacity of air can be approximately expressed as, Cp = 26.693 + 7.365 x10-3 T, where, Cp is in J/mole.K and T is in K. The heat given off by 1 mole of air when cooled at atmospheric pressure from 500\u00b0C to - 100\u00b0C is", "opta": "10.73 kJ", "optb": "16.15 kJ", "optc": "18.11 kJ", "optd": "18.33 kJ", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Gases diffuse faster compared to liquids because of the reason that the liquid molecules", "opta": "are held together by stronger inter-molecular forces.", "optb": "move faster.", "optc": "have no definite shape.", "optd": "are heavier", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Equal masses of CH4 and H2 are mixed in an empty container. The partial pressure of hydrogen in this container expressed as the fraction of total pressure is", "opta": "1/9", "optb": "8/9", "optc": "1/2", "optd": "5/9", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not a colligative property ?", "opta": "Osmotic pressure", "optb": "Depression of freezing point", "optc": "Lowering of vapor pressure", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Atoms of the same element, but of different masses are called", "opta": "isobars", "optb": "isotones", "optc": "isotopes", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If pH value of an acidic solution is decreased from 5 to 2, then the increase in its hydrogen ion concentration is __________ times.", "opta": "10", "optb": "100", "optc": "1000", "optd": "10000", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Kopp's rule is concerned with the calculation of", "opta": "thermal conductivity.", "optb": "heat capacity.", "optc": "viscosity.", "optd": "surface tension.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Density of carbon dioxide is __________ kg/Nm3.", "opta": "44/22400", "optb": "44/22.4", "optc": "22.4/44", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "The effect of pressure on heat capacity of gases at pressure above one atmosphere and above the critical temperature is negligible.", "optb": "The value of Cp of gases increases with increase in pressure, above atmospheric pressure.", "optc": "The value of Cp at critical temperature and pressure reaches infinity.", "optd": "all (a), (b), and (c).", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In case of a ternery system involving two liquid components and a solute, the ratio of the concentration of the solute in the two phases at equilibrium is called the distribution co-efficient. The distribution co-efficient depends upon the", "opta": "solute concentration", "optb": "temperature", "optc": "both(a) & (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Solution made by dissolving equimolar amounts of different solutes in the same amount of a given solvent will have the", "opta": "same elevation in boiling point.", "optb": "different elevation in boiling point.", "optc": "elevation in boiling point in the ratio of their molecular weights.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "N2 content in a urea sample was found to be only 42%. What is the actual urea content of the sample ? (molecular weight of urea = 60)", "opta": "80%", "optb": "90%", "optc": "95%", "optd": "98%", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Specific gravity on API scale is given by the relation(where, G = specific gravity at 15.5\u00b0C).", "opta": "\u00b0API = 200(G - 1)", "optb": "\u00b0API = (141.5/G) - 131.5", "optc": "\u00b0API = (140/G) - 130", "optd": "\u00b0API = 145 - (145/G)", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S.T.P. corresponds to", "opta": "1 atm. absolute pressure & 15.5\u00b0C.", "optb": "760 mm Hg gauge pressure & 15.5\u00b0C.", "optc": "760 torr & 0\u00b0C.", "optd": "101.325 kPa gauge pressure & 15.5\u00b0C.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "With rise in pressure, the solubility of gases in solvent, at a fixed temperature", "opta": "increases", "optb": "decreases", "optc": "remains unchanged", "optd": "decreases linearly", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "'Reduced temperature' of a substance is the ratio of its existing temperature to its critical temperature, both expressed on celsius scale.", "optb": "'Reduced pressure' is the ratio of the existing pressure of a substance to its critical pressure.", "optc": "'Reduced volume' is the ratio of the existing molal volume of a substance to its critical molal volume.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Vapor pressure of water at 100\u00b0C is about __________ bar.", "opta": "0.1013", "optb": "1.013", "optc": "10.13", "optd": "101.3", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "At  room  temperature,  the  product [H+] [OH-] in a solution is   10-14 moles/litre.   If, [OH-] = 10-6 moles/litre, then the pH of the solution will be", "opta": "6", "optb": "8", "optc": "10", "optd": "12", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A solution is made by dissolving 1 kilo mole of solute in 2000 kg of solvent. The molality of the solution is", "opta": "2", "optb": "1", "optc": "0.5", "optd": "0.5", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Average molecular weight of air is about", "opta": "21", "optb": "29", "optc": "23", "optd": "79", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "6 gms of magnesium (atomic weight = 24), reacts with excess of an acid, the amount of H2 produced will be __________ gm.", "opta": "0.5", "optb": "1", "optc": "3", "optd": "5", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong unit conversion of calorific value.", "opta": "1 kcal/kg = 1.8 BTU/lb = 4.186 kJ/kg.", "optb": "1 BTU/ft3 = 8.9 kcal/m3 = 0.038 MJ/m3.", "optc": "1 BTU/lb = 2.3 kcal/kg.", "optd": "1 kcal/m3 = 0.1124 BTU/ft3.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Increasing the temperature of an aqueous solution will cause decrease in its", "opta": "molality", "optb": "mole fraction", "optc": "weight percent", "optd": "molarity", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The activity co-efficient of a solution, which accounts for the departure of liquid phase from ideal solution behaviour", "opta": "measures the elevation in boiling point.", "optb": "is not dependent on the temperature.", "optc": "is a function of the liquid phase composition.", "optd": "measures the depression in freezing point.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Osmotic pressure of a dilute solution of a non volatile solute in a solvent obeying Raoult's law is proportional to the", "opta": "temperature.", "optb": "volume of solution.", "optc": "moles of non-volatile solute.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In case of an unsaturated vapor-gas mixture, the humid volume increases with increase in the", "opta": "total pressure.", "optb": "absolute humidity at a given temperature.", "optc": "both (a) and (b).", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b).", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is an exothermic reaction ?", "opta": "Conversion of graphite to diamond", "optb": "Decomposition of water", "optc": "Dehydrogenation of ethane to ethylene", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Heat of solution in a system in which both solute and solvent are liquids is termed as", "opta": "heat of solvation.", "optb": "heat of hydration.", "optc": "standard integral heat of solution.", "optd": "heat of mixing.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "1 kgf/cm2  is not equal to", "opta": "1 torr", "optb": "1 bar", "optc": "10000 mm wc", "optd": "100 KPa = 100 000 N/m2", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "Heat capacity of a diatomic gas is higher than that of a monoatomic gas.", "optb": "Equal volumes of Argon and Krypton contain equal number of atoms.", "optc": "Total number of molecules contained in 22.4 litres of hydrogen at NTP is 6.023 x 1023.", "optd": "The binary mixture of a particular com-positidn in both vapor and liquid state is known as an azeotropic mixture", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "On addition of 1 c.c. of dilute hydrochloric acid (1% concentration) to 80 c.c. of a buffer solution of pH = 4, the pH of the solution becomes", "opta": "1", "optb": "8", "optc": "4", "optd": "2", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The weight fraction of methanol in an aqueous solution is 0.64. The mole fraction of methanol XM satisfies", "opta": "XM < 0.5", "optb": "XM = 0.5", "optc": "0.5 < XM < 0.64", "optd": "XM \u2265 0.64", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}]]}